- [Narrator] So continuing our discussion with form design,
we can also look at incorrect desegregations.
So in the previous form, we had an incorrect desegregation
because it actually wasn&#39;t meant to be collected at all.
But now when we&#39;re looking at this incorrect desegregation,
I mean, this is valid.
It should be collected.
But if you have a look at the total at the top,
we have desegregations of zero to 11 months,
12 to 59 months, five to 14 years and 15 years plus.
Pregnant women is a subset of 15 years plus.
So when we go to have our total,
we&#39;re going to have duplicates.
And this also becomes an issue in our data quality
because we&#39;re now counting twice
these pregnant women in our totals.
So this should not be there.
Maybe there should be separate variables for this,
or there should be a separate section
or whatever it might be the case.
But obviously when we do our configuration,
we can control this a bit, right?
&#39;Cause even if it&#39;s displayed on the form this way,
it doesn&#39;t mean we have to create
these desegregations this way.
We can always exclude that pregnant women
from the desegregation we applied to these data elements,
but you know, we still have that total column at the end,
which is a bit jarring in the sense that, you know,
the total for that row would not be correct by any means.
So this is something you have to work with,
the country to kind of design something
that makes a bit more sense within your tools,
because if you just have it the same way as it is,
it&#39;s not really going to serve the purpose
that you actually want it to do so,
as your conclusions about this will be incorrect
due to this duplicate counting.
So another challenge that we often have
is duplicate variables within the same form.
So this is a delivery data set,
and you might not notice it immediately,
but if you take the individual items
and start kind of adding them up
by their categorization,
which might not be immediately apparent,
then we can see that there&#39;s actually different values
reported by these different variables.
So if we look at, for example, in this case, delivery,
by nurse and delivery by midwife,
we can add these up to get the total number
of deliveries by the type of individual
that&#39;s supporting these deliveries,
the cadre essentially, right?
And then if we look at the bottom part of this,
delivery in facility, delivery in transit,
delivery in community, this is location, right?
So we add this total up and now we have different values.
And in any case, even if we had the same value,
we would have these same totals essentially,
we were able to calculate the same total
for the total number of deliveries
within that period from separate data elements,
probably you&#39;re going to have
some disparity between the two, right,
where the values are not going to be exactly the same.
And even if they are,
then you kind of have this duplicate data
just in your system, so in a lot of ways,
this is not ideal because if they are different,
which value do you use, right?
And if they are the same,
then you&#39;re just storing duplicate data.
And this might cause some confusion further down the line.
So another issue that you might have
are duplicate variables between different programs.
So on the left side, we have the PMTCT program within HIV.
And on the right side, we have the RMNCAH a program, right?
And if you have a look at some of this information,
then actually we can take,
it might not seem apparent immediately,
that&#39;s the thing with some of these challenges.
It&#39;s only when we start to have a closer look
at this information that where are we are able
to discern that they are actually the same value.
So in this case, if we look at alive but not HIV exposed,
right, these are our number of mothers that have,
who have HIV essentially.
And then we have the number of deliveries or sorry,
the mothers that do not have HIV, right?
There&#39;s 62 mothers.
And then if we look on the other side for the delivery data,
the number of deliveries by skilled health personnel is 62.
So actually these values in this case are duplicated.
Now it might not be immediately apparent
because the names are obviously not the same,
but the whole idea is that the PMTCT program
and the RMNCAH program in this case
are now recording the same exact value.
But they&#39;re just between different programs.
And we see this a lot of the time, right?
Particularly with things like delivery,
anti-natal care, kind of core services
where there&#39;s other denominators
that are calculated within that program,
that they need that service information,
even things like outpatient consultations,
but this becomes problematic now
because you have multiple sources of information
in your system and you no longer have
a way to control which one to use.
Because if you utilize the incorrect one
or utilize the one of your choosing,
then it might not be the correct value, right?
So anytime you use these, it causes some issues
down the line with your data quality.
You can also have, if you&#39;re using different denominations
in this case, for example,
any of these values are being used as a denominators.
They&#39;re no longer comparable across different programs
because you&#39;re using different denominators essentially.
So measuring these service statistics has some direct impact
on the quality of the information
that you are then presenting.
So the last kind of duplicate, we&#39;re going to look at,
are duplicate variables within the same program.
So this also happens, so if we look at this information
that we&#39;re presented with, on the left side,
we have HIV core data elements.
So data elements that are kind of core to the HIV program.
Within HIV, there&#39;s always a PMTCT program
of some kind, right, and that&#39;s on our right side.
And we&#39;re actually seeing the exact same data elements
are being collected between the two programs.
Now, once again, this might not be immediately apparent
because the names might not be exactly the same,
but they could be close.
So this is something that&#39;s also good to point out.
So on the left side, our HIV core,
we have anti-natal client tested for HIV,
and this is essentially equivalent
to PMTCT tested for HIV on our right side.
This is also true for antenatal client HIV positive
on the left side for HIV core,
when we compare this on the right side
to PMTCT anti-natal client HIV positive.
So these two data elements actually represent
the same piece of information.
And this happens sometimes even within the same program.
Now this could be true, even for tracker data,
where information is being collected
across different programs and the same information
then aggregating to be representing the same value,
but it&#39;s being collected in different places.
So while we are focusing on aggregate information,
this sometimes does happen within tracker data as well,
where different programs are collecting information
that eventually leads to calculation of the same value.
So this is something that we have to be careful of
anytime we have these duplicates essentially,
because we&#39;re not sure what the source is for this program
or for the health system or for wherever it is
that you&#39;re analyzing this information.
And to clean this up and rectify this
can be a significant piece of work,
particularly if there is a lot of ownership
over this information.
So in many cases, because it might be the case
where this has been happening for a number of years,
I mentioned at the beginning, in many cases,
you know, we can think about when we introduce,
this whole idea of revising forms,
it&#39;s a long-term kind of process.
It&#39;s not something that happens immediately.
And you know, a lot of you would have been involved in this,
I think in your own implementations in any case,
but we have some power to affect this now
with the introduction of these WTO packages, right,
where we&#39;re trying to introduce kind of standards,
trying to make sure there&#39;s not all these duplicates
within or between different programs, but you know,
it can still happen of course,
but at least we have some way to kind of fall back
on best practice and point to some areas
where we might wanna rectify this
going forward in the future.
Because at present, if you look at this,
it might be hard in practicality to fix this,
immediately in particular, but going forward,
I think this is where you can have a lot more influence
and kind of change the way things are done
to kind of standardize this
and rationalize this information essentially.