(gentle upbeat music)
- [Instructor] In this video I&#39;m going to present
how to use the consistency data tab of the dashboard
of the WHO Data Quality tool.
Let&#39;s click on the consistency data tab.
For the presentation,
let&#39;s set data to core, periods to June,
and organization units to national,
with this aggregation to district.
Set this way.
The screens that you will see
will match up with the screenshots in the guide.
We can enlarge the chart
by making the settings window disappear.
And let&#39;s scroll down and look at the charts
that appear on the consistency data tab.
There are three of them.
There are two scatter plots
and then a third chart that shows a series of histograms
or bar charts with a bar for each district.
Let&#39;s begin by looking at the two scatter plots.
The first of these compares
the district value of ANC first visits
to the district value of ANC fourth visits.
Again, with a scatter plot like this,
each dot represents the values for one district.
And you see that for most districts,
there is a relationship between ANC first visits
and ANC fourth visits that is represented by this dark line.
That isn&#39;t to say that ANC 1 is close to ANC 4
just that the ratio of between these two values
follows a slope that is given by this black line.
For example, if a district had 40,000 ANC first visits,
then it&#39;s likely to have somewhere
around 7,500 ANC fourth visits.
And most of the districts in the country
follow this relationship.
And therefore most of the districts have dots
that fall between these two gray lines.
There is however, an exception.
You see this diamond shape dot again for District B-2,
which had far more ANC first visits
during this 12 month period,
far more ANC first visits than ANC fourth visits.
In fact, if we look at that,
it is perhaps 20 times as many ANC first visits
as ANC fourth visits.
Whereas the districts down here may have
only five times as many ANC first visits
as ANC fourth visits.
Now let&#39;s think about it.
District B-2 we&#39;ve seen this district appear before,
and in fact, when we looked at the consistency time charts,
we saw that there was a facility in District B-2
which had greatly over reported ANC first visits
in January of 2020.
So we have a pretty good explanation for why it is
that ANC first visits might be so much greater
than ANC fourth visits
that this might be the result of the same error
made in the reporting of ANC first visits.
Let&#39;s scroll down to the second scatter plot.
And this shows the relationship of ANC first visits
this time to the number of first doses of Penta vaccine.
Well, you may be surprised at first
that there is any relationship at all,
but if you were told that this was a country
where in almost every district,
more than 90% of pregnant women
got at least one anti-natal care visit
and more than 90% of eligible infants
got their first dose of Penta vaccine,
you might begin to understand
why the number of ANC first visits for a district
is pretty closely related to
the number of first doses of Penta to the vaccine.
And you see that for almost all districts,
this relationship is followed closely.
And again, there are certain exceptions.
Here&#39;s another exception.
But the diamond shaped dot up here
is once again for District B-2.
And we ask ourselves,
why is the number of first antenatal care visits
for District B-2 so much greater
than the number of first two doses of Penta vaccine?
Well, perhaps you can answered the question yourself by now.
But each of these diamond shaped dots
is worthy of some investigation
because the relationship between antenatal care first visits
and Penta first doses
doesn&#39;t follow what we see in these other districts.
Finally, we come to this last chart,
which is not a scatterplot,
but is a histogram showing one bar for each district.
And for most districts, the bars are blue.
These bars are showing the dropout rate
between Penta 1 and Penta 3.
What is the dropout rate?
The dropout rate is simply the percentage of infants
who got their first dose of Penta vaccine,
but who did not return for their third dose.
So since an infant needs to receive their first dose,
before they can receive their third dose,
we expect the dropout rate to be positive.
That is we expect the number of first doses of Penta vaccine
to be greater than the number of third doses.
But look here,
there are two districts where the dropout rate is negative
District A-2 and District A-3.
In both of these districts,
the number of third doses of Penta vaccine
was greater than the number of first doses of Penta vaccine
during the 12 month period shown here.
This warrants some further investigation,
is it because of over-reporting of third doses of Penta
by a single health facility,
which greatly over-reported third doses of Penta vaccine?
Or is it because many health facilities
in one of these districts or both of these districts
are consistently over reporting of Penta three doses?
We cannot answer the question with the dashboard.
We will see later how we can use the analysis function
and the data quality tool to investigate further
the phenomenon of negative dropout in these two districts.
(gentle upbeat music)