- [Narrator] So I wanted to spend a bit of time
discussing category options, categories,
category combinations, category option combinations,
category option groups and category option group sets.
Now that is a pretty big mouthful,
but actually, this model that we use to desegregate our data
has a lot of pitfalls if it&#39;s not managed correctly.
This is something I think a lot of us
have a direct impact in influencing
because we&#39;re often helping people set up their systems,
deal with this, set up standard operating procedures
to create their metadata and often
being the ones to have to fix this problem
when it is eventually noticed.
What you&#39;ll see here in this example
that I&#39;m going to go through with you
is that we have a category option
of five years and above
and a category option of five years plus.
So these individual category options
are duplicates of one another.
And this can create a lot of havoc later on,
as you&#39;ll see as we go through the model for this.
So what happens in this scenario?
So I have these two category options.
Now I&#39;m going to assign those to different categories,
to different category combinations.
This is going to result
in different category option combinations being generated
based upon those category options.
Now where this becomes challenging
is when they&#39;re completely different.
So they have different IDs.
So what you&#39;ll see here
is there&#39;s a group of category option combinations
in this green square that are the same,
but you can see the name is identical across all of them.
What has happened is a category option
is used in multiple category combinations essentially.
And this is generated, you still have to be
a bit careful here because you want to make sure
that you&#39;re storing your data in the right place.
So this has a big impact on data exchange for example,
when you wanna move data from maybe one system to another,
or you&#39;re importing data, whatever it is that you&#39;re doing,
because you wanna make sure that you&#39;re looking up
the appropriate category option combination
that&#39;s associated with the proper category combination
that&#39;s tied to your data element.
Now the reason you wanna get this right
is because when you bring in that data, you know,
if you bring it into the wrong category option combination,
then the data will not be correct at all.
And you will have to kind of go through a different process.
And of course, if you&#39;re always selecting
different category combinations
that are associated with category option combinations,
you&#39;ll have the same problem.
So let&#39;s stick with the orange bars, the orange boxes,
five years and above and five years plus.
Now what&#39;s in this green box, this is okay,
it&#39;s the exact same name, it&#39;s associated
with different category combinations essentially.
But these two ones in the orange boxes,
these are problematic, they&#39;re problematic,
both from any kind of data exchange standpoint,
where you&#39;re trying to bring in data
or even just store the data, you know,
because you might have then your data split
between these two, even though they should be
exactly the same.
And then they&#39;re also a problem
from the analysis point of view.
Which one do I select when I want to review my data?
Am I selecting the wrong one?
So on top of creating a host of data quality issues,
because now you&#39;re storing what is the similar object
in two different places basically,
the data is spread amongst these two
category option combinations.
Then you have this problem
where you&#39;re not even sure which one to select.
So what we can do, so I mentioned earlier
this concept of category option groups and group sets.
When I talked about desegregations collapsing,
that previous example was when zero
to one and one to four collapsed to less than five.
In this scenario, we can also take
our disparate category option combinations
and use category auction groups and group sets
in order to kind of at least for the user,
hide this problem.
So what we can do is we can create two
category option groups, one that is less than five
and one that is greater than or equal to five.
In our system, we&#39;re lucky enough that the under five years
does not have duplicates.
So there&#39;s no less than five something with a symbol
or something written out with the words less than,
and then five or whatever it might be.
There&#39;s only one under five, but for five years and above,
we have these two copies of each other.
And from the user&#39;s perspective,
what we can do is we can hide this entirely.
So this is something we can kind of help and support.
Now, maybe it was in the past this was done.
Maybe this is something that was, you know,
when we&#39;re supporting that configuration happened over time.
Maybe there was a lack of coordination,
whatever the reasoning behind this,
and this is often, you know,
something that does happen in practice,
there is a way at least to hide it from the user.
We just have to be very careful, of course,
when we&#39;re bringing in data or storing data
or whatever we&#39;re doing with that data
to make sure it&#39;s associated
with the right category option combination.
But let&#39;s have a look at this again, right?
So we create these two category option groups,
and this might be kind of a new concept
and I&#39;ll go over the actual example of this.
So we create these two category option groups,
and then we create what we call a category option group set,
which is comprised
of the category option groups that we create.
So let&#39;s actually go into DHIS2
so we can get a better idea
of what it is that we&#39;re talking.
Okay, let&#39;s have a look
at the example that I&#39;m discussing.
I&#39;m in the category option group
maintenance part of the app.
So I&#39;m going to go to less than five.
This is the first category option group that I created.
If I scroll down, we can see that I&#39;ve added
one category option, under five years,
this is basically a duplicate
of the under five years category option
that already exists in our system,
but we&#39;re not able to create category option group sets
based on category options alone.
So we have to kind of replicate it
in order to get the process to be the same as before.
I&#39;ll just go back and I&#39;ll go to my greater than
or equal to five.
So we can see here, I&#39;ve added the two category options
that are copies of each other.
These are duplicate category options.
And what I want to do is I basically want to hide
the fact that there are duplicate category options
in this particular system, right?
So I don&#39;t want the user to have any idea
that this exists basically.
So what I do, I create these two category option groups,
and then I create the category option group set.
So we can see here,
less than five and greater than or equal to five.
Okay, so I&#39;ll just go down here and we can see here,
you select from your available category option groups,
not your category options.
So that&#39;s why we have to create
individual category, option groups,
even if they contain same information
that&#39;s present in our category options.
You know, it&#39;s not the easiest process.
It&#39;s not the easiest process to understand certainly.
And you require a lot of experience
with the category model to understand this, but you know,
it&#39;s something we can do to help users
from seeing these particular problems
that exist in our database.
Now, because I&#39;ve selected this as a data dimension here,
let me just open up data visualizer.
Now you can see that I have this dimension here,
less than five, greater than or equal to five.
And when I click on this, you&#39;ll see
there&#39;s only two options there.
Even though we know in this group,
greater than or equal to five,
we actually have two category options,
two category option groups
associated with this particular group set.
So what we&#39;re seeing here is the group set, right?
And it&#39;s comprised of these kind of groups, right?
So this is a group set here, and these are our groups.
So this hides from the user completely,
the fact that there are two separate under five, or sorry,
two separate, greater than or equal to fives in our system.
And we can use this to then desegregate our data
without worrying about which one should I be using
for which data element, right?
It&#39;s something maybe that should be fixed in the future,
but this allows for a temporary fix to take place
in order to kind of hide this,
mask this from the user essentially.