- [Instructor] So in this discussion,
we&#39;re going to talk about DHIS2 system design
and how it affects data quality.
We&#39;re going to go through a couple of different topics
and we&#39;ll split this up into multiple sessions
just to kind of have these segmented by thematic area.
In this presentation,
we&#39;re going to discuss a couple of different ways
we can look at the inputs of our DHIS2 system
and how this ends up affecting data quality.
So the first thing we&#39;re going to look at is form design.
And I will just emphasize that we&#39;re talking about
aggregate form design in this scenario.
There&#39;s a lot about tracker that can also be discussed,
but in this particular case, just due to time restrictions,
we&#39;re not going to focus on that too much.
However, when we get to the other parts of the discussion,
database and metadata design
and the functions to assess databases and metadata design,
we will be discussing tracker as well.
So the other topics we have for database and metadata design
and functions to assess databases and metadata design,
first, we&#39;ll talk about the databases and metadata design
a little bit, in a little bit of detail,
and actually I&#39;ve separated this out
into two separate components.
The first thing that I&#39;m going to talk about is things that
we more or less have some control over.
So some customization challenges that we actually can modify
and have a great deal of impact on usability of the system
in terms of reviewing data and getting the data we need.
Then the second part of this is some challenges that we
have a little less control over currently,
just based upon the limitations of
the DHIS2 maintenance app.
So there&#39;s a lot of things we might be able to do
to get around this,
maybe running SQL queries
or accessing things through the API
and making modifications that way.
But then, if we&#39;re trying to build long-term capacity,
it becomes quite challenging to do this
if there&#39;s no real good way to do some things in DHIS2
to deal with some of these issues.
Lastly, we&#39;re going to talk about functions
to assess databases and metadata design.
So we&#39;re actually going to discuss some ways to deal with
these problems or at least assess these problems.
We&#39;re going to be presenting a number of problems, actually,
over the course of this discussion.
And we do want to kind of also provide some tools
to actually rectify the situation
when you find something that&#39;s wrong.
Okay, so the first kind of session that we&#39;ll have
is focusing on aggregate form design.
And we&#39;re going to talk about
a couple of different things here.
First, we&#39;ll talk about poor form source design.
So, when you&#39;re actually having a paper form that
really has a lot of problems with it and what you do.
And we&#39;re actually going to talk about
a couple of different kinds of aspects of this
as we go through the session.
We&#39;re going to talk about incorrect disaggregations
on these forms as well as duplicate variables
and duplicate variables happen
in a lot of different scenarios.
This includes within the same form itself,
across different forms, between different programs,
and across different forms in the same program itself.
So we&#39;ll break each of these down
as we go through this discussion.
So the first thing I&#39;m going to talk about
is just some basics on poor form source design in general.
And if we look at this form,
it&#39;s a form that&#39;s collecting delivery services,
essentially, antenatal care delivery parity
and have a look at the disaggregations.
Just think for a second what might be off
when you look at this form.
So this is based on a real paper form.
This is not something I just made up
for the sake of providing a poor example.
But if we have a look,
we have male here recorded for all these services
and that doesn&#39;t make any sense at all, right?
So we cannot actually record anything
for the male sex disaggregation.
So it shouldn&#39;t be there.
We don&#39;t need the sex disaggregation applied
to these age disaggregations at all.
And the problem with this,
it results in data being entered
that is subsequently incorrect, right?
So we might have information entered for males,
and we&#39;re not actually sure what to do with that.
Is this an incorrect value?
Should this go in the female disaggregation?
Should this be removed entirely?
And what happens in this scenario is,
we&#39;re not actually sure when we go to review
our data quality, why our numbers look incorrect,
or we&#39;re just reviewing our data and we&#39;re not actually
even aware of how this is affecting our final output.
And we&#39;re just kind of reporting the values that have been
recorded in that female disaggregation
and not really doing anything with the values
that have been recorded in that male disaggregation.
So it&#39;s just something to be wary of
when we&#39;re thinking about how we design systems
and how this affects our final data output, actually,
because it can have quite a deleterious effect
on our information because just giving us the wrong output,
the wrong values, our data quality is affected.
Our outputs are all affected with wrong values, essentially.