- [Narrator] So another area that I feel
we have quite a bit of control over
in terms of making recommendations
and supporting countries, as well as transferring
skills to, is in dataset design.
So in a lot of these things that I&#39;ve shown,
I don&#39;t have the answers necessarily
on how to fix everything, but at least, you know,
you can show countries for example,
what to do or how to identify duplicate data elements,
how to take categories, category options,
and collapse them, et cetera.
So these are within our control in a certain way, right?
I think that data set design is also something
we can have quite a large impact on.
We also, you know, on top of implementing best practices,
we now have these WTO digital data packages
to also fall back upon in scenarios
to kind of refer to and say, well,
what about considering this approach
based on what we&#39;ve seen in those packages?
But what we can do,
the first thing that I wanna talk about
is graying out cells.
And this is a very simple and effective way
to prevent people from entering data.
And I think the majority of you would have interacted
with this in some way and already know how to do this,
but when I&#39;m creating a data set, you know,
if I have a whole list of desegregations
and the majority of my data elements
are associated with particular category option combo,
you know, and I just wanna maintain that,
but the desegregation doesn&#39;t apply
maybe to a small subset of data elements
and they shouldn&#39;t be reporting on that basically,
then I can gray out these cells basically,
and I can make it such that people don&#39;t enter data
into those boxes.
Now, of course, this is taking into account
that you can do this with, you know,
a second based form for example.
If you&#39;re using a HTML based form,
of course you can also block that off,
just might have to go about doing it in a different way.
But the whole idea is to prevent people
from entering data where they shouldn&#39;t be entering data.
So sometimes you might use these desegregations
and it might not apply in all cases,
but in this example, you know,
if I had this OPV zero, for example,
and I didn&#39;t apply the same desegregation,
I just had it as a default data element,
because I&#39;m using a section based form for example,
I wouldn&#39;t be able to have that OPB zero data element
appear listed with all my other vaccinations.
So this can cause some challenges
with the user interface as well.
And we have to think about it from that perspective as well.
How are people going to actually enter that data?
So pass graying cells, I&#39;m not gonna harp on this too much,
&#39;cause I think a lot of you have a lot of experience
with the data set design already.
But the main thing is, it&#39;s kind of a summarization
of everything that we&#39;ve talked about so far, right?
If the source form itself is problematic,
that&#39;s something you should have a look at.
If categories and desegregations are problematic,
that&#39;s also something you should have a look at.
We can make and customize things in DHIS2
to a large extent, but development
of standard operating procedures and other types of tools
that allow us to reflect upon what we&#39;re doing
are really strongly recommended.
If you have a look at this form,
we can see a number of different problems
associated with it.
I mean, the layout itself is not ideal.
We have a full list of age desegregations
and then at the end, cases and deaths by sex.
Now the whole problem with this,
I mean, this is one of my favorite examples
because I think I&#39;ve seen it in nearly every system
that I&#39;ve worked in.
Desegregation of cases and deaths,
and people make categories of this.
Now this doesn&#39;t make any sense at all, right?
Other than saving you some time,
because you don&#39;t wanna make individual data elements
for cases versus deaths.
But cases plus deaths doesn&#39;t give you
any meaningful total at all, right.
And then, you know, separately at the end of this form,
we have more desegregations,
just for the sake of having them.
So there are some things
that we can influence, I think, right?
So we have the ability to look at things
in a bit of detail and try to influence, well,
how are people going to utilize this data?
Because if I add up the totals for this, does it make sense?
Is it going to be easy for people
to find what they need to break this down
and desegregate this information?
Can I modify user interfaces,
either by selecting the appropriate data dimensions
or by making the form easier to interact with
when they&#39;re entering their data?
It&#39;s a lot of different things
that we have some control over, and we can influence
quite a bit in terms of using, you know,
what we know from our own knowledge and experience,
and reflecting upon this with our partners
and with countries that we&#39;re supporting.
So just keep some of these things in mind
as you&#39;re kind of going through different things.
Of course, there has been a large focus
on aggregate data, and many of you have maybe moved on
and are really, you know,
the aggregate implementation is so mature
that this is something that&#39;s been processed to death.
And you&#39;re probably thinking more about tracker data,
but I think that there&#39;s a lot of things
we can still kind of take from this,
to influence our tracker data as well.
All the stuff we talked about having duplicate data elements
across different programs within the same form
and within the same program,
you know, that all applies still.
And even when we&#39;re then making program indicators for this,
we have to be a bit smart about how we create them.
So we&#39;re not creating a bunch of program indicators
that are difficult to interpret and understand and utilize.
So what we&#39;ve talked to a lot about data input,
we could imagine this as data outputs as well.
So come at it from these two different inflection points
and think about, you know, how we can utilize that data
and what impact this has on the quality of that information.
For the most part, many of these challenges
that I&#39;ve shown, that we have some ability to influence
and also train people to identify, you know,
they really have a strong effect on data quality.
So if this is something we can impart to others,
you know, then we&#39;re making some good steps
in terms of improving our systems.