- [Instructor] So that&#39;s where the next page
of the configuration dashboard comes in,
the configuration tool comes in
and that is to change these thresholds.
So I&#39;m gonna show you how that&#39;s done, more administration.
This page is really quite complex and a bit overwhelming.
Fortunately, the tool does a good job
of filling it in by default.
So if you leave the default settings,
then that usually works pretty well.
Now what I&#39;m looking for and completeness,
I&#39;m looking for how to reset the thresholds
or data consistency.
Maybe it was under numerator relations.
Oh yeah.
Okay, sorry.
That&#39;s 10% I was talking about.
It isn&#39;t set with the numerator quality parameters.
It is actually set in numerator relations
and notice here that when you fill this in,
that&#39;s when you set this, when I set it to 10%.
So by default it says 10%.
I&#39;m gonna loosen this and set the threshold to 30%
and let&#39;s see what we find when we change this threshold.
We go back to the dashboard and consistency data.
Now we&#39;ve got a wider set of thresholds
for consistency between ANC 1 and Penta 1.
And there&#39;s only the single only bow
as ANC first visit number.
Again, this is set for last 12 months.
So ANC is much greater than,
the ANC 1 much greater than Penta 1.
And these other districts are not flagged
as having outlier values.
That&#39;s how you set the thresholds for numerator relations.
You actually do it when you complete the form.
And maybe even with dropout, well dropout rate,
you don&#39;t set a threshold, but with each one of these,
you can decide what to set the threshold at.
For example, I like to adjust the threshold
so that you have only
a small manageable number of districts
which are flagged as having outliers
so that you can easily follow up
on that small manageable number of districts.
But other aspects of these quality parameters are set here
and there are so many aspects.
And in a moment, we&#39;ll share a PowerPoint presentation
that Nick has developed just briefly shift points to it
to help you understand what is meant
by expected trend constant versus increasing decreasing
compare with overall result versus expected result.
That&#39;s what the PowerPoint will go into.
What I&#39;m going to show you is how even the definition
of what is an outlier using standard Z scores,
you can change that in the tool.
And as an example with malaria cases,
you might find that because malaria is seasonal,
you want to pick up only quite extreme values for malaria.
So you could change the definition of a moderate outlier
to three standard deviations and the severe extreme outlier
to four standard deviations.
So this is something in your spare time to play around with.
And just one tip that I have about setting these parameters.
What I like to do is even though I,
sometimes I&#39;m not quite understanding
what the distinction is
between expected results and overall result.
I like to just play around with these,
go into numerator quality parameters
and see how it affects the dashboard.
Is the reference line going through mode,
most of the dots or is the reference line misplaced?
For example, if we, let&#39;s with IPT.
Let&#39;s go to quality parameters.
And if we set this to expected results
and we looked at the dashboard, it&#39;s not a core.
Okay, it&#39;s not a core because it&#39;s a malaria indicator.
Okay, yeah so this is what I was doing.
Notice how when it&#39;s set to expected result,
the line is below all these dots.
So what I like to do is as I say,
play around with the quality parameters.
And if we change this back to expected result,
oh, I forgot something.
This is, if you like, it&#39;s a bug of the tool.
Most parts of the configuration you don&#39;t have to save,
but this page you have to save or you don&#39;t see the effects.
So let&#39;s see if this has changed the situation.
Okay well, so now it&#39;s still below.
I&#39;m just gonna persist with this once more
and then I&#39;ll move on or pause for questions.
Let&#39;s see.
So I&#39;ve saved.
All right.
Oh, no, I&#39;m sorry.
I forgot to set that (indistinct)
Now, okay.
So we find that indeed overall results produces
the reference line which passes through most of the dots.
We assume that most of the dots
are the appropriate relationship.
And we just have a couple of outliers of suspicious numbers.
So I&#39;ll point too and maybe Nick wants to say something
about the presentation.
Do you see the PowerPoint presentation on the screen now?
- [Nick] Yep, yes.
I mean, I don&#39;t think we&#39;ll get
into too much detail on that presentation.
It&#39;s just there for your reference.
It kind of explains the link
between some of these numerator quality presenters
and their effect then on, in particular,
the analysis functions.
So there is some stuff in the analysis functions
we didn&#39;t go over in too much detail,
but just some of these terms that you see
in their expected results or overall results,
as well as increasing and decreasing
when you&#39;re setting these thresholds
as well as all the different analysis
that you could perform and basically just goes over
the effect of what you&#39;re doing on this.
So just real quick you had expected an overall result.
Expected result is kind of a theoretical result.
It&#39;s usually if you&#39;re, for example,
if I&#39;m doing an analysis over time, maybe I expect them.
If there are two variables that are comparing
the ratio, maybe should be one, right?
Maybe they&#39;re equal.
But then there&#39;s an observed result
and actual results right?
Not my theoretical actual result at your national level.
So that&#39;s the observed results, right?
Where you&#39;re actually seeing, okay,
if I compare two values at the national level,
what is my observed result?
And then I can take all the districts
or facilities or whatever and compare them
to that observed result.
So it&#39;s just kind of a, you know,
the tool does various things to model information,
pieces of information for you to kind of compare
and contrast how things are.
And sometimes this modeling
is based on ideal scenarios, right?
So you might not accurately reflect
what you&#39;re observing in reality.
So that&#39;s kind of the briefly,
the difference between this observed and expected results.
Just reviewing in a theoretical value
versus a actual observed value based on values
in your system.
I don&#39;t know where that theoretical value can help.
Obviously is where your data
is just completely stuck, right?
So if you have a lot of problems with your data
and then the observed result does not give you value,
you know, there&#39;s no added value in comparing districts
to that observed value because there&#39;s significant issues
with the data quality that you&#39;re already aware of.
That&#39;s where that theoretical value for the expected results
would be better to use.
But in any case, I think this is a bit of a
that way down in the weeds about how to look at this.
You know, you can have a look if you&#39;re interested
and I&#39;m happy to speak to anyone
who has any follow up about this,
but I don&#39;t wanna detract from the overall discussion.
So you can just have a look at the session in leisure
and we can talk about this more if you have any questions.
- [Instructor] Yeah, thanks Nick.
And if nothing else,
I encourage you to play around with those who have access
to the configuration of the tool.
See what happens when you change these parameters.
What happens to the chart?
And once you have figured out
what gives you the most useful chart,
then you can just leave that setting there
and not feel like you have to explain
to people about what the, what these parameters mean.
These thresholds for completeness and timeliness,
they don&#39;t actually appear on the dashboard.
These are thresholds that will appear in the annual report
that can be generated automatically.
And we&#39;ve covered a good deal of topics here.
And I want to have a moment of silence if nothing else,
to encourage someone to raise their hand
and ask about any of these issues.
This comparison of one data element to another program,
people often find this very attractive feature.
And instead of adding more comparisons to the dashboard,
what you can encourage them to do
is learn how to use the analysis function,
analysis, consistency and once they figure out
how to set this up, then how to find
the data element that they&#39;re most interested in.
So we&#39;re going to, let&#39;s see.
Then they can do analysis to their heart&#39;s content.
So for me, it&#39;s a way of relieving pressure
on configuration of the dashboard
&#39;cause you want the dashboard to run efficiently
and it won&#39;t.
I&#39;m not sure how I selected by accident
acute flaccid paralysis
but there&#39;s no relationship between treatment of pneumonia
and acute flaccid paralysis which shouldn&#39;t surprise us.
But the point is that there&#39;s no limits to the analysis
that can be done with the analysis tool.
Unfortunately, there&#39;s no way to save this configuration.
And hopefully with a future version
of the data quality tool, there, there will be favorites.
So this can be in a certain group of favorites
of the child health group, and then others can easily,
without going through all these steps
of hunting for the data element,
they can generate the comparison and look at the
and drill down all of the things
that we talked about on Monday
with the using the analysis function.