- [Man] So mapping reference numerators.
It is not always easy to identify the best data element.
Why not?
In principle, you just find the data element group
and then in the group you select the indicator
or the data elements rather.
So in principle, it&#39;s as easy as falling out of bed
in the morning.
But let&#39;s go on.
Okay. Why?
Challenge number one is this is not so unusual.
This is a national instance that has 8,000 data elements.
So finding the right data element
is the proverbial needle in the haystack.
So let me go to the next point.
You may find yourself in searching,
and this is searching in the Pivot Table app,
for
just the right one.
And we use the search function, all data elements.
In the Pivot Table app you can do all data elements.
So you could, and I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve done this yourself,
search for all of the data elements
that are related to DPT.
This isn&#39;t possible, again, within the Data Quality tool.
So you have to do some homework in advance
and use some other app like the Pivot Table app
to find just the right data element.
Okay. Of course,
one way of dealing with this proliferation of data elements
is to form groups or either a data element group
or an indicator group.
This is even an essential step
for configuration of the Data Quality tool,
because if your data element has not already been
assigned to a group, as I said before,
you&#39;re not going to be able to grab hold of it
when configuring the Data Quality tool dashboard.
So your data element needs to be in a group
and ideally your group should have
just a limited number of data elements in it.
I comment here about data element groups.
I have started,
when working and supporting configuration,
I&#39;ve started to form a
special group called Data Quality
and I put into that data element group
all of the numerators
that I think the ministry is interested in reviewing.
Hopefully that list is not too large
and this is where we advocate
for encouraging the ministry
to identify a small number of data elements
and indicators that they want to look at.
If you&#39;ve got 8,000 data elements
and 5,000 indicators,
there is absolutely no way
that you can keep informed about quality issues
with thousands of data elements and indicators.
So an essential step, absolutely essential
is that the ministry makes some decision about
a group of, let&#39;s say, at most 50 indicators
that they want to be tracking
the programs.
Now
the tuberculosis program, if they have data and VHIS too,
they may say, &quot;Well sorry, we want to look at more than 50.&quot;
So maybe each program in addition would have its own list
of 30 that it wants to look at.
So this is an essential governance step
that the ministry has to go through in deciding
what are these core indicators, to use the word core
in a somewhat different since,
and I don&#39;t know, Nick, do you have any other words
of advice on how we address this bottleneck
and people selecting the indicator lists
that are most important?
- [Nick] No, I think it&#39;s just,
some of this comes down to the database design obviously.
We&#39;ll talk about that more potentially later on.
But I think you&#39;ve covered the pertinent points.
It&#39;s just basically can be quite difficult to manage
because the tool itself has its limitations
in how you map things and then of course the database
on top of this, whichever database that you&#39;re using,
will have its own limitations and how things are organized
and they&#39;re often not optimal.
- [Man] Yeah. Yeah.
So indeed,
we&#39;re touching on design issues.
Are the groups optimally configured
to support easy use
and that&#39;s a bigger issue.
It also comes in with analysis.
The users who wants to
configure a chart or a table,
they need to be able to easily find
just the right data element.
I don&#39;t know other than to suggest that they
convene a meeting where they say, &quot;Okay, we know it&#39;s
very hard to select our favorite 50, but
we&#39;re going to lock the door
and you&#39;re not allowed to leave the room.&quot;
Who&#39;s going to be in the room?
The HMIS unit,
some representatives of programs,
maybe some representatives of districts.
Because if you don&#39;t focus your Data Quality desk review
you&#39;re not going to hit on the most important issues.
Okay. So to move along.
Numerator only indicator.
So here&#39;s this example.
Here we are actually in the maintenance app,
this screenshot.
And here&#39;s a country, in fact, this was
the instance we used on Monday,
here&#39;s the country where third doses of DPT-3
that are delivered from a fixed site, a static site,
that&#39;s a separate data element from,
I&#39;ve even defined this wrong I realize,
this should be a three here.
So I made a mistake
in configuring DPT-3 doses given.
In fact, that&#39;s the next slide.
But imagine this is DPT-3 from outreach.
So what you have to do is a step in configuring the tool
is to exit the tool,
go to the maintenance app,
go to the indicators function,
and define this new numerator only.
We call it a numerator only indicator because
the denominator for it is going to be one.
And it&#39;s simply to add together the fixed in the outreach.
That&#39;s the point of challenge number three.
And when you grab a hold of an existing indicator,
especially with tuberculosis, not unfrequently,
you come across indicators like this.
It requires a very painstaking process
to define this properly.
I&#39;m sure you&#39;re much more familiar with this than me,
having configured a lot of indicators.
The administrator has to sit down
with the tuberculosis people who understand
this great variety of TB indicators,
and with extreme attention to detail,
make sure that the indicator
is properly defined because in the end,
if what you&#39;re reviewing with the tool
is an indicator that isn&#39;t even properly defined,
then you&#39;ve wasted your time.
You want to review the quality
of a properly defined indicator.
Full stop.
Okay.
Another challenge of the process.
If you want to look at the quality of HIV data,
well, often the instance doesn&#39;t have the HIV data
or the TB data.
Sometimes the instance won&#39;t have hospital data
on inpatient care,
on human resources.
Very few instances have the staffing data there
or the logistics information.
So what do you do if you want to look for extreme outliers
in these other datasets?
Well, you&#39;ve got a couple of choices.
I like the DHIS2 Data Quality tool.
One solution, that&#39;s the second bullet,
is to take the HIV data and import it
into the DHIS2.
Take the aggregate data and bring it into DHIS2
and then you can use the Data Quality tool.
I remember one country that really
had its own data management system.
And we had an academy there,
the December before last, I think it was,
and the director of the HMIS unit was so impressed
at the power of the Data Quality tool
that she wanted to know how to code the tool
into their own data management software.
And I said, &quot;Well, why don&#39;t you simply import the data
into DHIS2?&quot;
I don&#39;t know whether she followed up on that advice or not.
Frequently when you demonstrate the tool
to high-level officials, they&#39;ll love it.
They&#39;ll say, &quot;This is what we need.&quot;
Okay. And then the other solution.
WHO has an Excel tool
that allows you to look for outliers
and look for all of these aspects of consistency
but it doesn&#39;t have anywhere near the flexibility.
You can&#39;t drill down.
But the point is that in some cases for these other datasets
that are missing, if you have district aggregate data
by month
or by quarter in the case of TB data,
then you can, if you format it properly,
you can load it into the Excel tool
and then you can look for these aspects of inconsistency.
I am not keeping an eye on the clock here.
How many minutes do we have?
- [Nick] Yeah. About 10 minutes.
- [Man] Okay.
Another challenge
you may find
and I found this in several national instances,
that there&#39;s more than one data element
that appears to be
for the same thing.
So here&#39;s an actual example where,
in the Pivot Table app, I&#39;ve used the search function,
the search window to look for DPT-3
and I found two different data elements
that appear to be for pinto one doses.
And if you&#39;re not careful, when you configure the app,
you may map it to a data element that&#39;s empty.
In this case, outside of the tool,
what you need to do is
a bit of investigation
and that&#39;s what the next slide shows.
Here, what I&#39;ve done is I&#39;ve used the data visualizer
to look at the data for these two different
data elements for pinto one doses, DPT-1 doses,
and I added in here the targets
just to know
just for comparison.
And what I found when I did this
is that there&#39;s the green data element,
which looks very similar to the blue one,
is empty.
There there&#39;s hardly any data for it.
And then you&#39;ve got to write down this
and carefully make sure when you do the configuration
that you grab hold of that right data, correct data element.
Another challenge here
is when you are
selecting indicators or data elements
that you want to include on the dashboard,
ideally, you would be using data elements
which had a high level of completeness.
If you put on the dashboard
an indicator or a data element from a dataset
where only half of facilities are reporting,
or even higher, if it&#39;s 70% of facilities,
you will almost always find
the data are highly inconsistent.
So in a way you don&#39;t even need to bother to use
the Data Quality tool
if the completeness is below 70% or 80%
because you&#39;re going to find so much inconsistency in there.
And the real fundamental problem has to do
with the reporting rate with the completeness.
But in this case,
we want to look at anti-natal care
and yet the data set
that is for anti-natal care coverage
has quite a low reporting rate.
So it&#39;s the best data element we can use.
It&#39;s imperfect.
The reporting rate is low.
But all the same,
we&#39;ll go ahead and we&#39;ll include it
on the dashboard
because there&#39;s no alternative data elements
available in the DHIS and this is the data
which the ministry is using to track
anti-natal care
even though we know it&#39;s going to generate
inconsistent results because of the low reporting rate.
Challenge seven, I&#39;m almost ready to wrap up
before I teach you a bit of Sinhala.
I don&#39;t know if (indistinct) is back on.
What we find with imported data,
if you import the HIV data into
the instance,
keep in mind that when you import data
you don&#39;t import the completeness metadata.
You usually don&#39;t.
And so here&#39;s the data on ART
care and treatment,
that dataset.
And you look at the tool
and it&#39;s blank.
It&#39;s got no completeness
on the page,
the completeness page of the dashboard.
And that&#39;s true of every region.
And the simple
reason that there&#39;s no completeness is that
you&#39;ve got to work with the completeness metadata
in order for DHIS to track this.
And that&#39;s not a simple thing.
I think we need to develop guidance on how to generate
completeness metadata for imported data sets.
I got started with it, but I&#39;m not a backend type of person.
So I think someone who&#39;s
got greater skills in using the backend
ought to come up with guidance
or an app or I don&#39;t know what,
on how to help to get the completeness metadata
in there so that we can track this most fundamental
metric of Data Quality.
So there we are. Thank you.