- [Instructor] So we&#39;ve talked a bit about form design
and I kind of went through that rather quickly.
It&#39;s just kind of a background piece of information
that I&#39;d like you to consider
when you&#39;re looking at your data.
You can see actually it&#39;s not just form design,
but when you review your outputs,
you might also see a lot of this happening
either between programs or within programs
where they&#39;re collecting duplicate data
or where there&#39;s incorrect desegregations.
And that is something to identify
and work with programs to try and update as you go forward,
because collecting all this duplicate information
can result in really poor data quality.
But moving on,
how do we rationalize some of the design decisions
that have been made that cause some of these problems?
And actually,
this falls back more on implementation teams,
more so than source, pieces of information or data, right?
So, this is something we can have much more
of an immediate effect on
if we think about it from that perspective.
So, let&#39;s just walk through what we&#39;re going
to talk about in the course of this discussion.
So first we&#39;re going to talk about procedural challenges
associated with DHIS2 system design.
Then, we&#39;re going to discuss the correct value types
to be used when we create data elements in DHIS2.
We&#39;re also going to talk about approaches
to handle historical data
and deal with historical data completeness.
We&#39;re also going to talk about approaches
to handle duplicate category options
and category option combinations,
which is a relatively large problem
that happens in many implementations.
It&#39;s also very common.
So, we&#39;ll talk about that a little bit,
and then we&#39;ll talk about best practices
when managing data dimensions,
the process of identifying duplicate data elements,
and considerations when creating data sets.
So you can see the items I&#39;ve described.
We all have quite a bit of a role to play
when we&#39;re helping anyone set up their system.
These are all things that are ultimately
something we can have a larger impact on immediately
versus some of the issues and challenges that I spoke before
about different parts of form design.
So if we look at some of the procedural challenges,
and this is kind of a source
of poor system design essentially.
So we often have a lack of procedures
for adding metadata, right?
And this is a big problem
because people just add metadata to wherever they want.
There might not be things like naming conventions,
or might not be any type of instruction
on where to do this.
Maybe they do it in their production system directly,
and maybe multiple people do it at the same time
and this is where this second point
on lack of coordination comes in.
So maybe you have two or more administrators
adding the same data sets
and they&#39;re not looking at what actually exists
in their system.
And this can also be a problem
because if you&#39;re hiding lots of metadata,
you&#39;re sharing is incorrect,
which we&#39;ll get to in a moment,
then, if I&#39;m an admin and I&#39;m working on one program
and I don&#39;t see the categories or data elements that exist
that can be reused potentially,
then I might create my own
and then we&#39;ll have duplicates essentially.
The WHO digital data packages also have some impact
on DHIS2 systems and how clean the design can be
and how easy it can be to find data
and the impact of data quality.
And this is because we can potentially introduce
a lot of duplicate metadata
when we import these and install these on our systems.
So something to really strongly consider
when we&#39;re doing this.
We&#39;re the ones often helping many countries set these up.
It&#39;s pretty rare
where these packages are just being set up
without any input from anybody, right?
So, this is something we often have a direct effect on
and it&#39;s something we really need to consider carefully.
Another problem is often revisions of data collection forms
over time.
So, when we take a look at data collection forms,
and when they get altered with new data elements,
new desegregations, et cetera,
we have to come up with smart ways
to handle this carry over.
And we&#39;ll talk about this a little bit more
as we go through this session.
We also often have new objects being added
directly to the production server,
and then they&#39;re abandoned without anybody cleaning this up.
So you get all kinds of data elements,
all kinds of different groups maybe,
all kinds of different data sets even,
and they&#39;re never used.
Maybe someone entered a couple of test values for them,
and they&#39;re just completely abandoned.
And no one&#39;s really sure why they&#39;re there,
but over time,
this becomes quite a significant challenge to deal with.
So one of the procedural challenges
that I mentioned was a lack of standard operating procedures
or guidance on how to create metadata.
So I&#39;m actually going to share a couple examples
with you about some things that have been done
in other places,
some things that I&#39;ve done,
some things that others have done,
to kind of work through this creation of metadata.
And there are some references
that I used as well to create this.
But I think it&#39;s important to have this in place
for both aggregate and tracker metadata,
so people are really aware of what that process is.
And this kind of training also goes well beyond
any type of customization training, right?
We&#39;re not just discussing with them
where to click and where different things are found,
but after that type of information has been done,
and they kind of understand how to use the interface
to add metadata,
we&#39;re really focusing on what to do procedurally
and what&#39;s right and what&#39;s wrong
and the considerations to make
when you&#39;re creating new metadata.
So it&#39;s obviously going a bit beyond
just regular kind of training,
but really thinking about,
&quot;If I make an SOP, then I train people exactly on this SOP&quot;
so people understand the process
that we&#39;re putting in place
and everyone&#39;s on board with this, right?
I kind of have in bold on this, if you can see,
that this is to be done on the development server first.
Right?
And I also mentioned this as a particular sticking point
in the presentation,
because you often have people just doing things
directly on production
and this can cause a lot of havoc,
particularly with things like category options
and categories,
especially if you rebuild those
and then things really get out of hand.
So, we have to be really careful how we approach this
and make sure that we can...
This is something I think we have a bit more control
and influence to help countries
in terms of setting up their systems
and making sure we transfer those best practices
over to them,
when we&#39;re doing training and capacity building
with them as well.