- Let&#39;s push on and get to the actual configuration.
Okay, so it hasn&#39;t been configured.
We recognize that, and now
let&#39;s launch the administration, the configuration page.
This instance is really very efficiently designed
and our internet connectivity is good.
So we are instantly taken to this first page
on configuration, but what what you will often find
is that you&#39;ll get a message, even as a super user,
you&#39;ll get a message that says you do not have authority
to change the configuration.
And the issue may be just internet connectivity,
that it&#39;s not able to communicate with the app
because of internet connectivity issues.
And you may have to wait awhile
before the message disappears
that says you don&#39;t have access rights.
To be able to do the configuration
you have to have the level of authority
of someone who can define indicators
and the user roles which have that level of authority
are the ones which are able to do this configuration.
Now, what is it that we are configuring here?
You can use the analysis function
even without doing any configuration.
So anyone with access to the data quality tool
can go through the steps of selecting one data element
or one indicator and looking for outliers,
doing comparisons.
But what we are configuring here is really
the dashboard of the data quality tool.
These are the numerators which will appear on the dashboard.
We&#39;re also configuring at the same time, the annual report.
And we won&#39;t spend time in this internal training
discussing the annual report,
but those are the two things that are being configured
with this page here.
Actually, there&#39;s a series of six,
and what we&#39;d like to do is take you through
the first four of these, in this internal training,
starting of course, with the numerators
and you see the columns here, groups,
what is a group, a reference numerator?
What does this mean? Core and data element indicator.
The groups, if you scroll down,
you see the pre-assigned groups,
general service statistics like hospital admissions,
outpatient visits, HIV.
These are the rest of the groups are basically programs.
You can actually add a group.
Now, what&#39;s the point of a group?
The groups determine what you see in the dropdown menu
and we have to configure at least one numerator
before we&#39;ll see any group.
So let me show you,
let&#39;s go ahead and configure DPT 3,
and then we&#39;ll see the functions of a group.
So I click on DPT 3.
This is the name, that WHO is recommending
that this be a core, notice core is checked here,
they&#39;re recommending that you configure this
as a core indicator or data element.
And if I recall for the play instance,
DPT 3 is a data element.
It&#39;s in the data element group of immunization,
or is it EPI up here?
Let&#39;s see, yeah.
Immunization data element group, a comment,
notice in this dropdown list,
there&#39;s nothing comparable to all data elements.
When you configure a pivot table or a chart,
you&#39;re used to having a dropdown menu
that allows you to select from all data elements.
Well, that&#39;s not possible with the data quality tool,
this version of the data quality tool.
So, if the data element you want
is not in a data element group,
or if the indicator that you want to select
is not an indicator group, then you simply can&#39;t select it.
And what you have to do is exit the tool and assign
that data element to a data element group,
or assign the indicator to a data element group.
It&#39;s one of the clunky features of the tool
that you simply have to get used to,
but in this case, the DPT 3 is there.
And what I&#39;m doing is I&#39;m finding the exact name
in the play instance of the data element
that is equivalent to this WHO recommended
reference numerator of DPT 3.
So the comparable one I found on the list is Penta three.
And then you have to specify what data set is in there.
And this one is a bit curious,
you see the detailed data elements and it almost
doesn&#39;t matter a great deal which one you select,
this appears in the annual report.
It doesn&#39;t appear anywhere else on the data quality tool,
but the annual report makes use of this.
And the rule that I suggest is to take the data element
that probably has the largest value, in this case,
it is fixed immunization under one,
only after you have filled in all of these,
let&#39;s say that we hadn&#39;t filled this in, we left it blank.
Notice the save button is grayed out.
So it insists that you fill in all of these
and sometimes if internet connectivity is poor,
one of these, just simply won&#39;t allow you,
the app won&#39;t allow you to fill it in
and then you just have to wait a bit,
pause until you&#39;re allowed to fill in
every single field of this screen
and then you can save.
So I&#39;ve saved.
Okay, and now notice, okay,
we&#39;ve got, it&#39;s in the immunization group.
This is the WHO recommended name,
the name doesn&#39;t really matter a great deal,
core is checked here and I&#39;ll show you what core means.
And this is the name of that, what we have mapped the WHO
reference numerator to a specific data element
in the play instance and it&#39;s from the child health dataset.
Now, let me show you the function of the group.
If we go to the dashboard
and the settings window, we now have,
finally, the dashboard has something on it.
It&#39;s got the child health completeness
on the completeness page
and under data, if we look at the dropdown menu under data,
we have two groups,
DPT 3 was assigned to the core group
but it&#39;s also in the immunization group.
So these groups are
the selections that appear in the data window,
the data you&#39;re not selecting, unlike the app,
the pivot table app, or data visualizer,
you&#39;re not selecting a data element
or indicator or a dataset,
you&#39;re selecting between these groups.
And as we go on, we&#39;ll see how using this data window,
it allows you to do a data quality review
that is specific for one program
and a program might have a larger number of indicators
that are specific to immunization, okay?
So I&#39;m going to go back to the numerator configuration page
and show you one more
and then we&#39;re going to,
we&#39;re going to see if a volunteer can,
or perhaps we&#39;ll do that tomorrow at the same time
and get a volunteer to practice this
so that I can show you some more features of configuration.
I&#39;m going to do one more, DPT one,
actually, I&#39;m going to show you another limitation
or aspect of the tool that&#39;s less user-friendly,
let&#39;s say that we don&#39;t want this to be a core,
see these check marks are in the column for core
and this means it is one of the data elements
that you see on the dashboard if you set data to core.
So let&#39;s say that we&#39;ve changed our mind,
we don&#39;t want to have DPT 3 amongst the core indicators,
just as an immunization indicator,
so we click on edit and you can easily enough
de-select core but notice what has happened
to all of these other fields of the window,
they&#39;ve disappeared.
So the app has no memory.
If you go in to reconfigure DPT 3,
you&#39;ve got to start from scratch
and go through this process once again,
repeat everything, which is a bit tedious,
but that&#39;s for now what you have to do,
you have to reset everything before you can reconfigure it.
So now we have changed DPT 3,
so that it is no longer a core indicator.
And in fact, let&#39;s see what we find if we,
yeah see it&#39;s blank, there&#39;s no indicator in core,
but if we change this to immunization,
then the indicator DPT 3 is in the immunization group.
So the dashboard shows results for DPT 3.