- [Instructor] Okay.
Another item to discuss is the data integrity checks,
and it&#39;s called data integrity checks,
but it&#39;s actually more of a metadata integrity check.
It&#39;s not really checking the integrity of the data itself,
but, because it kind of looks at the metadata,
there is some link then to, you know,
how this reflects upon the data quality itself.
So this is a function in DHIS2, that&#39;s built right in,
that you can run in order to kind of see the results of.
So, resolving these integrity violations
is quite an important aspect of both data quality
and data usability.
If a lot of their, a lot of these violations,
when they&#39;re resolved, really help people kind of select
the right, the certain, the right items when they&#39;re
creating their analysis.
And then obviously, if you&#39;re reviewing these items
routinely, it also allows you to kind of assess
the data quality more appropriately.
But, in practice, this is often a very low priority
resolving these issues.
This becomes quite challenging if you want the data quality
of your system to be improved.
As well as just kind of, you know,
improve the amount of data that is being used routinely.
The reasoning behind this, this link to data quality,
is because these data integrity check violations,
they tend to result in incorrect data itself.
So, there&#39;s kind of a direct, I will say correlation,
between the two and it doesn&#39;t necessarily mean
it&#39;s causing this problem,
but often it can be directly affecting at least what we see
in terms of our outputs.
And because it&#39;s causing problems with incorrect outputs,
then you know, the data quality itself might be reflected
on this because we&#39;re not really sure what kind of
assumptions to make.
We might think that we need to clean certain pieces of data,
but we&#39;re not really sure because we&#39;re not really sure what
that metadata should be pointing to.
And that&#39;s where the kind of problem lies, right?
The linkage between that metadata
and the data that we&#39;re seeing.
So, data integrity checks, or metadata integrity checks,
as I like to call them, they run a series of queries
that look at various aspects of the database.
And this is true for both aggregate datasets
and tracker programs.
So as an example, they could look at things like, you know,
all organization units should belong
to an organization unit group, right?
So when you add up all your organization unit groups
within a group set in particular, you know,
you should be getting the total number
of organization units at that particular level
that you&#39;re creating that group for.
You should also, you know, it also looks at things
like indicators with identical formulas.
So, you know, if there&#39;s several indicators
that have the same exact data elements in their formula,
you know, why do those duplicates exist?
So a total of 32 checks are run and we can access
this via data administration.
So let&#39;s have a quick look at this in practice.
So, if we navigate to data administration within DHIS2,
we can run data integrity,
even though it&#39;s metadata integrity, really,
but we can run this integrity check by clicking on this
first box here, checking data integrity.
And we just click on the item, run integrity checks.
So, this actually takes a little bit of time
because it&#39;s assessing your whole system essentially.
So, I&#39;m just going to come back when this is complete,
essentially, so you don&#39;t have to stare
at the screen loading.
Okay. So the data integrity check has completed running,
and I&#39;m just going to scroll through.
Any of these red violations are sorry, any of this in red
text are indicating violations.
And then when they&#39;re in green, it&#39;s saying, you know,
there&#39;s a check box next to it because it&#39;s passed
the integrity check, essentially.
So, any of these green items, I can&#39;t click on them
and expand and actually see because the database
has met the criteria essentially.
And we see that there&#39;s a mix of aggregate and tracker
being included here. You know, so things like program rules
and are also being checked during this process.
So if I go up here and I&#39;ll just click on one of these
data elements without a dataset.
Right? So I expand this and it actually gives me the list
of data elements that don&#39;t have a data set.
And, you know, what is the purpose of these data elements?
Did they exist in a data set before?
You know, so the whole idea is to identify these
and then work through them individually
and see how we can fix them.
So we can look at a couple other ones.
Indicators without groups. You know, same thing.
So all of this is kind of a mix of usability
and also kind of effecting our data quality.
Indicators with identical formulas, you know?
So, why are these things kind of there?
You know, it doesn&#39;t really make a lot of sense
when these things are violated.
And there can be some implications that result directly
in issues with our data.
So we have to be kind of careful when we see this.
Now, once again, as I mentioned, the priority to fix
these is often low,
but if we have a look at all the things it assesses,
we should really consider fixing some of these things
because it can have a direct impact on how we&#39;re kind of,
you know, seeing our information
and also what effect this has on the outputs that we create.
So, what I would recommend is that you actually
log in to one of the demo systems we have.
I put the link here for you and just run the data
integrity check, the metadata integrity check.
See, as you can see, it&#39;s not checking any data.
This is running purely checks against the metadata.
And just think about how you would potentially fix
some of these problems. You know, some of them have
immediate solutions when you look at them,
others might not be so clear.
So, just click on the database link below,
use the login that you created for that particular database.
It&#39;s the same as the data quality app
configuration exercise,
and just run the data integrity check
and see what you come up with.