- [Instructor] All right.
So today our first session before our break
is going over DHIS2 Data Quality Validation Rules
and Notifications.
Again, this is gonna be fairly technical.
I&#39;m going to have to go quite quickly through this.
So if you fall behind, please ask a question on Slack.
List of video will be posted later today, hopefully,
maybe tomorrow.
And so you are certainly invited to rewatch it.
You can slow it down if you&#39;d like
and make sure that you&#39;re capturing everything
if this is something that you wanna implement
in your country or project.
What are the objectives of the presentation?
Well, essentially we wanna understand
the logic behind validation rules.
We also wanna give you a quick overview
on how to build validation rules.
This may be a recap for some of you.
I know many countries already have
a lot of validation rules.
I think we&#39;re gonna expand your appreciation
of what validation rules could actually be used for.
But the key message is that we need
to have data quality coming to the user.
So right now all of you are using your email
more than you&#39;re using DHIS2.
I certainly do.
And I&#39;m one of the DHIS2 product managers.
I&#39;m looking at my email every day, almost all day.
And we need to start to build in processes
where data quality and even just alerts for data,
start to come to people&#39;s emails.
That&#39;s where they&#39;re spending their time.
They&#39;re not spending their time so much on DHS2 dashboards.
And there&#39;s just two little jokes here.
You can look at these yourself,
but the whole point being is we need to start sending data
to where people are spending their time.
Certainly we need to start sending notifications
for any kind of major data quality problems
to where people will actually see them quickly,
which is probably going to be their email.
Again, send data quality issues to the user.
Over the last couple of days,
we&#39;ve been looking at the various data quality apps,
the WHO data quality app in particular.
And we appreciate that there&#39;s a lot of functionality there
if you go into the application.
But we also have to appreciate the fact that many people
are not going to go into that application very often.
Many people are going to not feel compelled
to dig through the data, to find the data quality issues.
This is where we assist Administrators,
as DHS2 managers, as health information system managers
have to be proactive.
We have to set up the system to be able
to push data quality alerts and notifications
to where people again are spending their time,
which is probably their email.
You can even set it up to send it via SMS.
We know that data use is low.
And we talked about on Monday,
how one of the driving reasons for this
is because data trust is low.
There&#39;s actually a whole lot of research out there
that makes this point very, very clear.
And that people just don&#39;t trust the data
because they&#39;re not able to see the data quality issues.
And what are some things that we can do?
Well, again, data quality issues
are not a failure of the system.
They&#39;re a feature of the system.
Any kind of large project that is using DHS2,
will have data quality issues.
The failure is not being able to do something about it.
The failure is to keep people unable to see
the data quality issue.
And so how do we do that again,
probably for the fifth time already this morning?
We need to start sending the data quality alerts
and notifications directly to the folks.
DHIS2 is smart enough to actually send people,
alerts and notifications directly
to where they&#39;re spending their time,
email, SMS, even WhatsApp.
And the point of this presentation today
is to start to train you on how to configure DHIS2,
to actually do this, and also introduce some best practices.
The final point here to make is that the alerts
and notifications that you actually send to people,
need to be based upon some standard operating procedures.
We saw in the case that (indistinct) presented in Sri Lanka,
they have very clearly defined,
standard operating procedures.
On Monday, Andrew from Rwanda is going to present
on the Rwandan standard operating procedures.
Many countries have very good
defined standard operating procedures.
Many countries also have very poorly defined
or don&#39;t even have data quality,
standard operating procedures.
You need to have the standard operating procedures in place.
And the notifications and alerts
that you start to send from the system,
need to be in agreement or in alignment
with your existing standard operating procedures.
You don&#39;t need to have people guess what they need to do
when they receive an alert.
The alert should tell them what they need to do.
And if they are confused,
then they can refer back
to their standard operating procedures
that should make everything very clear.
So how do we start to send the alerts?
Well, the best way to do it is through validation rules.
So quick intro to validation rules,
validation rules are a way to assess the data
that has been entered in DHIS2.
And it&#39;s very based sense.
They&#39;re based on predefined rules.
You define the rules in the system,
and we&#39;re gonna show you how to do that, just a minute.
Validation rules though do not fully allow you
to check whether the data that is reported
is complete or accurate.
It&#39;s just going to tell you,
does it fit this rule that you have defined?
So the data could still be wrong and not trigger
a validation rule, just to make that point very clear.
But we&#39;re asked quite often to do various HMI assessments.
And one of the first things that we usually look at
is do the countries, or do the projects
have clearly defined validation rules?
And are they being used routinely?
And if they are, and they do then typically what that means
is the country is taking data quality very seriously.
If they&#39;re doing that,
then we can hopefully make a little bit of an assumption
that there is some data use
or data use is actually happening in the country.
If countries or projects
do not have clearly defined validation rules,
if they&#39;re not using them routinely
or they just don&#39;t have them at all.
It&#39;s fairly safe to say
that they are not taking data quality various seriously,
and that they do not probably
have very much data use going on.
And again, why is that?
Because people are not able to see the data quality issues.
There&#39;s no transparency, there&#39;s no data trust.
And these are things that the validation rules
can really help with.
All right, let&#39;s get in a little bit more technical here.
What exactly is a validation rule?
It&#39;s an expression that defines a relationship
between a number of data elements essentially.
The expression has a left side,
a right side and an operator in between.
We can think back to our grade school math days here,
we have a left side, we have a right side,
and then we have an equals greater than,
or less than in between those.
You create validation rules,
based on what you know to be true.
This is very, very important.
And I&#39;ll say it again.
You create validation rules,
based upon what you know to be true.
The reason that you need to appreciate this and DHI2S
is because in other statistical analysis software
that maybe you&#39;re using, this is the opposite
where you make validation rules based
upon what you know to not be true.
But in DHIS2, you define validation rules,
what you know to be true, what should be happening?
The example here is, Malaria RDT positive.
The number of positive malaria tests
should always be less than
the number of malaria RDT tested done.
How can you have more positive case tests,
than you have total number of tests completed?
If you have more positive tests,
then you actually have total number of tested.
There&#39;s an issue, there&#39;s a problem there.
It&#39;s either a problem with the malaria positive,
the number of positive tests
or an issue with the number of malaria tested.
But clearly there&#39;s an issue,
&#39;cause you know that you can&#39;t have more positives
than you have tested.
So this is a very simple example.
When to use validation rules.
Now, Nora is also going to talk about this
a little bit later.
I believe either tomorrow or next week,
but validation rules can essentially be used
in three different times.
They can be used during aggregate data entry.
So data set, data entry.
I think we&#39;ll be able to show you
an example of this a little bit later in the week.
But validation rules can be triggered
while data is being entered.
So for example, if I enter more malaria positives
than malaria tested during...
If I&#39;m at a clinic and I&#39;m putting that into my dataset,
a validation rule can be triggered,
and saying, &quot;Hey, you&#39;ve entered data.
that should not be possible.
You should go back and check this.&quot;
They can also be used to block data entry altogether.
So we can say that if they enter
more positive than the tested,
don&#39;t allow them to submit that data.
Now that can be a good thing.
It can also be a bad thing.
The general rule of thumb is,
allow users to get their data into the system.
Send them alerts and notifications during data entry,
if necessary.
But typically you want people to be able to put
their data in the system.
Only for probably the most highly trained users,
maybe folks at regional or national level,
should you disallow data to be entered
that does not pass.
That&#39;s the best practice or rule of thumb.
Second bullet point here,
validation rules can also be run manually.
So you can run data validation, rule analysis at any point,
you can do this before you do a supervision visit
for an individual health facility
or a group of health facilities,
or a group of community health workers.
When you run it manually,
it can also trigger emails or SMS alerts
that can be sent out to those
who are assigned to the organizational unit
that has prompted or resulted in the validation alert.
So we&#39;ll cover that a little bit today as well.
The last point is that validation rules
can be scheduled to run automatically.
And this is probably the most useful functionality
of validation rules is that,
you can schedule validation rules to run periodically,
say weekly monthly.
And then those can send again, alerts, emails, SMS messages,
to the various users who can actually go in and correct it.
All right, sorry, go ahead.
Is there a question?
Nope, just unmute the microphone for a second.
All right, so let&#39;s talk about
how we can make a simple validation rule.
Now I&#39;m gonna show you this through PowerPoint slides,
but you can in the exercise, go in and do it yourself.
These PowerPoint slides are just direct screenshots
from DHIS2.
So let&#39;s make a simple validation rule.
Here, we&#39;re looking at a bar chart
that&#39;s showing ANC1 visits, ANC2 visits, that&#39;s blue,
ANC3 that&#39;s red and ANC4 visits, that&#39;s orange.
And if you&#39;re not familiar with anti-natal care,
then essentially there are four visits
to the clinic that every pregnant woman should make.
And these are to receive different clinical services,
vitamins, minerals, checkups, that kind of stuff,
while the woman is pregnant.
And typically we have relatively high ANC1 visits.
Most women go to their first ANC1 visit,
but over time throughout their pregnancy,
they go to fewer and fewer of the visits.
And by the point we get to ANC4,
we typically see much fewer women going
to the fourth visit than went to the first visit.
Folks out there who work in maternal in child health,
you&#39;re saying, &quot;Wait a minute, these are different cohorts.&quot;
Well, yes, that is true.
But the model does play itself out fairly consistently
and only in certain countries do you have
which may have more seasonal pregnancies.
This model doesn&#39;t hold true.
But for the most part,
we almost always see that there are fewer ANC4 visits
than there are ANC1 visits.
So let&#39;s make a simple validation rule
that we check for this.
So we&#39;re gonna say that ANC4 should be less than
or equal to ANC1.
So what are the steps to build this validation rule?
And more importantly,
what are the steps to actually get
this elevation rural built into a notification
and pushed out to people?
Well, there&#39;s essentially six steps.
One of which is optional though.
The first one is you need to make the validation rule.
I&#39;m gonna show you how to do that just now.
Then we need to assign the validation rule
to a validation rule group.
Just like we assigned data elements
or indicators to various groups.
We need to of course test the validation rule.
Testing is so important
that I&#39;ve seen some several countries
that did not adequately test the validation rules.
And it was a disaster.
You need to make sure that you&#39;re testing these
before you actually start to push them out to everyone.
You need to make the validation rule notification step four,
make the validation rule notification.
Step five, which is again, optional,
but highly encouraged is you need to schedule
the validation rule group to run automatically.
This has done in the scheduler app.
I&#39;m gonna show you how to do that.
The step six, which is not optional.
You definitely need to do this,
is you need to write a protocol and guidelines
on how use the validation rule group.
You need to make sure that every step of the process
of performing these data quality checks,
how to run them, when to run them,
who receives what notifications?
You&#39;ve defined, all of that.
So that if you have maybe turnover in the organization,
whoever comes after the person who made the validation rules
is able to update, modify and follow
what&#39;s been done previously.
And you also need to have control over this process.
You don&#39;t want to have just dozens of validation rules
that no one is using that are completely useless,
that are not tested.
As system administrators, as DHIS2 managers
or HMEs managers, you need to have a fair amount
of control and very clear documentation
of the validation rules.
All right.
If you want to start making validation rules,
again, I&#39;m gonna go through the slides,
but the slides I&#39;m gonna show you
are just step-by-step screenshots of the actual process.
But if you did wanna go in
and make validation rules yourself, this is the link.
It&#39;s a separate instance
than what you&#39;ve been working in so far, and you need to go.
So it&#39;s academy.demos.dhs.org/dqapp-config.
So you can copy and paste this link directly
into your web browser.
We recommend that you use Chrome
and you&#39;ll be able to start building your validation rules.
All right.
So what&#39;s the first step to making a validation rule?
Well, we&#39;re gonna go to the maintenance app
and in the maintenance app,
we can click on the validation on the top header bar.
So you see that&#39;s underlined in orange
at the top of the screenshot.
If we wanna make a new one,
we just go down to the add new button,
which is that blue button right
at the bottom right corner of the screen.
Let&#39;s go step-by-step here.
You see the steps are numbered on the right.
All right, so follow with me as I speak through the steps.
If you&#39;re following along,
you&#39;re actually building this validation rule
as I&#39;m going through it right now,
what you need to do is you need to give
the validation rule a very clear name.
And this example,
we&#39;re calling it ANC1 greater than ANC4.
And then if you are building this validation rule
in the demo database,
recommend that you put hyphen your name
so that you can go in and you can remember
which validation rule is yours.
Then it&#39;s not necessary.
It&#39;s not compulsory,
but we recommend that you do give it a short name.
And then of course we do recommend that all data is coded
or all metadata is coded.
So that&#39;s the third step here,
not again necessary,
but it is strongly recommended that you have
some kind of coding procedure or coding methodology
for all of your metadata items
so that it helps keep your metadata more organized
and allows you to certainly system administrators,
to query the database more quickly and easily
to pull up any kinds of issues that you may have.
Anyways, not compulsory,
but we do recommend short names and codes.
Then the description.
Now, the description is very important.
This is step two.
You need to provide a clear description of what it is,
what they&#39;re actually looking at.
So in this one, it says ANC4
should not be greater than ANC1.
Then after the description,
we can provide some instructions.
Again, not compulsory,
but highly recommended that you put
in some clear instructions.
You see, in this one, we have ANC4
should be greater than ANC1.
Please check these two values and correct.
So imagine the situation where this validation is triggered.
Someone has put in the ANC4 is greater than ANC1,
what should you tell them to do?
Then you need to provide them very clear instructions.
And then that&#39;s the place to put it here
in the instructions.
Again, don&#39;t make people guess
what they need to do about their problems.
Tell them specifically.
Step four is to assign an importance.
And let me tell you a little bit about what this means.
So this is completely up to you.
We have a high, a medium and a low option for importance.
And the default is medium,
but you could use this importance
for a couple of different reasons.
And I&#39;ll tell you two different examples right now.
There are some countries and projects
that give validation rules at high importance
if that validation triggers an alert for something
that they know to be wrong.
For example, if you have more tested than treated,
you know that one of those numbers is wrong.
There&#39;s no way physically that you can have more...
If you&#39;re monitoring just those
who are treated after receiving tests,
there&#39;s no way that you can have more treated than tested.
Now, I know some of you epidemiologists
are out there saying,
&quot;Well, what about clinical malaria,
People who aren&#39;t tested?&quot;
But if you just bear with me,
what I&#39;m saying is those who are treated after tested,
if you have more treated who weren&#39;t tested,
you know that&#39;s not something
that can actually possibly happen.
So you give that validation rule, high importance,
because you know one of those numbers is wrong.
And then whoever receives that notification knows that,
&quot;Hey, this is high priority.
One of these numbers is wrong.
Something needs to be corrected.&quot;
That&#39;s one way of doing it.
The other way of doing it is setting
the high priority validation rules
for disease outbreak monitoring.
Now, this is a little bit of a different concept
to what we&#39;ve been talking about.
You can use validation rules for disease surveillance.
For example, you could say the number of Ebola cases
should always be equal to zero.
What happens?
As soon as one health facility reports
a single case of Ebola, it will trigger a validation alert.
People receive SMS, just people receive emails.
And then all of a sudden, everybody knows,
&quot;Hey, there was a case of Ebola reported,
we need to go out and do something about it.&quot;
Several countries in west Africa use validation rules
and high importance validation rules,
specifically for disease outbreak and monitoring
in this way.
Then you need to define your period.
And your period, step five here,
should be set to at least the same as the frequency
in which the data is captured.
So if your data&#39;s captured monthly,
then you should set your period to at least a monthly.
You can&#39;t set it to weekly.
You can&#39;t set it to daily.
That would not work.
You need to at least set it to monthly.
However, you could set it to like quarterly or annually.
And what would happen is that this validation rule
would aggregate that data from those months to that quarter,
in which you&#39;re doing the analysis, if that makes sense.
But the general rule of thumb is that you just set
the validation rule to the same period
at which you&#39;re capturing the data.
After you go through those steps,
you need to define the left side and the right side.
Here, I&#39;m going to just quickly show you.
This is the left side generator.
And how about this?
I think I&#39;ve stretched that a lot.
Let me just go in and...
I&#39;m just gonna show you,
this is a little bit easier to show it to you
than to present it on a slide.
The left side and the right side.
So I&#39;ve gone into the maintenance app.
I&#39;m gonna go to my validations.
I&#39;m going to list my validation rules
and yeah, great, looks like some folks
are already in here doing this.
I&#39;m gonna click on one validation rule here,
which is ANC2 should be less than or equal to ANC1.
And I&#39;m going to...
so I&#39;ve defined my period.
I&#39;ve defined my importance.
Now I&#39;m gonna go into my left side.
I&#39;m gonna zoom in a little bit for you here.
That&#39;s a little bit bigger.
If I go into my left side,
then the first thing is you needed to find
is your value missed...
Oh, sorry, excuse me.
Missing value strategy.
So you have three options.
You can say skip if any value is missing,
skip if all values are missing or never skip.
All right, this depends upon which one you choose.
Depends upon the different data elements
that you&#39;ve included in your expression.
Typically I would say more often than not.
You want to probably have skip
if all values are missing or skip if any values are missing,
you don&#39;t want validation rules to be triggered
if there&#39;s no values there.
It&#39;s not usually good practice
if they&#39;re just missing values,
so DHIS2 will stand in a zero value.
So I&#39;m actually gonna change this.
I&#39;m gonna say skip, if all values are missing.
&#39;Cause why did I do that?
Well, I actually have two different data elements here,
so I have ANC second visits fixed,
plus ANC second visits outreach.
So I&#39;m gonna say skip,
if all values are missing for these two here.
Okay, the next thing that I want to point out is...
One second.
This sliding window.
What does sliding window mean?
Well, the great thing about DHIS2 these days
is that we have a lot of user documentation out there.
There&#39;s a lot of resources out there.
So what I&#39;m gonna do just to show you the processes,
I&#39;m just gonna Google, DHIS2 sliding window.
You can see I&#39;ve Googled this before.
And so what&#39;s my first link?
It&#39;s a link to the master user documentation,
let me click on that, see where that takes me.
Well, I think I found my answer right here
about sliding windows.
I&#39;ll just give you a quick summary of what this is.
Now, this is our good functionality
and primarily intended for disease surveillance.
So the typical use case for this is
if you have a threshold, like an outbreak threshold,
and that threshold for outbreak is calculated on,
may say a weekly or monthly basis.
But you have maybe daily data coming into the system.
And what the sliding window will do
is as you move forward in time, as you go from week to week,
and make this validation rule analysis,
the days will follow you incrementally
as you move forward in time.
And that&#39;s actually what you see this little diagram
that&#39;s playing out.
You see that we&#39;re going
from week one to week two to week three.
And our threshold for week one is 10.
Our threshold for week two is nine.
And our threshold for week three is eight.
And you can see that the number of cases is...
And that threshold is calculated on a weekly basis,
but as we move forward in time,
we&#39;re getting more and more cases reported in.
And so you see that our number of cases
is changing every day.
And that sliding window allows you to go period
by period or day by day as new data comes in.
So instead of the alternative would be that on week two,
the validation would only run for and say,
you&#39;re on Monday of week two.
First day of week two,
the validation would only count the data
that&#39;s entered for Monday against the weekly threshold.
That doesn&#39;t actually really work well
in disease surveillance.
We want this sliding window.
We want the data to be aggregated
as we move through time, day after day.
I appreciate this as a bit of a nuanced thing,
those epidemiologists out there,
hopefully you appreciate what we&#39;re trying to go for here.
Again, sliding windows are principally used
for disease surveillance,
and using validation rules for like outbreak detection
or against say like a threshold, an outbreak threshold.
If you have more specific questions on that,
I&#39;m happy to go into it in more detail.
But for now I think we just have to keep moving on.
So the next step is that we actually need to build
our expression.
So here you see, we have ANC first visits fixed,
ANC second...
Oh sorry, ANC second visits fixed,
ANC second visits outreach.
Just for the sake of showing you, I&#39;m going to delete those.
And you see that when I deleted those
and I deleted those in this expression builder field here,
they says the expression is empty.
See the translator down at the bottom is saying,
&quot;Hey, you&#39;ve got nothing here.&quot;
So how am I gonna build this?
I am gonna come over to the right side.
I&#39;m gonna leave.
I&#39;m gonna select data elements,
and I&#39;m gonna search for my ANC2 visits.
So I&#39;m gonna search ANC2 and here they&#39;re.
And I have fixed an outreach.
I&#39;m going to double click on fixed.
You see that it comes here.
And this thing that you see here,
this hashtag and then brackets
and seemingly random series of letters and numbers
is the unique identifier of this data element.
This is how DHIS2 stores this data element in the backend.
All right, so, if you&#39;re curious on how to query the API
for different metadata items,
the easiest way to do it is through the UID of them.
Anyways, you still have to deal with it here
as you&#39;re building the validation rules.
So I&#39;m gonna say ANC second visit fixed,
plus ANC second, visit outreach.
So here I&#39;d just click the plus button and I click outreach.
And then here you go, we&#39;re back to our original expression.
So just this plus this.
I won&#39;t go over all of these various other operators.
There&#39;s clear documentation of what these do.
Hopefully most of these are quite clear,
like multiplication, division, minus, addition.
Counts the number of days in the org unit,
in the period that you are running the validation for.
So if you have a monthly validation
and you are running that validation for October,
it would say that there&#39;s 31 days in October.
So that would substitute a value of the number
of days in the period at which you&#39;re running
the validation for.
All right, so I&#39;m gonna save this,
After that you have to select an operator.
You see that we have quite
a number of different operators equals two,
not equal to greater than greater than,
or equal to less than compulsory repair.
Compulsory repair means that both values have to be there.
That one value cannot be missing.
That the left side has to be there
and the right side has to be there.
You also have exclusive pairs,
which means that one side has to be there.
If the left side is there,
then the right side cannot be there.
And then we have to define our right side,
defining the right side is just like defining the left side.
Then we have to assign...
Well, you don&#39;t actually have to do this,
but you can assign the org unit level
for which you want the validation rule to run.
If you leave this blank,
if I don&#39;t assign any of these,
then what it&#39;ll do is it&#39;ll run the validation rule
at the level at which the data is captured,
that triggers that validation rule.
So this data is captured at facility level.
So it would provide the validation at facility level.
If I turned on say district level,
then what do I actually do is run the validation
at district level, not run it at facility level,
and it will aggregate the data to the district.
So all the facility level data
will be aggregated to the district.
In this case, all of the data for ANC2,
across all the facilities,
will be aggravated to the district.
All the data for ANC1 across all the facilities
will be aggregated to the district.
And if the validation doesn&#39;t pass at the district,
then you&#39;ll receive an alert for the district.
The last tick that we can say
is skipped the rule during form validation.
Now this allows by default,
the validation rules
will produce alerts during data entry in the dataset.
If you don&#39;t want that to happen, then you take this box.
But by default, the box is not ticked,
if we go in to a dataset into a data entry form,
we start entering data.
And we say that ANC2 is greater than ANC1.
Then you&#39;ll see a alert pop-up.
If I tick this box, then the alert will not pop up.
Let&#39;s get back into the PowerPoint.
I think we can actually skip ahead a bit.
We&#39;ve covered all of this already.
The next step is you need to make a validation rule group.
And the validation rule groups, making these is very simple.
Again, in the maintenance you go to validation rule group,
and you just group your validation rules together.
So if you have all of your ANC validation rules,
you can put those into one group.
So the next step is that we need to cover
before we&#39;re able to break,
is going through building validation rule notifications.
So, because we&#39;re actually running
a little bit of short on time.
I&#39;m gonna skip through running the validation rules.
I believe that we&#39;ll be able to come back
to that later in the week.
So I&#39;m just gonna show you how to build
the validation rule notifications now.
So let&#39;s again, do this one together.
So I&#39;m back in the maintenance app.
I&#39;m gonna go to validation rule notification.
You see that on the left side of the screen,
we see that Robert,
Robert you&#39;re winning the prize today
and (indistinct), you&#39;re also doing a great job.
So you&#39;re already a bit ahead of the pack here.
Let&#39;s just add one together though.
So I&#39;m going to click the plus button
in the bottom right corner like we always do.
And I am going to give this a name.
I am just gonna call it ANC4, less than ANC1.
I&#39;ll give it my name, -Scott,
just so, I can find it later if I want.
Obviously, if you&#39;re making these in your system
in your actual DHIS2 instance,
you don&#39;t put hyphen in your name,
I&#39;m just doing it now because we&#39;re all building
and sharing inside of one database.
All right.
And then we need to find our validation rules
that we want to use.
So I am just gonna randomly six because Robert
was the first one I saw this morning.
I&#39;m gonna choose Roberts.
Hopefully Robert, your validation rule is working properly.
We&#39;ll find out in a minute.
And then we need to define our recipient groups.
Now we can send this to different org...
Sorry, user groups.
This is not necessary.
You could have it sent to notify users in hierarchy only.
That&#39;s also an option.
So what does that mean?
That means that anyone who is assigned to this org unit
would receive this notification.
But it&#39;s also generally best practice
that you have different user groups.
Maybe you have a user group for disease surveillance
or disease response.
And any validation rules that are associated
with disease surveillance,
they should maybe be sent to this user group.
Even if the validations are coming
from places that that user is not really associated with.
So this is an option here.
It&#39;s completely up to you to decide and how best to use it.
But like I said,
it&#39;s useful to make various user groups,
based upon different kinds of associations or projects
or different roles within the system.
I am going to say, though,
I wanna notify users in the hierarchy.
And you can see that you can do both.
You can say, I wanna send it to this user group
and notify users in the hierarchy, for example.
And then it&#39;s important.
The next step is you have to define
how you send the notifications.
Do you wanna send it as a collective summary
or as a single notification?
I&#39;ll show you an example of this in a minute,
but essentially a collective summary we&#39;ll group,
all of the validation rules into a single message.
So for example, if you have 20 validation alerts triggered,
then it will send it in a single email.
If you say single notifications,
then it was send those 20 different validation alerts
as separate emails.
So instead of you receiving one email with 20,
you will receive 20 emails with one.
Again, depends on the different strategy
and purpose of the validation rule.
I would say the general rule of thumb though,
is try to minimize the number of emails that people receive.
People receive too many emails, it just becomes noise.
They start paying attention to it.
Most countries, most projects I&#39;ve seen
have found it more useful use collective summary.
Then we have to define a message.
And this message you&#39;ll find can be relative
to the validation rule.
So you see, we have our template variables
over here on the right side.
So we can use these,
drop these into our subject template.
And it will automatically fill in these for us.
So I&#39;m gonna say rule name
has been triggered for, let&#39;s say organizational unit.
So whatever facility, on actually for the period.
So (indistinct) did the validation will get triggered for?
And then I&#39;ll say on the current date.
So the date at which the validation rule
was the validation rule analysis actually took place.
So it&#39;ll say in this case,
the translation for this would be ANC1 minus ANC4
Robert has been triggered for,
let&#39;s say like facility 146 for October, 2020
on the 22nd of October.
So that&#39;s the subject short, but sweet
but gives a lot of good information.
And for the message template,
we can make this even a little bit longer.
We could say something similar, like validation rule name
with validation rule description
has a left side description of left side value
and right side description of right side value.
Then maybe we drop in at organizational unit on the period.
This is incorrect.
Please follow the data quality SoPs, something like that.
So it&#39;s just a longer message is giving
the user more information about
what&#39;s the validation rule?
What was the description of the validation rule?
What are the actual values that are triggering
the validation rule?
Where&#39;s it at?
When was it?
And then giving them maybe some more specific instructions
about how to actually correct it.
Again, if you remember earlier, we were talking about,
it&#39;s very important to give specific instructions
on how to correct the validation rules
in the validation rule notifications.
So if this happens to someone,
they received this notification,
what specifically should they do about it?
This one is quite vague.
Please follow the data, quality SoPs.
You could say, review during monthly data quality,
verification meeting or something like that.
We can make it specific to whatever actually
is your standard operating procedures
or your processes in your project or country.
All right, so that is making
the validation rule notification.
I&#39;m just gonna pop back over to my PowerPoint.
I&#39;m gonna skip how to run the validation rules.
We&#39;ll be able to come back to this.
So when to run your validation rules,
now there&#39;s a point here.
I do wanna make this quite clear,
and I made reference alluded to this earlier.
When you&#39;re configuring your data set, there is a tick box.
And that&#39;s what you see on the right side
of the screen here.
This is a screenshot of configuring a dataset.
The dataset is reproductive health,
and you see where the red box is,
it says complete allowed only if validation passes
and you see that that box is ticked.
Now, what does that actually do?
That means that any validation rules
that are associated with the data
that&#39;s being entered for that dataset,
if there&#39;s a validation notification that is triggered,
what happens?
It means that that data set will not be allowed
to be marked complete,
which means the data that was entered
for that dataset will still be in the system.
But that means it won&#39;t show up
in your reporting rate analysis.
Datasets have to be marked complete
in order to show up for a reporting rate analysis.
Now, this can be a good thing.
If you have highly trained staff
who know how to correct the data quality issues,
and you have very clearly defined validation rules
with good descriptions and good instructions
that tells them exactly what they need to do.
In most cases though, in my experience,
this has caused a lot of problems.
The reason it&#39;s caused a lot of problems
is because people have not clearly defined
their validation rules.
They&#39;ve not clearly defined
their validation rule instructions, their district staff,
the people who are putting them data in
or facility staff are not highly trained.
And it just means that people are trying
to put the data in the best they know how.
And they&#39;re being prevented from being able to do that.
There is one country I worked in who had one validation rule
that was configured
that it was not possible of being passed.
There was no way to pass the validation rule.
And this was the main data set that they had
for the country.
It was the monthly facility reporting dataset,
the major dataset.
And it prevented people from the district
and the city levels from being able to mark
that data set complete for a couple of years
before they noticed the problem.
And that means that they had no reporting rate data
for years.
So they asked what we could do.
All we did was go in and tick the box.
That was it. That was the easiest fix.
I think I&#39;ve ever had for DHIS2 to be honest with you.
And what did that then do it allowed them
to put the data in
and we reinforce the data, quality checks, post data entry.
All right.
Now I wanna show you quickly before we break
in a few minutes,
on how to schedule validation rules.
So we talked about,
you can actually schedule the validation rules
and they can send out automatic notifications.
So we&#39;ve talked about how to make the validation rules.
We&#39;ve shown you how to make
the validation rule notification.
Now we&#39;re gonna show you the last part of the job,
which is scheduling the validation rules
to run automatically.
And so there&#39;s an app for this.
The app is called The Scheduler App.
This app is again an app that should only be accessible
to system administrators.
This is not an app that you want anyone
to be able to go in and do stuff with.
But if you&#39;re a system administrator,
you should be able to use this application,
The Scheduler App.
And what we&#39;re gonna do is we&#39;re actually go in
and we&#39;re gonna make a monitoring job.
And so I&#39;m gonna walk through the screenshots here.
When you go in to make a new job in the scheduler app,
you first have to define...
You have to of course give it a name,
just like we do with everything else.
Give it a name in this case,
we&#39;re going to call it ANC,
and then you have to schedule
when the job will execute.
All right,
you have three options for this.
And the first option which is that first orange box
on the far left.
You see that you can use a predefined frequency.
So you see that we have five predefined frequencies there,
every hour, every day at midnight,
every day at 3:00 am, every day at noon every week.
So these are your options for predefined.
If you want a different frequency,
say you want the first day of every month,
then you have to put a chronic suppression.
Now, if you are a server administrator
or anyone with a bit of background in software development,
you know what a chronic depression is,
but if you&#39;re not familiar with chronic expressions,
all I can say is you should just Google it.
There are a lot of great chronic depression builders,
out there in the world.
You don&#39;t necessarily
have to know anything coding or anything.
You just have to be able to say,
&quot;I want something to run
at the first day of the month at 1:00 am.
And then there&#39;s chronic suppression builders out there
that will give you the syntax for that.
And you can copy and paste it here into DHIS.
The other alternative is to have continuous execution.
Continuous execution means that it will constantly run.
As soon as it finishes, it will run again.
Now this may be good for a few situations.
The first one is disease surveillance.
If you are monitoring just one or two validation rules
that are used for disease surveillance,
you can have this continuously running.
That&#39;s not going to tax your system very much.
But if you&#39;re using,
say you want to make an expression or a job
that will check maybe 10 validation rules,
I guess a monthly dataset.
You do not want that to run continuously.
The reason is, is because that will be very taxing
to your server.
It will be very difficult for your server to maintain that
because the validation rules require
a lot of processing to run.
And if you&#39;re running it continuously,
you&#39;re going to really slow down
the performance of your server.
So again, this is useful for disease surveillance.
If you&#39;re just running for one or two validation rules,
but I highly, highly, highly recommend
that you do not use it
if you are running maybe three validation rules or more.
You&#39;ll really tax the performance of your system.
All right.
The next thing that we need to do is to find
a relative star and a relative in.
Now, this may sound a little bit confusing to you.
And essentially what this is,
you enter a number here,
you enter either a negative number or positive number,
and you see here, we&#39;ve entered a negative one
for our relative start.
What this means is this is relative to today,
and it is counting the number of days.
So a negative one here means yesterday,
yesterday was negative one day from today.
You see that our relative end is positive one
that is tomorrow.
So what does that mean?
That means that it will run any of the validation rules
that are included in this job.
We&#39;ll check any data that was entered
between yesterday and tomorrow.
So that&#39;s includes three days.
But these three days fall within October,
which is one month,
October falls into one quarter three.
And that these three days follow within one year.
So for example, if I have this job looking
at this the last three days,
then it will also trigger any validation rules
that are set to monthly and run those for October as well.
If we fast forward and say that we&#39;re sitting
in October 31st, today, today is October 31st,
let&#39;s just imagine that.
And we have our relative start to negative one
and a relative end to one.
That means that tomorrow will be November.
And so it would run the validation rules
for both October and November.
Because these three days straddle two months,
hopefully that makes sense to you.
I know it can be a little bit confusing.
What&#39;s a good rule of thumb.
Well, I actually recommend that you use
a pretty large number for your relative start.
So something like negative 90 or negative 60
or something like that.
And excuse me, this PowerPoint is not updated.
So negative 90 days is not March 24th.
Sorry, I&#39;m recycling a PowerPoint presentation here,
but you say relative negative 90 days relative
into maybe just what plus one, which is tomorrow.
You don&#39;t have to put in the plus.
You can just put in the number one.
And negative 90 days to today.
Well, that covers 91 days that will cover about four months
I think in this situation,
it will cover two quarters in one year.
So any data that was entered in the last 91 days,
in the last four months,
the last two quarters of the last year
would be included in this validation check.
The second to last step is that you have to choose
the validation rule group
or you can add your validation rules one at a time.
You can also say if you want to send notifications.
So again, notifications, where does this come from?
This means that validation of role notification
that you configured earlier would be sent out
and notifications can be sent via email or SMS or both
if the notification is configured
and you configured an email server to your DHIS2,
you configured an SMS gateway to your DHIS2
and the user who is receiving that notification
is configured to receive emails and SMS.
You have to do all four of these
in order for anyone to receive any notifications from DHIS2.
There&#39;s documentation online
about configuring email servers and SMS gateway.
So we won&#39;t get into that today,
but if you&#39;re struggling with that,
please send us a message and we can point you
to the documentation and support material for that.
Or of course answer your questions.
The last one is persists results.
Now, if you take this persist results,
what it will do is it will save any of the validation rules
that are triggered.
And when this job runs automatically,
in this case it&#39;s running every day at midnight,
when this runs automatically,
any validations that have already been triggered
will not be shown.
It will only show the new ones.
Why is that?
It&#39;s because it&#39;s persisting the results of the old one.
Now, if you are a DHIS2 expert,
and you know how to query the API,
these validation rule results are actually saved
in a data table.
So you can actually start to build analytics
around these if you want.
That&#39;s just for the folks who are DHIS2 experts
and are familiar with the API.
If you&#39;re not, you just need to remember
that the functionality here is saving
the validation rule results,
and when that validation job runs again,
it will only show you the new validation rules
that have not been shown in the past.
One other consideration is that if you&#39;re having
a lot of validation rule notifications triggered,
these are being saved onto your server.
It could take up some server space.
All right, I&#39;m going to skip this for now.
And I&#39;m gonna show you quickly some examples here.
I know we&#39;re running a little bit over time,
but let&#39;s take a look at this.
So this is an example that I made for our demo database.
And you can see that I made the ANC validation
or notifications run for the whole country.
This was just two validation rules.
And what did it do?
Well, it actually ended up sending me 19 emails.
And in those emails contained,
2000 different validation rule alerts.
Now, is that useful?
Well, certainly receiving 19 automatic emails
is not useful.
And receiving 2000 alerts is completely unuseful.
There&#39;s no way that anyone would be able to respond
to this or do anything about it.
What do we need to do?
We need to make sure that our messages are clear
and concise and are in a manageable amount.
Now, here&#39;s a look at what the actual email said.
So looking in the email itself,
it says that this health facility has produced
an alert for ANC2 which is less than or equal to ANC1
for this month.
ANC2 can not be greater than ANC1.
So the message is useful, but I received 2000 of them.
Now, can I do anything about that?
Really? No, you cannot.
So we need to ask ourselves,
we have to be very careful about this.
How and whom can automatic validation,
emails and alerts be useful?
Here is a good example from Rwanda.
Now, Rwanda is using DHIS2 validation notifications
for outlier detection.
And we&#39;re gonna cover how to do that in the next session,
after our break.
But essentially what they&#39;ve done here.
And you can see,
this is an actual email from the Rwandan demo database.
This is not real data, but this is their demo database.
You can see that
this person received 23 high priority validation rules
in their email.
And there&#39;s a clear message.
So as validation for Penta 3 outlier,
data validation rule has been detected
at this health facility on this date,
for this month or for that year.
Please confirm the value is correct for Penta 3.
And they only received 20 notifications.
Now, this person is at district level.
These health facilities that are producing the alerts
are from their health facilities.
This is the amount of notifications
that they can do something about.
Also the message is quite clear.
It&#39;s telling them exactly where and when the problem is.
So if you&#39;re a district health officer,
you&#39;re able to receive this email and you&#39;re saying,
&quot;Okay, I need to go in and I need to check these 23 values.&quot;
How long does that take?
I don&#39;t know, maybe a few hours.
Maybe it could take a day.
But you need to go in and correct these values.
These are suspicious values that need to be corrected.
This is a great example from what Rwanda has set-up
Here is another one from Cameroon.
Cameroon is still experimenting with this,
but they have set up some basic alerts
for disease surveillance.
And so in this case,
you see that I won&#39;t translate it for you.
Those are your friends.
I think there&#39;s a bunch of Cameroonians on the call as well.
This is just a test.
I don&#39;t believe that this is in production yet,
but you have at least tested using validation rules
for disease surveillance.
So you are able to send alerts and notifications
to those who are on disease surveillance response teams,
when there is some outbreaker number of cases
that needs to be investigated.
So another really good example of how this can be used
from Cameroon.
And again, the person&#39;s only receiving four notifications.
That&#39;s an actionable number.
That&#39;s not 2000 notification.
So the last point to be made is that,
again, these notifications
and everything need to be built
into your standard operating procedures,
and you need to test them thoroughly.
So that is the end.