(gentle music)
- Min/max values,
the lost secret to data quality success
and part of the series on the data quality online academy.
So some discussion about min/max ranges.
What we know is that good quality routine health data
is stable and consistent
and does not yo-yo doesn&#39;t go large variations up or down.
And any variations can and should be explained.
Your number of first anti-natal visits should be constant
month in, month out with maybe some seasonal variation.
Head count should be consistent.
The setting of minimum and maximum ranges provides a guide
as to what the data should not exceed
and if used correctly assists in preventing
or limiting extreme outliers.
So the idea is that the min/max ranges gives you
a safety cushion within the data that can work,
that would be expected, would be usable
and outside that you have to start and think and see
what&#39;s going on.
This means that ranges should be wide enough to accept
most values and narrow enough to trap values that
are not lucky.
A range of one to 1000 is not a min/max range.
A range from 10 to 12 is not a min/max range.
Min/Max ranges are not punishment.
In other words, people shouldn&#39;t-
when they&#39;re entering the data,
keep on tripping over the messages
that this is out of range.
In most cases with extreme outliers,
we notice that they are either no min/max values preset
or if they are set, they are just ignored.
Press enter, enter and continue.
So some considerations about min/max ranges,
they&#39;re used during data entry.
We also know that there are quite a few data elements
which can show a fair degree of fluctuation
that we would consider normal;
family planning supplies are a good example
Vaccine supplies, drug supplies,
this month, you got nothing, next month, you get 2000,
but it can be considered normal
and they are not problematic.
Where you&#39;ve got a disease or medical condition that
runs at very low numbers and slowly there is an uptake,
min/max ranges might help pick that one up.
However, where you have expected seasonal increases,
be careful when using min/max.
An example is malaria or diarrhea in children
in the rainy season.
So there are times when you have an expected
seasonal increase.
And in order to access mim/max ranges,
you need access or rights to the data entry screen.
And according to the user role policy in most countries,
that&#39;s only granted to the people who enter data,
the data capturing stuff.
So if you double-click on any value,
you will see the last 12 months of data.
And so the ranges promotes good data quality and alerts
to data that does not fit the norm,
doesn&#39;t fit the normal pattern.
And 12 months.
If you double-click on a value,
you get what is called the data information window.
Top left-hand corner is the comment.
And we see that this comment field is almost never used,
perhaps mainly because it&#39;s not seen.
And above the comment is a star, which if you click on it
will save it and allow you to run a follow-up analysis.
On the right, we see where you can set the min/max ranges,
you can manually set them and save it.
And we see here,
data in graph format for the last
12 months.
If we look at this data information window,
no ranges have have been set and there&#39;s a substantial
amount of variation.
And if you eyeball the values,
do you think that we could manually think about ranges
for this specific data element for this specific facility.
And possibly, open to debate, our minimum could be four,
because that would track everything except the zero
and the maximum would be 18,
which would trap everything above the 20 line.
Just remember that this range here is only for
this data element for this facility.
It&#39;s not carried over anywhere else.
The other thing that we find on the data information window
is an audit trail.
And every time somebody changes the value,
it keeps track of it.
So you can see when values were changed and updated
and who did that.
This is how you set about making min/max ranges in bulk
and you find this under data administration,
min/max generation, you select a dataset,
select an OU level, restrict your selection,
do not try and run it for the whole country at once.
Run it for one small area.
You run it for more than that, it will crash because
remember it has to go through every facility
and every data element.
And you click generate and that will automatically
make it calculate.
So the exercise for this session is either access
to your own country DHIS2 or the demo database.
If you&#39;re looking for your own country,
DHIS2 instance, confirm if min/max rangers have been set
for your country.
And then if you have a staging or testing instance,
have a look at it, generate min/max values for one dataset
and a limited OU level.
If possible, open the data entry screen and view
the data information window.
We saw that picture earlier on.
Run min/max violations for selected dataset and OU level,
remember the min/max violations is in the data quality app.
Write a short report of the violations,
in other words, where they have been triggered.
What is the action plan,
now that you&#39;ve got these violations?
What are you going to do about it?
Are we just going to ignore it,
or do you think that is something that you could do?
Maybe manually change some of the values,
discuss with the facility stop, what is the action plan?
And if you&#39;re using the demo database, follow the
same instructions, except for you it&#39;s not a staging
or testing instance.
Thank you very much.
(gentle music)