(lively music)
- [Bob] Good day. This is Bob Pond.
I&#39;m going to be presenting
on how to use the WHO Data Quality Tool.
We have shared with you the document that you see here,
which is a guide on how to use the WHO Data Quality Tool,
and it includes a lot of screenshots
that take you through step by step how
to practice exactly what I&#39;m going to be presenting on.
You see at the beginning of the guide,
there is a URL where you can log into a special instance
of DHIS2 even after this academy.
If you log in there, use the demo,
use the username and password that are on the log in page,
and even those who are not here
at the academy should be able to practice these steps.
In this first presentation,
I&#39;m going to cover how to use the Completeness dashboard.
Then we will go over the Consistency-time dashboard
and onwards with the various sections
that you see here in the table of contents of the tool.
So without delaying further,
let&#39;s take a look at this special instance
of DHIS2, which has been set up for you
to practice data quality assessment.
(lively music)