- [Narrator] So I realize that this has been a summary
of a lot of different concepts.
Often, we would spend much more time
going through this in more detail, you know,
particularly concrete examples of collapsing categories
or maintaining categories over time,
or you know, linking indicators, making sure we can make,
do something with various desegregations,
all the items that we&#39;ve talked about.
You know, we&#39;ve been kind of pushing it
into the smaller session, but you know,
what I really wanna emphasize is that being able
to identify these issues is enough to get started.
If we&#39;re able to have solutions for a lot of these problems
is that we can influence more than others,
then that&#39;s also something we can kind of support.
There are some areas of course,
that are more challenging to support directly
in a country, because even though it&#39;s something we,
as Groups have capacity to support,
it might be more challenging
to share this capacity with others.
And I think that that&#39;s a key, critical challenge.
You know, if we&#39;re going to have
good systems that have good data quality,
then we need to have, you know, the ability to share
a lot of these processes with our partners.
And that is still something we&#39;re struggling with.
So some of the concepts that we&#39;ve talked about,
we went through poor form design, you know,
just looking at some forums
that had in particular desegregations in the wrong place
and had lots of duplicates,
either between different programs
or even within a different program,
or even on the same form itself
when you added up various data elements and categorize them.
So the whole idea here was just to kind of start
to think about these and how you would identify
some of these, right.
It&#39;s not necessarily something you can fix quickly.
You can give recommendations of course,
but you know, this takes time to fix often,
and it also can influence your design to some extent,
if you are able to kind of set up your data elements
in a way where totals, for example,
would give you the correct total
and not give you subsets and, you know,
misinformation about the totals
that you&#39;re actually adding up.
We then talked about a number of customization items
that we could influence.
And there were a number of actually that we could actually
have some greater influence on,
due to processes that we could implement,
mitigation measures we could take,
things that we could review manually.
You know, this included various things
like collapsing categories, sorry, category options,
via category option groups in group sets.
This included things like putting in procedures
for creating our metadata,
making sure that we&#39;re not doing things
on a production instance directly.
Implementing things
that would kind of support their local workflow.
And that is something we can have a bit more influence on.
But then we also talked about maintenance challenges
that were more difficult to handle directly
within an implementation,
and maybe not so much more difficult to handle
from an expert&#39;s perspective,
but actually sharing this knowledge with others
and having others interact with this,
decentralizing these roles and tasks.
This can often be a bit more challenging
because the way DHIS2 is built,
some of these things are impractical to do
using the user interface.
So then how do we teach people, you know,
using other tools?
Is that a whole other discussion,
and what is the effect this has then
if we&#39;re not able to do this
on data quality and data use, if we&#39;re not able
to maintain these systems over time that, you know,
eventually lead to all this problems
with usability essentially,
and being able to find the information
or even just maintain things over time.
We also discussed some tools and processes
to support assessments of DHIS2 to design,
and it might&#39;ve come a surprise to some of you,
but a lot of this is manually done,
as you would have seen as I presented
a lot of these challenges, you know,
it&#39;s really a measure of looking at things in more detail
and going through, either through the interface
or kind of diving through the database
and looking through things in more detail,
but there are some tools and processes
that can help you with this, you know,
but just identifying these things to begin with.
You know, I think it is quite beneficial,
even if you&#39;re not able to fix them directly,
you know, find ways to identify them,
to share them with others and to kind of have them
on the potential roadmap of fixes
to implement in your systems.
So you can improve the data quality
and data use of that system essentially.
But in terms of some tools and processes
we discussed outside of manual work of reviewing things,
we discussed the data integrity check,
which really looks at metadata, not data.
And we also discussed some extended SQL scripts,
but give you a broad summary
of some of the issues that you might see,
particularly with things like blank pieces of metadata
that are just kind of there in your system,
and really might not be serving any purpose anymore.
Things like data sets, data elements,
things like maps that might be shared incorrectly,
or you know, just giving you totals, et cetera.
So there are some examples there,
the SQL file is there and you can run those
if you so choose, but just letting you know
that that option is there to help you perform
a bit more of a detailed assessment of the metadata
that you can compare and contrast,
and kind of give a high-level overview to people
on what some of the issues actually are,
without going through a detailed
manual review potentially.
You know, that could be the start.
And then you start going through things in more detail,
finding out the actual source
of these problems, and then you know,
finding out a strategy to deal with them one by one.
So, this wasn&#39;t meant to provide answers necessarily
to all of these different problems,
but it was meant to kind of provide a wide overview
of what some of these challenges might be.
And it might not seem at first
when you see some of these problems,
that they might affect data quality, but I think
you know, the longer these problems persist,
the more and more challenges you will have
with getting the correct data
out of your system and you know,
if you can&#39;t access the data,
if you don&#39;t even know where to find things in your system,
because it&#39;s so poorly designed, then you know,
this really has a great impact on the quality
of the information and the outputs
that are being produced by said system.
So just keep selling these things in mind
when you&#39;re dealing with your own implementations
and, you know, because of the nature of this
and the way how we went through things
in a lot of quick detail,
it was more informational versus, you know,
having hands on examples for everyone to work through
and really kind of think through these problems
on their own, please feel free to reach out
and ask us any questions about this.
We&#39;re quite happy to discuss this in more detail
and walk through some of these processes a lot more,
if that is something that you would like.