- [Instructor] So, in the previous set of discussions
that I&#39;ve been having about customization,
I think that there&#39;s a lot of ways
we can influence our partners
and our organizations that we&#39;re working with
to think through some of these measures
or at least identify some of these challenges.
Now I&#39;d like to talk about things
where I didn&#39;t have the answer
in a lot of cases in the previous examples,
but I think that they&#39;re relatively,
they&#39;re something that we can influence,
something that we can support,
something that we can transfer to countries.
But then we have other problems
that are to do with maintenance,
that are maybe a bit more challenging to handle,
something we can have less influence on.
And it&#39;s more difficult
to write up procedures on supporting.
So what I want to talk about in this
kind of part of our demonstration
is talking about general maintenance challenges,
challenges with organization unit management,
challenges with users and challenges with sharing.
And where I am coming from from this perspective
is that there are challenges
basically with showing other people
to manage these things in the way they want,
because the user interface
is not really there in the same way it is
for some of the other issues
that I&#39;ve been discussing so far.
So some of the general challenges that we have,
well, one big challenge is batch changes to metadata.
As an example, let&#39;s say we need to correct
the number type of data elements.
So we have a number of data elements
that have the number value type associated with it.
We want to change these to positive or zero integer.
So what&#39;s an easy way for someone
who might not know how to import metadata to do this,
or modified metadata through the API or through SQL
or some other way that maybe we know how to do it?
Maybe us as groups know how to do,
but can often be challenging
to transfer to others, right?
Because we want to impart this knowledge to others,
this is something that system administrators
often have to deal with.
So how do we fix these types of things?
Searching and filtering is another example.
We cannot, for example, list all the data elements
associated with a particular data set or a program.
Now I know there are ways of doing this.
We can do this through the API.
We can do this through an SQL query,
but we cannot easily do this through the maintenance app.
So how do we kind of show others
who might not have that skill set to do this,
even though it&#39;s something we would expect people to do?
Now, so, this is something where influence
on how we approach these things.
It&#39;s not really clear at this point in time.
Dealing with unwanted objects is also often difficult.
Removing data elements with data,
both in aggregate and tracker,
can be quite significantly difficult.
Every time you enter a data value,
there&#39;s then an audit type of value
that gets associated with that data element.
And there&#39;s this basically set of relationships
that is then created.
We have to remove all the dependencies
first in the correct order
or remove them all at once,
depending on what the relationships are like.
And then we can finally remove maybe a data element
we&#39;ve created and just wanted to test.
But this makes development processes
a little bit more challenging than they need to be,
because there&#39;s no cascading delete.
Now at the same time,
there is some good reasons for that perhaps
because you don&#39;t want people
to just go through your system
and remove necessary items,
but it does make it a bit difficult
when you need to remove things
that need to actually be removed.
Removing users is also challenging.
So anytime a user does something,
there&#39;s also relationships that are there
and they might just be associated
with maybe a private or empty dashboard
or something else in your system.
There&#39;s some relationship there
that is not really clear to you why that&#39;s occurring.
So the general processes
that probably many people follow is to disable users
and there might be some reasoning behind that,
but then you might find a user
who&#39;s been inactive for 12 months or two years,
and they&#39;re completely gone.
They&#39;re not associated with the health system anymore,
either, maybe a partner of some kind,
for example, that was accessing the system,
but it&#39;s now located in a completely different place.
And there&#39;s no real easy way
to delete these types of users
or even deleting test users that are just associated
with one or two objects somewhere in your system.
Another kind of potential challenge is merging orgunits.
So over time, if you need to modify orgunits in any way,
there&#39;s no real easy way to do this.
You can, there is some interface for this,
but it does become challenging
to actually implement this in practice
because you can also really mess things up
if you&#39;re not careful.
And of course, when you do any of these operations,
that the feedback is very limited,
particularly through the user interface.
So we can access the log and we can pull out
this information perhaps and see
exactly what the dependency is,
which table it&#39;s referencing,
and what we need to do to remove it.
But this does not really translate well
to working with our partners
and our countries all the time,
compared to a lot of the other operations
that we&#39;ve talked about.
So from that perspective,
let&#39;s take a look at organization unit management first.
So we&#39;ve talked a bit about things like completeness,
and we certainly talked a lot about categories,
desegregations from categories.
Now, organization unit group sets
are another type of desegregation.
And we haven&#39;t talked about that too much so far,
other than knowing that it is a data dimension
that we should consider whether or not we to use
as one directly in our analysis tools,
but using these organization units
to analyze our data is obviously critical.
Everything about completeness associated
with our organization units here,
or sorry, is tied to our organization units.
We also want to be able to desegregate
by various organization unit group sets, right?
So by type, by ownership, whatever it might be,
whatever are the common kind
of organization unit groups and group sets
that you&#39;ve created in your system
for people to desegregate data down further by.
So this become critical to manage.
Obviously, we know organization units
are the backbone of many systems
and there&#39;s all kinds of other areas
that they affect on system design,
but we&#39;ll limit the scope
to kind of more focusing on the data quality
and data use aspect.
So what are the best practices
for actually managing these orgunits?
So, also writing down who does what
for organization units is very important.
So if you have any standard operating procedures on this,
that&#39;s very important to establish.
That&#39;s more of a proactive solution
than kind of trying to fix things after the fact,
because it does help you kind of train people
to do this a bit more,
but actually implementing decentralized
organization unit management can be very difficult.
You might only have a central team
who&#39;s managing literally thousands of organization units.
And this can become challenging
to kind of keep that up to date.
Also for data set assignment,
because data set assignment
has a big effect on completeness,
we often take shortcuts when we do this.
So maybe we&#39;ll just say,
&quot;Assign my data set to the facility level,&quot;
but who&#39;s actually reporting on that data set?
Is it every facility?
Is it a subset of facilities?
Are there facilities who aren&#39;t reporting
and this is contributing to a lower reporting rate?
So these types of things can have a direct effect
actually on what we see in our analysis
when we&#39;re performing various items.
So there are different ways to assign basically.
There&#39;s not good ways through the interface, so, right?
So that&#39;s a bit of a challenge as well.
How do we transfer this down to to others
when everything that might,
when a lot of things I should say
that would be useful perhaps,
we have to come up with a different solution
to implement in practice.