And I am going to now give a quick introductory PowerPoint
just to walk us through
what we&#39;re actually gonna be doing this week.
What are the objectives of this academy?
Well, we really only have five main objectives.
These are quite broad.
But let&#39;s just go through these quickly.
We want you to be able to understand
all of the necessary components of data quality.
Many of you are experts.
Many of you could probably give
a lot of these presentations and lectures yourself.
We appreciate all the various skillsets that are coming in,
and we hope that you&#39;re able to communicate
and talk to each other throughout this week
to be able to share your own insights.
But there are some foundational components of data quality
that everyone needs to appreciate.
And if we collectively understand this,
we can have conversations and build each other up around it.
So that&#39;s a big part of today
is understanding these necessary components of data quality.
This exists outside of DHIS2.
This is everyday work, data quality kind of concepts.
The next objective is that we want you to be able
to know how to use all of the key DHIS2 functionalities
for data quality.
Our promise that there are many functionalities
that you&#39;re probably not using.
There&#39;s a lot of incredible features in DHIS2
that allow you to perform routine,
annual or even notifications and alerts,
automatic data quality checks.
It&#39;s important that you know how to use all of these,
know when to use them, know how to use them,
and then you&#39;re able to apply them to your own projects
and or country implementations.
And I think that&#39;s the third bullet point,
is we really want you to be able to take away
from this academy practical skills
that you can immediately apply.
We don&#39;t want this to just be apps, just theoretical.
We want you to actually be able to say,
hey, I can use that feature.
I can use that tool that Scott or Bob
or whoever just introduced to me,
and I&#39;m gonna be able to immediately use this
and start performing routine data quality checks next week,
later this week.&quot;
We want these things to be immediately implemented.
And we wanna hear about it.
We want to hear about the successes, the failures,
your user stories that you have in using DHIS2
for data quality checks.
But we&#39;re gonna incorporate all of this feedback,
as well as answer any of your questions
into some guidance documentations
and to improve this academy going forward.
The second to last bullet point here
is we wanna make sure that you are exposed
to a variety of use cases and examples.
There are many really wonderful examples
and stories that exist out there of people using DHIS2
for data quality checks,
and really utilizing the features to the max.
And that&#39;s what we wanna expose you to.
So it&#39;s one thing for me to kind of go through everything
in theory, it&#39;s a very different,
an extremely useful thing for you to be able to see people
actually doing it.
And so throughout the week,
you&#39;re going to be seeing
all of the several different data quality user stories,
and you can start to build up
your own data quality strategies and plans
around what other people have done.
There&#39;s a whole world of DHIS2 users out there,
many, many countries doing different things.
You don&#39;t have to reinvent the wheel.
You can just build on top of what good practices
other people have already done.
The final point, and this is the one
that I really wanna kind of drive home as much as possible
is we wanna build a DHIS2 community
of practice around data quality.
Everyone is talking about data use, data use, data use.
Lots of folks focus on individual disease programs,
patient tracking.
But there doesn&#39;t really exist
a strong DHIS2 community of practice
that&#39;s principally concerned with data quality.
And of course, we appreciate that without data quality,
people aren&#39;t gonna use data.
All of the data that&#39;s coming in
from these various disease programs and projects,
it&#39;s not gonna be useful, it&#39;s not gonna be reliable.
And so just as much as we focus on all the other aspects
of the different types of data we get in,
the different way to look at data and visualize data,
it&#39;s equally as important, if not more so,
to also have a group focused on data quality
and how do we address data quality in DHIS2?