(upbeat music)
- [Instructor] I&#39;m going to present
how you can quickly train staff at district
and even facility level to make use every month
of the WHO Data Quality Tool.
First, I want to share with you a single slide
that explains why data quality assurance
should be decentralized and it should be routine.
Let me define some of these terms.
By data quality assurance, I mean a continuous process
of checking the quality of the data
and investigating where there are suspicious values
and if necessary editing the data to remove any errors.
By decentralized, we mean that data quality assurance
is best done at the level of the district
and the health facility.
And this process should be routine,
that is should be done every month
as data are entered into the system.
This is a bottom up approach to data quality assurance.
It is more efficient for data quality problems to be fixed
closer to where the data are first recorded and reported,
rather than wait for staff at higher levels,
regional or national to review and attempt
to fix these data quality problems.
This is for several reasons.
First of all, at the district level,
the volume of data to review is smaller,
especially if the data are reviewed every month
rather than waiting months later to identify
and investigate suspicious values.
Secondly, investigation of suspicious values
is more practical for staff at a decentralized level.
The district staff have access to the paper records.
They have established relationships with the facility staff,
and it can more easily communicate with them
to undertake investigations.
And finally, DHIS2 data belong to the district
and district staff have the permission to edit them
and remove any errors.
So let&#39;s get started with a demonstration of how district
and perhaps facility staff, can be trained quickly
to use the DHIS2 data quality review tools.
First of all, the user needs to understand
how to launch the WHO Data Quality Tool.
Users at district level do not need to understand how to use
all the functions of the WHO Data Quality Tool.
In fact, they don&#39;t necessarily need to be instructed
in how to use all of the four tabs of the Dashboard.
They can simply understand the power of the outliers page
of the Dashboard.
They will first need a bit of orientation
to the settings window of the Dashboard.
They should understand
that they can make the settings window appear
and disappear by clicking on the settings icon.
For review of the quality of data at district level,
it&#39;s best to configure a special group of indicators
that are most important for review at district level.
So the data quality reviewer should set data
to district group and they should set period to last month
if the review is being done at the end of the month
when you have data entered for last month.
If review is done at the beginning of the month,
and it&#39;s probably best to set the period
to the month before last.
Now, how should the organization unit
of the settings window be configured?
If the user is at the level of the district,
then the organization unit is going to automatically be set
to show the data just for their district.
However, if you are practicing the instructions
of district staff at national level,
you&#39;ll have to configure the boundary
of the organization unit to the specific district
that you are supporting for data quality review.
In this case, we&#39;ve selected district A-1.
Again at district level,
they won&#39;t have to go through this process
because DHIS2 will automatically set the window
to show data only for their district.
The dis-aggregation should ideally be set to facility level.
In the case of this DHIS2 instance,
facility is the only level below district.
So the desegregation is automatically set to facility
as soon as we set the district,
as soon as we set the boundary to a single district.
But you may have two levels below the level of the district,
in which case the menu will show those two levels
and you should select facility.
By dis-aggregating to facility,
we&#39;ll see how it simplifies the process
for the person doing the data quality review
at district level.
To free up space on the screen,
it&#39;s best to hide the settings window.
Users at district level will need a bit of explanation
to understand the table, the results table that appears.
They&#39;ll need to understand that all of the data
are for their district and that each row represents data
for one health facility in their district
and one of the indicators in the district group.
The data and the row are for the 12 months
leading up to the period that has been selected.
Users need to understand that values that are highlighted
in red are suspicious and cells that are pale yellow,
have missing values.
The results table is lengthy,
so users need to understand how to filter it
in order to identify only the most suspicious values.
And the filtering process involves as we have learned
to click on options,
and then they can include the Z-score in the table.
Users need to understand that the Z-score
is simply a measure of how suspicious the value in red
is with a higher Z-score.
In this case, the modified Z-score
showing that the value is more suspicious.
We can now filter the table to show only values
that have a modified Z-score that is quite high
by clicking on outliers and modified Z-score and extreme.
We now have a relatively small table of the most important,
suspicious values for the reviewer
at district level to investigate.
They should follow up on at least the first page
of the filtered results table.
For some of these values, let&#39;s take for example,
the value that is highlighted in red in the first row.
And the user can be taught how to use the menu icon
and click on visualize in order to see this chart.
For this value, they may have an explanation.
They may understand that this facility
indeed had an increase in out-patient attendance.
So not all values that are highlighted in red
will require extensive investigation.
But the point is, that the data quality reviewer,
needs to understand why it is that that value
is so different from the other values in the row.
Again, they can be taught how to click on the menu icon
at the end of a row and visual utilize.
And they will almost certainly see that some of the values
that are highlighted in red are so suspicious
that they are likely erroneous, that they are errors,
and deserve to be followed up with a phone call
or some other communication to people
at facility level.
In addition to investigating the suspicious values,
the reviewer at district level
needs to look into the most important missing values
and to use the outlier tab to identify those missing values,
they should be taught to turn off the filter,
click on missing data,
and now the results table shows at the top.
Those indicators and those health facilities,
which have the largest volume of missing data.
And it may be worthwhile for them to make attempts
to mobilize these additional data context in this case,
the district hospital,
and see if they can get these missing reports.
After all, the values from the district hospital are so high
that if the reports are missing,
it will affect the total performance measurement
as measured at the district level.
Finally, the user at district level should understand
how to use the download button,
so that they can download to their computer
and visualize a spreadsheet that they can use
even when they are not connected to the internet.
(phone rings)
And they could print this out
and make use of it in supervision.
The user at district level may already understand how to use
the sorting functions of Excel,
but you might need to refresh them
that if they click on data and then sort this table,
can be sorted according to the values of one row.
In this case, let&#39;s select the maximum modified Z-score
and largest to smallest,
and now we see at the top the values
that are most suspicious.
Or they might filter this
to find the most important missing values
sorting in this case, by the modified,
by the gap weight, largest to smallest.
And here again, we see the facilities that are responsible
for the most important missing data.
In summary, to instruct staff at district or facility level
to use the tool in a short amount of time,
perhaps even during the supervision visit,
the instruction should focus on how they can quickly learn
how to make use of the outlier page of the Dashboard,
and how they can by screening the data
routinely every month, identify and investigate
the most important missing and suspicious values.
And in this way,
maintain the quality of the data bottom up approach.
(upbeat music)