(smooth jazz)
- [Norah] This is the session on the Data Quality Review.
And your report is part of the Data Quality Online Academy.
So there are two aspects that we are going to talk about
in this session.
The first one is the annual report
using the WHO DQ Tool,
and then secondly the process
of actually reviewing your data
and making the appropriate corrections.
So if we start back at the WHO DQ Tool,
your first question is, have you installed it?
Has it been customized or have you left it as the default?
Again, brings up the question,
who&#39;s responsible for this customization.
Only the HMIS Team or the M&amp;E Team,
the program managers.
Who all is involved?
If we take the purpose of this report,
who needs it and why do they need it?
And out of this report,
the actions taken or are any actions going to be taken
that result in demonstrable changes?
So the bottom line is does this report change anything
or does it just become a nice report in a glossy folder
stored in a glass cabinet?
The second aspect of this data quality review
is to look at the data and to fix it.
And it&#39;s about checking for outliers and obvious data errors
and then correcting them.
Checking for missing months of data
and then filling them in.
Specifically if you know a facility has worked,
but no pieces of paper have arrived.
On the tool bar for the WHO DQ Tool,
there&#39;s something that says Annual Report.
You click that open and the first option you have is data
and you can select a group.
It could be Core, it could be Immunization,
it could be Maternal Health,
for the period.
You then select the year
that you want to run the annual report for
and how many years before that
do you want as reference so that there is some background.
And then you select the organization unit.
This could be the whole country,
sub-level, sub-national, or sub-national times two.
The choice again is always yours.
You will then get a report that is completed
and it will show up under in the WHO DQ Tool.
You then have the option of printing the report
and you will be able to save it as a PDF.
So this report, the one I ran was nine pages.
Looks at completeness, timeliness, facility reporting
completeness of indicator data, and all of guidance
and indicators showing you what&#39;s helping
with completeness, with timeliness of the data.
So this is what this report looks like.
So the questions are,
so here&#39;s this report.
Is this report helpful?
If it&#39;s helpful, for who is it helpful?
What guidance can you gain from this report?
And is this report a guarantee that the data
is correct, complete, consistent, and timely?
So all four of things that are whole
are looked at with part of the development
of an annual report on data quality
using the DQ Tool.
The second section of this presentation
looks at the data quality review and data cleaning.
And the use case we&#39;re going to talk about is South Sudan.
Fortunately, or unfortunately it was them using DHIS 1.4,
not DHIS 2.
We are still looking for use cases with DHIS 2.
And it was done for the years 2012, 2013, 2014 data
and here is a map of South Sudan,
and a flag if you don&#39;t recollect it.
So the first question is why do we bother to clean the data?
And the problem is that poor quality data
makes the data unusable.
You can&#39;t use it for accurately estimating indicators,
coverage of performance, coverage of service delivery,
and that means that all that effort that you went into
to create and to collect and to capture
and to clean the data from all the facilities,
there is no return.
So the data is collected, but it&#39;s not usable.
We also know that if there are
a few obvious data entry errors,
people can take this as a sign
that all the data is untrustworthy.
And that we know is not true.
Experience has shown that on the whole,
generally HMIS data is generally reliable.
It&#39;s not perfect, it will never be perfect,
but it should be good enough so that it can be used.
If we go about correcting any of the obvious errors
that we see, the data then becomes usable and acceptable.
And usable data, and acceptable data
is much better than unusable data which has no value.
Just stores up space in the computer and costs money.
What we do know is that in spite of everybody saying,
well we do validation checks
and we have quarterly data reviews,
data errors do creep in
and they frequently remain undetected and uncorrected
and stay there to haunt you for years.
And as we said, South Sudan was using DHIS 1.4
at the time of the data cleaning process.
So some background to what happened in South Sudan.
First of all, because a minimum indicator based dataset
implemented in 2011, so it was based on indicators
and from the indicators we defined the data elements,
we put them into data collection tools
and it was two pages with one page for EPI.
And there was a decision made in 2013
to provide a report for 2012, the Annual HMIS Report
because we now had a year of data.
However, on reviewing this data,
it quickly became apparent that the data
was not good enough to be used.
We could not use it for the annual report.
And so the decision was made
that we would go back and we would clean the data
so that it would become usable.
And so this was then done at state level, some national
and we also did combine some states for convenience
just so that in terms of time
and in terms of distance and travel.
Present at these data cleanup workshops
was the State M&amp;E Officer, and the County M&amp;E Officer
for each county and they were responsible
for correcting the data.
Because it was the county, they knew
what was going on in their area.
They could easily contact the facility people
responsible and ask questions.
They did all of that work about fixing the data.
It took approximately four to five days per group of States
and it was a really labor intensive process
with everybody working from early in the morning
to late in the afternoon in the heat and dust
of South Sudan to get this work done.
So, we first made some crucial decisions.
The first one was that we were going to
concentrate on the headcount.
Knowing how many people access the health services
is crucial to understanding how much money you have,
how many resources you need.
So headcount.
Then we looked at children
with diarrhea, pneumonia, and malaria.
Because we&#39;re also defining a vulnerable population.
We then looked at maternal health in terms of
anti-natal visits, deliveries, live births, IPTP
and the things relating to maternal health
because we also see that those were the crucial things
to have correct.
We ran validation rules, absolute and statisticals
were run and any violations triggered were noted.
The same process that we use in DHIS2.
Extreme outliers were identified
and corrected using tools in 1.4,
which include interpolation and regression analysis.
Interpolation is making an educated guess
based on data before and data after.
And regression analysis, we&#39;re not going into
a mathematical discussion this afternoon on this.
The second process was we would concentrate
on replacing the missing months of data.
In other words, we will know that a facility worked,
but for some unknown reason,
the piece of paper never arrived.
And there are many explanations and reasons for that.
Insecurity, unable to travel, no stop, whatever
but we know the facility worked
so we professed missing data.
And when we looked at validation rules
with compulsory pairing.
In other words, if you have one you must have the other.
An example would be diarrhea treated
must have diarrhea reported.
We fixed those up.
We look for extreme outliers and corrected those
at facility level.
Specifically if a value materially altered the indicator.
If it skewed the indicator, it became important enough
to correct the data.
And in this process, we looked both at raw data
and at indicators.
Because frequently on raw data,
you may not see that something is wrong.
But when you look at it as an indicator,
that that data element is part of an indicator,
it becomes apparent that something is not right.
So some of the actions
and some of the things that we did.
We developed a decision tree for data outliers.
If it was out of range and then there was the services,
first of all look did the data elements hang together?
Did they make sense when you looked at them?
Then, using regression we recalculated
a value that made no sense.
If the data elements did not hang together,
in other words they made no sense,
we would recalculate the key data elements.
The most important ones and provide a comment.
Again, using data from previous months and months after.
And if we had data, there was no services
that were provided by the health facility,
we would just delete it.
So this is just some of the ways we looked
at trying to fix outlier data.
Trying to fix missing data.
We looked at was the facility
actually providing any services?
And if it wasn&#39;t, then we closed it.
If we realized that the facility did not work for one month
or maybe even two months due to security,
due to no staffing, whatever,
but if the services were not provided,
we wrote a zero and we gave a comment.
So that was no longer missing data.
The facility did not function so it&#39;s not missing data.
And if we said that services were provided
by the health facility, and the data was missing,
we corrected it using interpolation
and regression analysis to fill in the gaps.
So why was it possible to do this in South Sudan?
Well, there were a few reasons.
First of all, it was a very, very small dataset.
It was only two pages.
The local staff of M&amp;E offices were eager to be responsible
and fix their own data.
They wanted good, clean data.
And they took great pride in having data with no violations.
And there was a lot of hands on support and supervision
to guide people through this process.
Well what were some of the results?
First of all, we had cleaned data for three years
resulting in an annual report for each year.
How many of your countries are doing an annual report
each year for your HMIS data?
Because we had data for three years,
we were able to measure service delivery over time.
Were counties and states getting better,
were they staying the same?
And one of the most crucial aspects for us,
the development of the capacity and the knowledge
of the M&amp;E staff regarding both HMIS and DHIS.
And as we all know, when you start out in a country
one of the biggest issues is an updated facility list
so a lot of work went into fixing a facility list.
So in conclusion, has all the missing data,
where you know a facility worked
but there&#39;s no report been added in?
Have you fixed all your outliers?
Have all your validation rules been fixed or explained?
And then the question is
whether WHO takes responsibility for this?
Is it important to do this in your situation?
And so we are left with two exercises.
The first one is about the WHO Annual Report.
So you either use your own country&#39;s DHIS2 instance
or the demo one.
Run the annual report for a selected OU unit
and Data Elemental Indicator Group.
Print it, which will allow you to download in PDF format.
Then review it and discuss it.
How can you use this report?
We know that there are quite a few of you
working in the same country
and I think that this would be a very nice exercise for you
as a group to have a look.
And then in terms of the data review and corrections,
either your own DHIS2 or the demo instance.
Using the WHO DQ Tool, find the missing data and outliers.
What needs to happen to replace these missing values
or correct the obvious data outliers?
And here&#39;s the difficult question,
how will you decide what the new value should be?
Thank you.
(smooth jazz)