(upbeat music)
- As we have seen, the dashboard
of the data quality tool is easy to use.
A limitation of the dashboard of the application, however,
is that it can only be used to review
those indicators or data elements
for which the dashboard has been configured.
We&#39;ll next see how we can use the analysis function
of the WHO data quality tool
to look for outliers or inconsistencies
between any data elements which have data in the dhis2,
let&#39;s start by looking at how we use analysis consistency.
When we select analysis consistency,
a window appears asking us to select the type
of consistency we want to analyze.
Consistency over time is equivalent
to what we saw on the consistency time dashboard.
Whereas consistency between indicators is the equivalent
of what we saw on the consistency data dashboard.
For the example I will now present,
we want to analyze further dropout rates, and to do that
we select consistency between indicators,
then click on expected result.
And it&#39;s now possible to select dropout
as the type of analysis.
We next need to decide which two indicators
will define the dropout rate.
Let&#39;s look at the Penta 1 to Penta 3 dropout rate.
To do that, we have to first select Penta 1.
And for that, we need to find out which indicator,
which data element group to select.
And if we select immunization,
we find that Penta 1 given before 12 months of age
is a data element in the immunization, eight element group.
Next, we need to select Penta 3
given before 12 months of age.
Again, we need to select the data element group,
immunization.
And the immunization data element group includes
Penta third doses given before 12 months of age.
So already you see some of the challenge
of using the analysis function,
in that we need to configure it
and to configure it, we need to know
what is the data element group or indicator group
we want to select from, what is the data element
or indicator we want to select and so forth.
This configuration requires that the user be familiar
with how the data sets are organized.
So this is not a function that can easily be used
by the beginner,
but we&#39;ve now set up to look at the dropout rate
between Penta 1, given before 12 months,
and Penta 3, given before 12 months.
Now we only need to select the period,
let&#39;s select last month, last year, as the period
and disaggregate by district, then click on analyze.
The screen shows us a chart
that is identical to what we saw
on the consistency data dashboard.
But, in addition to this histogram with one bar
for each district and two districts
that have a negative dropout rate,
we have a table, and the table shows us the number
of first doses of Penta given by each district
and the number of third doses given by each district.
And it shows this for these two districts
with negative dropout rates,
that the number of third doses given in 2019
was greater than the number of first doses.
So we get this additional information
when we use the analysis function.
We can select one of these districts
by clicking on the row and the row turns light yellow.
When we do that,
a table with a single row
for district A-2 appears at the bottom of the screen
and a chart showing,
for each month over the 12 month period,
the value of Penta 1 and the value of Penta 3,
and notice what we see.
For most months, we see that district A-2 reported
a higher number of third doses of Penta
than first doses of Penta.
For example, in may of 2019, 1063 first doses,
but 1,139 third doses.
So district A-2 has a consistent practice
of reporting higher numbers of third doses of Penta vaccine,
than first doses of Penta vaccine.
And then for November of the 12 month period,
there&#39;s this quite suspicious value that may be due
to an error in data entry because the number
of third doses is so much greater
than the number of first doses.
But for these other months,
there seems to be some habit of reporting higher numbers
of third doses, just a bit higher
than first doses of Penta vaccine.
We can continue the investigation by clicking
on the menu icon at the end of this single row.
And we&#39;re allowed to drill down.
What we now see is a histogram
that disaggregates the Penta 1
to Penta 3 dropout rate from 2019,
by individual health facility.
And we see that almost all the health facilities
of district A-2 have been reporting higher numbers
of third doses than first doses of Penta vaccine.
Most all of the facilities have negative dropout rates.
We can again, select one of these health facilities,
one of these rows
and look at the trend over the 12 month period
and the values for the self facility.
And we see that this one facility, 197,
again, appears to have some kind of a very suspicious value
that is probably erroneous,
where it has reported 10 times as many third doses
as first doses of Penta vaccine.
So in summary, by using the analysis function
and looking at analysis of dropout rates,
we get additional information that allows us to investigate
and determine is the negative dropout rate
for a district due to a single erroneous value,
a single outlier such as here,
or is it due to a pattern, amongst
many different health facilities,
and for many different months of reporting higher numbers
of third doses than first doses.
Let&#39;s look at one more example before we then see
how we can use analysis to look at outliers.
With this example, we&#39;re going to look
at analysis between indicators,
but this time we&#39;re going to look at two indicators
that we expect to be roughly equivalent.
And in this case, we&#39;re going to compare third doses
of Penta vaccine,
to third doses of OPV vaccine.
These two vaccines are typically given on the same visit,
so we expect the values to be roughly the same.
Again, setting period to 2019,
disaggregation to district, click on analyze.
And we see a scatter plot,
which reassures us that indeed, for all of the districts,
the value of third doses of Penta vaccine is closely related
to the value of third doses of OPV vaccine.
And we could, if we wanted to, do some investigation.
Although, the fact that all of these dots are
between the two gray lines reassures us.
Let&#39;s look next at how to use the analysis function
to check for outliers and missing data.
The function works just as the outlier dashboard does,
except it is much more flexible in that it allows us
to select any data element at all,
not just the ones that are configured for the dashboard.
In fact, we could select from
multiple data sets and multiple data element groups.
We could even
select
all data elements
from a data element group.
Set period to last 12 months,
organization unit to disaggregation by district, analyze,
we&#39;re waiting for the data to process.
And we get the table,
showing us all of the suspicious values
for the selected data elements.
It has the same options as with the outlier dashboard.
So we can filter to identify only the most suspicious values
or we can filter, if we are at facility level.
We can use it to identify facilities
that have large amounts of missing data.
In summary, the analysis function works in a way
that is quite similar to the dashboard
of the WHO data quality tool,
but it is much more flexible.
The price that you pay for using the analysis function is
that you have to configure it and to do that,
you need to be familiar with how the data sets are organized
and you need to find just the data element or indicator
that is most appropriate for the analysis.
(upbeat music)