- [Pamod] In this session, what we are going to discuss
is about Data Quality Practices in Sri Lanka.
So, what I hope to do in this session is that,
I will be taking two examples,
two implementations in Sri Lanka.
One is from the RMNCAH program,
and the other one is from the nutrition program.
And I&#39;m going to discuss how these elements
of ensuring data quality has been applied
in these two implementations.
So the first scenario,
or the first use case that I&#39;m going to talk about
is the RMNCAH program in Sri Lanka.
So this in fact, was one of the major DHS implementations
in Sri Lanka, and it took us a lot of efforts
to get this implemented.
The main reason being,
the paper-based data collection system of RMNCAH
has been a well-established system
for more than three decades.
So trying to introduce a digital system,
and also trying to ensure at least the minimum data quality
that was already there in the paper-based system
was a major challenge.
So let us see how we apply these concepts of data quality
while we were planning the implementation.
So we might feel that ensuring data quality
is a very complicated task,
but I will show you how simple you can start.
So for example, the first thing that we did was,
we concentrated about data quality
while we were designing the data entry forms.
So one simple step that we ensured was that,
because we were trying to introduce this digital system
to an already existing paper-based system,
we tried to adhere to the well-established data flows.
In simple words, what we tried to do is,
the data entry interfaces or the data forms,
in the DHIS2, the datasets,
we tried to make the use interfaces as much as similar
to the existing paper-based format.
I mean, we always say
that you have to optimize the data collection forms.
But while ensuring that,
we tried to keep the flow of the data,
the order in which it appear,
the same as how it is in data entry forms.
So by doing that, we can minimize the random errors
that data entry people might do,
because they just have to follow the same workflow
that they are doing while entering data into paper formats.
So for this instance,
what we created was a custom data entry form,
not a section or standard DHIS2 dataset,
but it was a custom form.
So let me show you, first of all,
now this is the paper format that we had in the RMNCAH,
the main aggregate data collection form.
You can see it&#39;s a very complicated form.
There are so many data items or data elements.
And of course, most of these columns that you see here
are the periods.
So the columns of course, do not come into this,
our data entry interface, but what I&#39;m talking here
is about having this same model as how it is appearing
in the paper format.
And we had the same workflow,
while we did the transition to the digital format.
So here what you&#39;re seeing is our DHIS2 custom dataset,
or data entry form, and please excuse me for the language.
The forms are in local language,
but what I want to highlight is the same order
that we have it in the data format,
we have been following in DHIS2 dataset as well.
Even though we have done some slight modifications,
for example, we have set up here the vertical tabs
to capture this large amount of data,
but the flow of information capture remains the same.
And the next thing is,
sometimes when we are designing forms,
we cannot actually replicate the paper forms into the DHIS2.
There are some optimizations that we have to do,
especially like there are things
like duplicate data collection,
and there are so many things that we don&#39;t do
in an optimum way in paper-based collection,
but which we can optimize
when we are creating the datasets in DHIS2.
So for example, in the mental health system,
this is the paper form that we are using.
But when we were trying to convert that into DHIS2,
what we actually did was, we optimized the data form.
And at the same time, we had the opportunity of modifying
the existing paper-based data collection form,
so that it kind of added to the quality of data
that is collected.
For example, now this is the modified paper-based form
that we were able to create,
because when we&#39;ve been one step ahead,
this is the DHIS2-based data collection form.
So to minimally confuse the users
and at the point of generation of data,
we tried to use the same data collection form
as we have been in DHIS2.
So what we did was,
we kind of modified the existing paper-based form
to be an optimized paper form.
This is another example of the same mental health system,
where we have optimized the data collection forms, right?
And sometimes, of course, in this RHMIS system
there were requirements such as like,
when we wanted to collect these WHO MNH Indicators,
we did not have a paper-based form to start with.
So there of course, we had the luxury of designing
of a paper-based form also from the scratch,
which was kind of easy because this is the DHIS2 dataset,
or rather the event form.
And that one, based on that one,
so when designing that one,
we were able to follow the best practices.
And then we came back and we designed a new paper form
for the collection of data,
because most of the institutes
that are involved with our MCH system,
they do not capture the data, the electronic system
at the point of generation.
So usually the data entry happens on a paper-based form,
and then that is copied into the DHIS2.
Right, and I mean, for the expanding on this,
one thing that we had to make sure,
like when we are having this digital transformation
from paper system to the electronic system
is to minimally interrupt the workflow.
Because the thing is, I think that should be the context
of most of the countries,
because you may have a well-established paper format.
And when you are trying to introduce the digital system,
we should try to minimally disrupt the existing data flow.
It&#39;s like, the government&#39;s motive
is to provide better health, not only data.
So if you are just trying to enhance the data,
I mean, the quality of data
by introducing the digital system,
and at the same time,
if you are kind of disrupting an existing data flow,
that will have a lot of resistance during the implementation
from so many stakeholders.
So the other thing that we tried to do with this is that,
in our paper-based system in Sri Lanka,
we had these different approval levels.
So those were inherent data quality measures
that were there at field levels.
So when we were introducing DHIS2, what we did was,
we did not try to capture data to the digital system
just at the same time.
So we preserved the paper-based system and we kind of,
as they have to copy the data that is captured
in the paper-based system into the digital system,
and also the approval workflows that were already there,
we tried to implement the DHIS2,
so that there was one step verification
before the data goes higher up along the health hierarchy.
So that the data approval workflows
was a major contribute in factor,
ensuring data quality in the CRHIMS
or the digital MCH system.
We conducted the training programs.
In fact like, well, what you&#39;re seeing here
is one of our field level training program,
and the person who was in the front
is the one who was leading this entire MCH system
Dr. Kaushal, I think she&#39;s a participant
in this academy also.
We are so much grateful to her and her team
for implementing all of this, the data quality practices
in her system.
So here the data quality measures
and how they should capture data, and at that point,
how to ensure data quality was an inherent component
during these training programs
that we conducted at field level.
So what we did was we had a national team,
we&#39;re kind of master trainers,
and we were able to replicate the training programs
using our trainers who are at a field level.
So all these training programs had a special emphasis
on ensuring data quality.
Like for example, especially at the point of generation,
point of capture of data,
there were so many data quality measures,
which I will be showing you in non-exclusive slides.
So they have a special emphasis that we put on data quality
during this and use the training program.
And one other thing about ensuring data quality
is to have proper user manual, so SOPs.
The thing is like the DHIS2
has its own extensive user guide,
which like I&#39;m sure that they confuse many end-users
if you just ask these end-users to refer
the DHIS2 user manual which is available online.
So that of course didn&#39;t work and we realized that.
So what we did was we created the end-user manual,
which is of course it&#39;s a very comprehensive end-user manual
with the screenshots and also like explaining everything
in very simple manner
which could be comprehended by end-users.
So this end-user manual was something that we handed over
to the end-users during our training programs,
which they can keep at their work places and they can refer.
But the thing is like,
this is a kind of a comprehensive user manual,
which maybe a bit too much
when you are just trying to find something real quick
when you are entering data at your desk.
So for that purpose, we had another type of manual,
which I&#39;ll show you in a while.
And the other thing is, there were so many SOPs
that we created before we tried to implement the system.
Because like, we understood initially
that when you are having this digital transformation
from paper-based system,
which was kind of list I&#39;ve issued to the digital system,
there may be a lot of resistance that we might encounter
because for the simple reason
that users don&#39;t like too much of change.
So we try to simplify everything so that to make sure
that the end-users don&#39;t see this learning curve
as a very difficult one.
So this is where we had different levels of SOPs.
So this one that you&#39;re seeing is a checklist
that all the facilities should have
before entering data into the system.
So here we try to explain everything in a simple way,
and this we have asked them to keep
by the side of the computer that they&#39;re using
for data entry.
But the one that we have asked them
either to keep at all times next to their computers
or else to paste it on the wall where they&#39;re entering data
is this ones.
So these are single page end-user manuals or SOPs
that we have created just specifically to given tasks.
So these kinds of, I mean like how this helps
in data quality is that the thing is like,
if you perceive using a system as a kind of a difficult one,
then there is high chance that,
I mean, that&#39;s this is what we have seen,
that there is a high chance that they might make mistakes.
So having these specific SOPs and the use of manuals
with the end-users kind of really contributed
to ensuring the perceptive ease of use of this system,
which of course contributed to the data quality in the end.
So these kinds of manuals or SOPs
we had for each of these tasks,
and this is exactly what we followed there
in our COVID implementation,
which was kind of a rapid implementation from the learnings
that we had from other MCH system.
And this is another single page user document
that the MCH system is using.
And then, we also tried to use
remote administration software.
So remote desktop softwares like TeamViwer.
Because like, how it really contributed us
in ensuring data quality is that,
what we saw was that
when we are trying to provide support to end-users,
there were some issues where they cannot actually explain
even on the phone.
So if they actually cannot solve their problem,
they try to enter data which might be a radiance, right?
Because if they would assume
that this would be the proper way of using,
and which is not exactly the correct thing.
So here we are using TeamViwer as a tool
where we can connect from national level
to the end-users computer and assist them in troubleshoot.
So with this, we were able to in fact,
observe the data, I mean,
like how they are entering data,
what other mistakes that they are doing,
as well as it helped us in troubleshooting
when they&#39;re having issues.
So for this one also we had a separate SOPs that we created.
And the other thing that really helped us
in ensuring that data entry is timely and data entry users
are having minimal issues is that, the user support.
So for the, to provide the user support,
we had this three tier model.
So here what happens is we had this,
the initial communication method
which should happen using fax or hotline
or else we are using this instant messaging platforms
such as Wiver.
So there of course, they can reach over initial help desk
for for simple troubleshooting.
They did public health related issues,
or else very technological issues.
Like this will be attended at tier one.
And then in case they cannot settle there,
they&#39;ll be directed to the tier two
where we have a medical officer in public health,
as well as our ICT officer
will be attending to these issues.
And if they can&#39;t also solve them,
we have the consultant committee divisions
who are attending this technical matters
related to public health issues.
And the medical officer in health informatics
who is going to attend to the very technical
or technological issues.
So this way, it really helped us in ensuring
that all the issues the end-users are having are attended.
And when it comes to specific data quality measures
that are already there in DHIS2,
we are mainly using most of these same MCH datasets,
their validation rules and compulsory data elements.
In addition, we are also using the data.
But we are in the process of incorporating min-max,
predictors, WHO Data Quality Tools, score cards,
and legends in this MCH instances.
But like why there is a delay is that,
we are trying to match all these tools that are there
into the existing the workflows
so that is why it is taking some time.
But this is our planning over the next a one year&#39;s time
to incorporate all this into the MCH data flow.
And when it comes to review and feedback,
we identify review and feedback as a major measure
in ensuring data quality.
So what we do is we have created dashboards
and provided our end-users instructions
on how they should be following and adhering this dashboard.
So they are supposed to use this monitoring Dashboards
at facility level, district level,
provincial level and at national level.
So there have been clear instructions that we have provided
to the end-users on how to use these dashboards.
And in addition, we have the national level staff
who will be drilling down and conducting distributes
from time to time,
just make sure that whether there are any data quality
or any major data quality issues,
which are happening at a field level.
Because like, this is kind of like a secondary level
of monitoring for the district level staff,
which we are doing at national level.
And to compliment this, we have regular reviews,
which is happening at the PHM is the field level,
public health midwife level,
or medical officer of health is kind of like
sub-district level, RBHS is the district level
and at the country level
in this frequencies that we have mentioned.
So how this happen is that,
now, what you are seeing here
is kind of like a district level review
where all the medical doctors who are in charge
of all these sub-districts will come to this place
along with few public health field level staff
and we are doing a comprehensive reading.
So these are, and one key thing is that,
for all these reviews,
we are using the DHIS2-based MCH system.
So we will be displaying the dashboards
and they have to comment on any of the data quality issues
that they expect panel from national level are asking.
Now these reviews did not stop
even during the COVID pandemic.
What actually happened was like,
it was another opportunity for us to further explore
what are the avenues which are available
to conduct these online.
So what we did was we organized the Zoom platform
that we have, and through the Zoom,
we were able to conduct this monthly and quarterly review
at district level using the remote technology.
So none of these review activities have stopped
even during the COVID-19 pandemic.
So what you&#39;re seeing here is the district level staff
who were joining through Zoom,
and then a certain level of staff
who are kind of volunteering whatever they are presenting.
Right, and these data that we have gathered
through our MCH system is produced as an annual report
from the Ministry of Health.
And we also have a MCH quantity report.
For all these reports,
the data is coming through the DHIS2-based system
and this is why like, once these reports are public
are made public, the institute and the ministry
has to hold the responsibility.
So that is why we are trying to ensure data quality
in our DHIS2-based system,
because the reports are actually generated
through this system only.
Right, so these are some data quality measures
that we have insured in our MCH system.
So with this, I&#39;m going to move on to our second example,
which is the nutrition monitoring system.
Right, so this of course was the requirement
which is coming from the presidential secretariat level
of Sri Lanka, where the requirement was to identify children
who are having nutrition-related problems at field level,
and to obtain multi-sector support to address them
at field level.
But then the information had to be connected
and verified and transmitted
all the way up to the national level
and shared with the multi-sector state.
So the major functionality of this system
was to register the children with malnutrition
at field level.
And then they wanted to routinely monitor and track
the nutritional parameters such as height and weight
and household total risk factors.
So these are the routinely monitored components,
and then obtain household geo locations,
and also perform analytics (indistinct)
and the mobile users,
and to synchronize the data
which is collected at field level with the central server
and then share with the stakeholders.
So to achieve all these requirements,
we felt that it was the mobile technology
that we have to use and the traditional use of laptops
and computers to enter data will not really work
because the data has to be captured at individual level
at field level.
So this requirement of course,
came around four to five years back.
So at that time, the DHIS2 Android native mobile application
was not that mature
because nowadays it is having so many useful features.
But those days, there were some restrictions
to fulfill these functionalities
that were required by the program.
So what happened was this public health midwife
who&#39;s a field level health stuff,
a health worker will collect data at field level,
which is then synchronized
into the DHIS2-based central server,
and which could be accessed by their supervising officers
and all the staff at district and national level
using the web interface.
And once this data is sent by the midwife,
their immediate surprising officer
who is the medical office of health
or the applicant nursing sisters should validate that data,
and the data had to be returned back.
I mean, this validation once it happens only,
the data could be shared with all the stakeholders
who are involved at the process.
So to do this, of course,
what we did was to have this design,
this custom Android application due to the obvious reason
that some of these requirements were not be able to meet
by the DHIS2 Android application at the time.
Right, so let&#39;s quickly look at few data quality measures
that were in place in this Android mobile application
while capturing data.
So the first thing is like, there were some,
there were a few simple interfaces.
And now as you can see here,
these are few interfaces that we used
and simplifying interfaces itself
was identified as one major factor
to enhance the compliance of the end-users
who are using the system, this is field and stuff,
and also enhance the data quality.
Because like, what we found out from our study was that,
when you have very complicated workflows
and very crowded interfaces,
it contributed adversely to the data quality
because the end-users can make lots of mistakes
because they just become confused
the complexity of the interfaces.
So using simple interfaces was one major practice
that we followed.
And secondly, because they were collecting
this height and weight values
of the children with malnutrition, what we did first,
we provided them a visual verification of the data
as they enter it.
So if you can focus in on this height and weight values
that are entered here,
you can see that color of this one is greenish, so that,
and this one is kind of like a yellowish amber color.
So what happens is now when someone starts typing height,
what will happen is like,
there will be some age verification based on the,
so we have the date of birth of the child
and the today date, and with this,
we&#39;ll be able to know which is the age.
And there&#39;ll be a kind of a verification
with the comparison of this WHO, there are standard ranges,
the reference ranges for different standard deviation values
for height and weight for that particular age.
So if the height or weight value is okay
it will be kind of a greenish color,
if it is a slightly bad it be amber,
and if it is really bad, it will be red color.
So that way, there&#39;ll be a visual verification that happens
at the point of data entry.
So that it will be about idea about,
if there is a major mistake done by the end-user
at that point itself.
And then of course, to further assist with data quality
as well as to support the interventions,
what we did was we provided some longitudinal charting.
So these are kind of like analytic outputs
that we integrated into system,
which contributes to enhancing data quality.
So here what happened is like, in the mobile app itself,
the end-user after entering the height and weight values
and verify by observing this height and weight charts
and see whether there is a, I mean,
kind of a significant abnormality in any of these values
that have been entered, right?
So there&#39;ll be a kind of a,
this kind of a like a dual verification of the data
that was entered by the end-user.
And in addition, there were simple reports
and simple analytics which are available to the end-user
in the mobile application itself.
So it kind of provided them a very brief overview
about say like here, what you can see is like,
how many children have each of these nutrition problem
when they are under her care.
So that kind of analytical outputs are available
for the end-user.
Right, so once this data was captured that the field level,
the next, there was some validations that happened
at a facility level.
So for this one also,
there was a (indistinct) which was designed
mainly to cater the requirement of data approval
of tracker data, because this is tracker data, right?
So this is even though it&#39;s collected
by a custom Android application,
the data is sent to the DHIS2 system.
So that means, all this has to be in compliance
with the DHIS2 data model.
So this tracker data that is entered here will be verified
by their supervising officers.
So the supervising public health nursing sister
has to go through this data,
and they will be the ones who will be marking them
as completed after ensuring that they are adhering the,
I mean, at least these days are possible values
that&#39;s what they can, I mean, at maximum level they can do.
So once this is done, there will be a data approval
which happens at the medical officer of health,
the MOH level.
And once the data approved only,
the data will be visualized
and shared with other stakeholders at provincial
and national level.
And in addition, there were several data quality measures
that happened at various other levels,
which kind of assisted in this entire process,
because like the data had to be shared
with the multi-sector stakeholders.
This was a crucial step for validation of data
that is captured at the field level.
Right, so I think I have consumed almost 25 minutes,
so slightly over, so I will stop it at there.
And if there are any questions, I&#39;m willing to take it.
Thank you so much.
- [Instructor] Great, now thank you so much Pamod.
That was an outstanding presentation.
I really appreciate how you touched
on so many various elements of data quality
that people don&#39;t always think about.
We&#39;re always, you&#39;re exactly right,
we&#39;re always so concerned about checking the data
once it gets into the system and the different tools
that we have in DHIS2.
But you hit the nail on the head, so to speak,
when you talked about like form design,
standard operating procedures, training processes,
all of these things are absolutely critical to data quality.
And I&#39;m really, we tried to make that point yesterday,
and I&#39;m really glad you were able to drive it home today.
We did have one question from the community,
and again everyone, we are taking your questions
on the Slack channel just like we did yesterday.
So please if you have a question,
post that to the Slack channel.
There was one question,
they are asking if you faced any challenges
or you had to change anything during the implementation
of these various reporting forms and data quality checks.
So once you started actually implementing,
how did you, were there any changes that you had to make
in the process?
- [Pamod] Well, okay.
So as I mentioned one crucial fact was that,
we had to minimally disrupt the existing workflow.
So one major,
like this was not a very kind of a abrupt implementation.
So there was a, I mean, especially my other colleague
from Sri Lanka, was the one who was greatly involved
with this MCH system.
So there was like at least more than one year of planning
in assessing all the workflows and paper forms
to ensure that was, and there was a, I mean,
the other thing that I did not mention here
is the testing and piloting
that goes into the entire process
before you actually implement the system.
Because like, most of these data quality measures
should be captured at that point
if the system is not capturing data for, I mean,
like there are errors in data quality that you observed
during this piloting process.
Those have, I mean, you have to come back and reverse
whatever the workflow so the datasets,
the signs that you&#39;re following.
So there was a lot of planning and that&#39;s how, I mean,
after doing that only,
we went for the first round of implementation.
So there were a lot of issues that we&#39;ve found
at that fields that were corrected.
And then what happened was,
during the initial round of change training
that we did all around the country,
there were some feedback that were coming
related to different issues with the datasets
and accessing the system workflows, things like that.
So during that time, we accommodated a lot of changes
that came from the end-users.
But after the first round of implementations,
we kind of like what we did was we received feedback
from the end-users,
but we did not go on changing the formats,
the day-to-day formats from time to time.
But (indistinct) was that,
if you need us to accommodate something
in the designs of the forms, so this will only be done
maybe at the start of next year.
So we kind of like, if they&#39;re not really critical,
we kind of collected all these things
and we discuss internally within our team.
And maybe at the start of next year,
only we will accommodate them into the DHIS2-based forms.
But if they have a major changes that required
maybe collect, I mean,
like to decide whether this data item
had to be collected or not,
that of course had to go to the complicated specialist
and there has to be a decision that is required
which is of course totally out of the scope
of the DHIS2 implementation, so yes.
The other challenges but we were careful
not to entertain and include all the changes made
by the end-users, but we reviewed and incorporated them
on time to time basis, thank you.
- [Instructor] I think that&#39;s quite clear.
Thank you for that answer.
A couple of more questions, I know you&#39;re a busy man,
but if we can just keep you around for a few more minutes.
Question from Lisa Grout, in the application
that where you&#39;re tracking individual children,
do you do the validation child by child?
- [Pamod] Yeah, good question.
Yes, the thing is, it&#39;s a very difficult,
I mean like, this is one reason
like why we tried to incorporate
all these the color verification and things like that
at the point of data capture,
because otherwise it&#39;s going to be a very hectic task
for the supervising officer to go through all the reports.
So what we have, I mean like, we have made promises
in the system to verify child by child,
but when we are implementing what we have asked them
it&#39;s like, because these are kind of like
when you try to have these systems implemented
in a couple of districts or provinces,
the infrastructure could be even technology, a mobile,
I mean, like the network, as well as human resources,
they did greatly vary from district to district
or even from health facility to health facility.
So what we have instructed them with,
like, you always need to like,
the system has the potential,
but like it really depends on the capacity
that you have in your health facility.
Like ensuring data quality.
So there is always a kind of a fine balance
between data quality and actually capturing data.
Because they, if you have minimal capacity
and you priority number one is ensuring data quality,
then unknown data will come out from the facility.
So it&#39;s kind of like we have given them the choice.
So this is what the system has, this is the best practice,
but it&#39;s totally up to you to decide on what you should do,
but we have given them some incest
really how to capture
if there are any major data quality issues.
Like we have asked them to observe
the data entry practices of end-users.
And if they identify from the preliminary study
that there are a couple of end-users
who really do these mistakes over and over again,
then you can either focus on them
when you are validating the data or is to provide them
kind of refresher training and guidance
to ensure that they are not doing those mistakes.
So there are the simple answers,
like we have not kind of strictly enforce these rules,
and we have make it so taxable
so that the end-users, the health facilities can decide
which is the best option for them.
- [Instructor] Right, okay, thank you very much for that.
The questions are coming in quite quickly now.
It seems like people are really intrigued
by your presentation.
Just two more questions for you
before we need to take a break and move on.
We have one question.
I&#39;ll just go ahead and ask both of them now.
We have one question is, how long did it take
to implement these various data quality checks?
And then the other question is,
what happens if suspicious data is found
in the review process, how do you go back
and make the change and how to keep track of the changes
that you&#39;ve made?
- [Pamod] Yeah, so I will take the MCH instance
for this example (indistinct).
So like, the MCH instance was initially set up in year 2017
and now we have asked three years of implementations.
So data quality, ensuring data quality
was not the number one priority during 2017.
So in 2017, it was mainly about addressing user use
in accessing the system, entering data,
and to ensure the completeness
like even those are data quality measures,
but like, we didn&#39;t go into this final data related issues
in the first year.
But then from your 2018, 2019,
the easiest we focused mostly on the data,
I mean, like things specifically,
we put a lot of emphasis on during the reviews,
because these reviews used to be happening
based on the paper data that was previously before 2017.
So then there was some transformation required
from 2018 onwards to use the system
for these review meetings, so it took some time into that.
So it was like, so what I would like to say is like,
if you see how it&#39;s our plan for future,
so we have more plans
like compared to what we have done so far.
So, it&#39;s a work in progress.
So we have achieved some level as of now,
but we have lot to do.
So we can say like we have ensured data quality
this last three years, we have done,
we have taken some major steps,
but there&#39;s lot more to do.
So it&#39;s really about like what you&#39;re trying to achieve.
And sorry, what was the second question?
- [Instructor] What happens if you do find suspicious data
in the review, how is it changed
and how do you keep track of the changes?
- [Pamod] Yeah, the thing is like, now that of course,
like what happens is like,
they try to understand what is the issue with data
during this review.
So for example, now I mentioned about this distributes
that our staff is conducting at national level.
So during the distributes,
if they identify some data quality issues
before the reviews, they will contact the health facility
and advise them.
And if for some reason, if the same mistake is happening
over and over again,
they really try to talk to the health manager
or the public health doctor
and identify why it is happening and try to like,
if they identify the issue
that this may be happening recurrently,
so then there may be some training gaps,
which if we identify the, even like, what we try to do
is if we feel that in a particular district,
that there is the same mistake that is happening
over and over again,
we try to organize the refresher data analysis training,
there we also talk about data quality during that process.
And then the other thing is sometimes like, I mean,
to ensure the timeliness,
we locked the data after a particular given period of time.
So then we have to put what we do
is we will put lock exceptions and after accepting that
it&#39;s a mistake and when they have like the end-user
at the facility developed,
they accept that it&#39;s a mistake
which has been communicated to national level.
Then normally we will put a doc exceptions
and unlock the data for it to be corrected.
So those kinds of measures are what we do
when I know there are some data quality issues.
- [Instructor] Okay, that&#39;s very clear.
And again, thank you so much Pamod
for the wonderful presentation.
There were many quite a few questions
that I don&#39;t think we have time to get to, we.