(light music)
- [Bob] On the login page, there&#39;s the username.
And we&#39;re in, before we proceed
to discussing the WHO Data Quality Tool,
I want to pause for a couple of minutes
to draw your attention to a special dashboard
that has been designed on this instance of DHIS 2.
This is the data quality dashboard
and we encourage you to also configure on your own DHIS 2
something that looks at data quality in the same way.
In fact, the standard applications of DHIS 2
are well-designed to look at
such aspects of data quality as the completeness.
Here you see for multiple datasets,
the trend over the last 12 months
and the reporting rates.
Or a table that disaggregates
the reporting rates by district.
This is a chart that is looking at
that second dimension of data quality
which is internal consistency in time.
Is the value of in this case ANC first visits,
is it consistent in time?
And we see at national level a couple of examples
where the monthly value was not consistent in time.
So a chart like this showing the month-to-month trend
can allow you to identify the very largest outliers,
suspicious values, values that are very different
from what was reported in other months.
We will see how the WHO Data Quality Tool
is even more sensitive at picking up these outlier values.
Also on the dashboard,
there&#39;s a table that presents for you
the very largest extreme outlier values
reported for various data elements.
And there&#39;s a chart that is looking
at the consistency between related elements.
Remember this was one of the metrics,
one of the things to assess with the Data Quality Review.
In this case, comparing the first doses of Penta
reported by a district to the third doses of Penta.
And these two districts have a negative dropout rate,
So that is suspicious
because they have reported higher numbers
of third doses of Penta than first doses.
And just wrapping up our quick view
of this standard data quality dashboard,
here&#39;s a chart which is comparing
estimates of coverage from two different sources.
The blue bars show you
the routine estimate of coverage
based upon the data
reported monthly by each health facility,
and that routine estimate of coverage
is compared to the estimate
from a recent demographic health survey.
So this is the assessment
of that third dimension of data quality that we mentioned.
This is external consistency of the data.
And we see that for one region,
there is not very good external consistency
between the survey and the routine estimate.
And finally, the fourth dimension
of the Data Quality Review framework
looks at the consistency of the denominator values.
And in this case,
we see that there is not consistent growth from year to year
in the estimated S value of the population
under one year of age,
that denominator used to calculate
coverage with most immunization data.
We see that there was a drop between 2015 and 2016,
whereas with other years there was what we would like to see
which is a steady annual change,
a steady annual growth in this denominator.
So we encourage you to use
the standard applications of DHIS 2 to look at data quality.
What we&#39;re going to do now is switch over
to using the WHO Data Quality Tool application.
If you&#39;ve got a lot of applications to choose from,
one way to rapidly find the WHO Data Quality Tool
is to in the search apps line type in WHO
and then you&#39;ll find the only application
that has WHO in its name.
We&#39;d launch that application.
And right away, we&#39;re taken to this page
which as you see from the highlighting up at the top,
this is the dashboard of the data quality.
The WHO Data Quality Tool.
Later, we will learn about some of the other functions
of the WHO Data Quality Tool
and specifically the analysis function.
But for now, we&#39;re going to focus on the dashboard
and specifically on this first page.
You see that the dashboard
or the WHO Data Quality Tool has four pages.
We will present on each of these four pages.
For now, we&#39;re going to focus on the completeness page,
the dashboard of the WHO Data Quality tool.
The completeness dashboard shows results
for the completeness of several different datasets.
If we scroll down here,
we see ANC dataset completeness,
HMIS dataset, immunization, malaria, maternity.
And for each of these datasets,
there are two charts.
The charts on the left is showing you
the trend in the reporting rate
and the completeness over a 12-month period.
You see here on the axis which 12 months,
from September 2019 to August of 2020.
Why is it going up to August of 2020?
Well, over here is something called the settings icon.
And if we click on that,
a special window opens that allows us
to set how this dashboard is configured.
We&#39;ll say something later about setting data,
but let&#39;s change how the period is set.
Now it is set to August 2020
and notice the chart on the left
is showing completeness over 12 months up to August 2020.
The chart on the right is showing
the completeness for a single month.
Which month? August of 2020.
Notice what happens if we change the period.
We&#39;ve selected July as the period
and now the chart on the left
is showing also a trend over 12 months,
but it is the 12 months which end in July of 2020.
And the chart on the right
shows us the completeness for a single month,
the month of July 2020.
The histograms, the bars in the chart on the right
are disaggregated by region.
It shows completeness for each of the four regions.
If we look at the settings for organization unit,
notice it is set here to desegregate by region.
Let&#39;s see if we can change that.
Let&#39;s change it to desegregation by district.
Aha, now we see that the charts on the right
are showing completeness for the ANC dataset,
disaggregated to show completeness
for each of the districts in the country.
So we see how we can configure the dashboard.
We can change the configuration by changing the period.
We can change disaggregation.
We could also instead of looking
at all of the data nationwide,
we could decide to look at only the data
for one specific region.
Here we have completeness
only for the districts within region A.
Or even if we click on the plus sign,
then we see a dropdown menu
showing all of the districts in region A
and we could select one,
and automatically desegregation is set
to one level below the district
so it&#39;s set to facility.
Okay, we will go back.
Leave this on the month of July.
Set the national as the boundary.
District as the disaggregation.
And let&#39;s see what happens when we change data from Core
and Core, notice Core shows you results
for multiple different programs.
Let&#39;s change Data to one specific program, Immunization.
Now we are looking at completeness
only for the Immunization dataset.
So we see how by changing the settings,
we can use the dashboard
to look at a different set of programs.
In this case, Core means multiple programs.
We can look at the completeness for a different period.
Even we can change the year
and look at the completeness for December of 2019.
And we can change
organization unit to disaggregate differently
or look at a different boundary of data.
We will continue in the next presentation
to review consistency time
and that&#39;s when we will see
how useful it is to change the data
to a specific program like immunization.
(light music)
Thank you.