- [Instructor] So, another area where we can have a bit of
a positive impact on,
is dealing with historical data.
And this can be quite challenging, in reality, to implement.
Whether it&#39;s tracker data,
or whether it&#39;s some kind of aggregate data,
but we just have some different approaches
that we can potentially implement to, hopefully,
reduce the impact this has on our data quality.
So, what we want to do is, kind of,
make data usable over time,
when reporting tools change.
This always happens, right?
Forms are revised, new standards are released.
You know, even with the digital data packages,
these are often new standards
that many countries have to adopt,
and, kind of, you know, figure out how it will fit
into their overall health system,
if they want to report on those values.
So, there are a couple approaches,
and actually we&#39;re gonna talk about historical data,
hopefully in a little bit of detail,
to give you some information
that you might be able to utilize
to deal with different scenarios, essentially,
where we have historical data present in our system.
So, first things first.
I recommend reusing anything that remains the same.
So, if I have a new reporting tool,
and a number of the data elements are the same,
just keep them the same.
There&#39;s no need to create new data elements for a new form.
Another way you can also do this,
let&#39;s say there are, kind of,
old and new data elements, right?
The new data elements,
maybe their definition is now up slightly different,
or they are collecting something similar,
but not exactly the same,
or maybe there are already sets of old and new data elements
and you&#39;re coming in after the fact,
and you&#39;re unable to rectify this proactively,
but you have to come up with some fix now, right?
So, what you can do is actually use indicators,
just numerator only indicators,
to add up the old and new data elements, essentially.
And by doing this, I would also recommend
hiding the individual data element groups
that contain these data elements
so you&#39;re only pointing them to do analysis
on the indicators
so they can access data as far back
as they have information for.
If you&#39;re having two separate sets of data elements,
and you&#39;re not linking them in any meaningful way,
you know, you&#39;re going to have to do separate analyses
on different data elements for different periods.
This is going to be difficult over time.
And it also might be very difficult to review data over time
and find out any quality issues,
on top of making your information outputs
difficult to produce.
So, another problem we will have,
when dealing with historical data,
is what we do with our categories or dissaggregations.
When dissaggregations change,
this can cause a bit of a headache,
in all honesty, right?
And some of you might have dealt with this problem already,
many times, but for those of you who kind of haven&#39;t,
you know, here are some things you can do
to kind of assist you in working with this.
The first thing is using the category combination override
to apply a new disaggregation.
So, I just want to show you what that actually looks like.
So, we can apply new disaggregations to data elements
within a dataset, within dataset maintenance.
This feature has been around for some time,
but I find that it&#39;s not used necessarily everywhere.
And when I show this to people,
it&#39;s sometimes a bit new to them as well.
So, if I scroll down within the dataset maintenance
to all the data elements that are associated
with my dataset,
and I&#39;m going to click on this little wrench icon here,
and you can just see before I go over,
it says &quot;Override the data element category combination&quot;.
So, I&#39;m going to click on this here.
Now, it brings up a list of all the data elements
within my particular dataset.
And you can see underneath the data element name,
it has the disaggregation that&#39;s been applied
to my data element.
And you can see here, a number of them are just default.
A number of them have age and sex.
A number of them have age only.
So, what I can do, I&#39;ll just scroll up to the top.
Right now, let&#39;s say for example, &quot;All cause death&quot;.
This is disaggregated by age alone.
Now, two things can happen when I modify the form.
Age categories could collapse.
Well, actually three things I should say.
Age categories could collapse,
they could remain the same,
which means we don&#39;t have to touch this at all,
and also, you could have
additional disaggregations occurring.
So, let&#39;s say in this scenario,
it said that the numerical ages are staying the same,
but I&#39;m adding sex to this.
So, I want this data element now disaggregated
by age and sex.
I&#39;ll just go here to where it says
&quot;Override data element category combo&quot;,
and I can apply the age and sex disaggregation
to this data element.
All the data stored in the previous disaggregation
will remain the same.
When I go to make my totals across time,
let&#39;s say this was the case up until 2020,
and then, in 2020 I modified it
to add sex to this disaggregation,
all the data before 2020 will still be stored
in this data element, within that category combo.
Now, all the new data going forward from 2020
will be stored in this category combo, essentially, right?
So moving forward, all that data will be there,
but because I&#39;m storing it within the same data element,
my historical total, over time, will always be intact.
And I will just be able to look at the single data element
in order to, kind of, review all the information
associated with that data element.
So, another thing we can do
when working with categories and disaggregations,
is we can just, basically, add everything as totals.
This means we&#39;re going to lose some granularity.
We&#39;re going to lose our disaggregations for historical data.
This is not a recommended approach often,
and it&#39;s just a potential way to do things.
But I wouldn&#39;t recommend doing this, if you can, right?
You want to maintain the integrity of this information.
You don&#39;t want to lose information
as you move from previous forms to new versions of forms.
The only issue is you might have to do this
because of a way they&#39;ve done something within their system.
And then, okay, if this is the only approach you can use
to make things work, that&#39;s fine, I suppose, right?
Because there&#39;s not a whole lot you can do
if you&#39;re coming in at the end
and you&#39;re kind of having to rectify this after the fact,
and this approach is, kind of, the most reasonable one.
But where we can avoid this, obviously, we try to.
Okay, another thing we can do is
use category combination groups,
and group sets to make comparable disaggregations.
So, I&#39;m going to talk a bit more about
category combo groups and group sets
in the next couple of sets of slides,
just so you can, kind of, get a better feel
for what this does.
But for example, if you have a more granular disaggregation,
so, previously, it was zero to one and one to four,
and this is collapsed and it just becomes less than five.
We can use the category combination groups and group sets
to collapse this disaggregation, essentially,
and, kind of, make it comparable over time.
Now, I&#39;m going to walk through an example in more detail,
so you can see this, so you can see how this works.
Another challenge that you will have
with dealing with historical data relates to completeness.
And there are a lot of potential challenges here.
If you have facilities opening and closing all the time,
then this is going to adversely affect your completeness.
There&#39;s no way, inherently, in DHIS2 to close a facility
for one period, for example,
and then, say it&#39;s open again the next proceeding period.
So, there are some ways you can do this manually.
And maybe, even, you&#39;ve thought of some ways
you can do this successfully in your own implementations.
So for example, you could have them mark the facility
as open every month.
So, when they go in to fill in their core datasets,
they could also mark them as open,
and then, you can use this in calculating
your completeness rate,
rather than the in-built tools in DHIS2.
You could also run a script that, basically,
says all facilities are open and they, basically,
have to, kind of, do the opposite
and only input facilities that are closed each month.
That&#39;s obviously a custom solution,
rather than something that can be inherently done
within the platform itself.
So, this is a bit of a limitation here with DHIS2
because there&#39;s not a good way around this,
at the moment, currently.
You will also have to deal with imported data.
So, when you&#39;re bringing in imported data,
there&#39;s no completeness that&#39;s brought in with it.
Unless, of course, you have completeness tables
from somewhere else.
But if you&#39;re bringing in imported data
from an Excel sheet or some other kind of,
maybe an access database, whatever it might be,
if it&#39;s not another DHIS2 system,
the likelihood of it having this completeness data
in the exact format that you require is pretty low.
So, what you can do is create completeness estimates
based on what you identify as mandatory data elements.
So, if you say, you know, data element A, B and C
should be filled in every month,
so you can go through all the data that you&#39;re importing
and check.
For that particular facility,
if the data is filled in for that month
and generate completeness tables based on that,
and then, kind of, bring this into the system
through the API or through SQL,
however you want to push it.
But, of course, once again,
this is not something that there&#39;s a very good solution for.
Another issue you might have is when datasets are modified
or added or split up.
So, let&#39;s say I have version one of a HIV data set,
and now I&#39;m bringing in the digital data packages,
and I now have version two of my HIV data set.
What happens is,
because there&#39;s completely separate datasets,
that completeness does not carry over
from one dataset to the other,
even though we might be able to reuse
some of the data elements from that previous dataset
in the new dataset,
as we had recommended earlier,
we&#39;re not able to actually do anything
about the completeness.
So, this becomes a potential problem
when we&#39;re dealing with,
actually, you splitting up this information.
So, the only solution that I have to offer
is moving this historical dataset completeness via the API.
So, at least it&#39;s in a format that&#39;s, you know,
already kind of useful for DHIS2,
and you can just move this from the old previous dataset
into the new dataset, via the API or through SQL as well,
I suppose.
But there&#39;s not really a good way to do this
through the interface.
So there are some challenges here that extend beyond,
you know, what we, we can have an impact on this
but this is very difficult, I think then,
to show people in countries how to manage this.
It&#39;s still a big challenge actually,
but, obviously, completeness, it has such a big effect
on how we analyze our data.
And we talked about this earlier in previous sessions,
when there is issues with completeness,
big variations in completeness over time,
it affects how you actually make decisions based on the data
that you&#39;re seeing.
So if the completeness is not set up correctly,
then you could make a,
you could be making incorrect interpretations of your data,
which will lead to lots of other problems down the line
when you&#39;re actually reviewing both your data quality,
as well as a lot of your data outputs.