- [Yuri] Good morning or good afternoon.
Hello everyone.
My name is Yuri,
and I&#39;m working here in Norway with tracker implementation.
I hope you can hear me well.
And Scott, do you see my screen?
Can you?
- [Scott] Yeah, looks great and hear you fine.
- [Yuri] Okay.
So I will show you how to move the tracker data
to aggregate data sets today.
And as Scott mentioned, you know,
capturing this individual level data in DHIS2
does improve the quality of data
that we report to the aggregate HMIS,
and it also helps us, you know,
to get to the analysis of data as regular,
as often as required.
So I first
got familiar with this question of how we transfer the data
when I was working on the TB case surveillance
on the tracker module that has been published
now in August.
And so my examples that I will share with you
will be based on the TB case surveillance.
So as you know, for countries that implement tracker,
it is recommended that they use two instances for one,
for aggregate modules and one for tracker apps.
And so by maintaining these separate track
and aggregate instances,
the performance can be best managed by admins and the tools
so that the data can be protected and used as required.
So basically what we do is that when we collect
the individual data in tracker,
it is being aggregated via program indicators.
So when we produce the analytics in tracker,
sometimes we&#39;re liking those dimensions
that the aggregate world allows us to use.
And therefore, we need that step of transferring the data
from tracker to the aggregate modules.
And I&#39;m going to talk about two ways of doing that.
One is more user-friendly,
and this is a solution
that has been developed by HISP Uganda,
and I just would like to say thank you
to my colleagues in Uganda who shared that information
with me and helped me at the beginning.
And the other way, the other solution I will talk about
is a script approach
that requires more tech knowledge.
So first,
the app that you can all use in DHIS2
is called the Data Import Wizard developed by HISP Uganda.
So it has a user-friendly interface,
it supports various import types,
and you can save your mappings and edit them
and have a good way of controlling them.
But the consideration that you need,
well, things that you need to think about as you use the app
is that the mapping process is manual
and it&#39;s best suited for small scale data sets.
So basically if you have to transfer a lot of data
from your tracker to the aggregate modules
and you have a lot of indicators or data elements to feed,
you&#39;ll be better off using the other solutions.
So how does it work?
I&#39;ll just say a few words,
and then I will show it to you on the example
on the instance.
So once you install the app from the app store in DHIS2,
you have to do it in your aggregate instance
and then you can start with a new mapping.
So as you configure it,
I will walk you through the steps now.
You will see that it&#39;s quite simple.
So let me see if you can.
I&#39;m trying to make sure that,
Scott, did you see that I switched the screen now?
- [Scott] Yes, we can see that you&#39;re looking at DHIS2,
the who-dev.
- [Yuri] Yeah, okay, so as you see here
is my tracker instance with a whole list
of program indicators that I&#39;ve created for my data.
And as I said, you know,
for each of the data element in the aggregate set,
I have to create a program indicator.
So I need to create one for the age,
the segregation for sex, and so on and so forth.
Here is my aggregate instance
with the report forms on the TB.
And as you see, this form is empty now.
So we&#39;ll try to fill it in with some data.
So here is the app that I was talking about,
the Data Import Wizard.
So once I start it up, it actually serves many purposes.
It can help you import dummy data into your instance
or data from Excel or whatever,
but we are talking about the aggregate import.
So once I start a new mapping,
so basically I will have an overview of the data sets
that are present in my instance.
And here I will go and take the TB case notification.
So I have to create a mapping name,
and choose the import type.
So in this case,
I&#39;m going to import DHIS2 indicators
into a DHIS2 aggregate data set.
So I go for program indicators,
I have to specify the address of my tracker instance,
which will be this.
So I put it in here,
and then I have to log in with the system admin password
that has access to the instance.
Let&#39;s see if I get it right this time.
Because in the app
you can see the actual password,
you don&#39;t see the stars.
Let&#39;s see.
So that was right.
So now, here I have to specify what period of time
I want my mapping to work for.
So I will take a 2020,
and I will take the first quarter.
Indicate aggregation level.
Okay, so we can do a facility.
And then we need to map the facilities
on the tracker instance with the facilities
or with org units on the aggregate instance.
But as you see, if the names are matching,
then the mapping happens automatically.
I don&#39;t need to do much here.
Then I can filter my indicators.
And these are the indicators that I want to send data
to my aggregate modules.
And I&#39;ve been using the prefixing in the indicators
that I&#39;ve created, so I can assign all of that.
And then I can move to the next step.
Here, I have the data sets
that you see that I need to manually map.
And this is what I mentioned earlier
that for data sets that include just a few indicators,
this is the way to go with this app.
If you have several hundreds or thousands of elements,
you need to map, this will be a cumbersome process.
So let&#39;s say here is my agent sets TB form.
And here I can select the indicators that I,
that can feed into it.
So I can also look for the indicators.
Okay, so if it&#39;s this one, and here is,
oh no, that it was a female, sorry.
Female and I need a male.
Here, and then I will find one for female here and so on.
So I proceed like that till I reached the end,
and when I click next.
So right now, I didn&#39;t do all of this,
but if I did, I would be shown the,
I will see the status that all of my indicators
in that form were mapped.
I guess it takes so long because of the fact
that I have not selected everything here yet.
So I will just interrupt this process,
and I will show you a mapping that I&#39;ve created earlier.
And you will see what it does.
So let&#39;s see, move on to the next step.
So here are my mappings.
And here, you can see that
the import summary of my job
that I have updated eight values from my mapping,
and I can save it as adjacent file,
or I can also see, sorry.
I could also see the report on what has been done.
And if I go to my aggregate module now,
I will be able to see the data that has been filled in.
Okay, so this is how this app works.
Basically what&#39;s in the background,
there&#39;s a JSON file that is generated with a payload
and then it&#39;s uploaded to the aggregate module.
So,
the next way of moving the data to the aggregate modules
is the script.
And here, I&#39;m referring to the script
that has been developed by (indistinct).
A lot of you might know him.
And we are now working on upgrading this script
so that it will be more universal in what it&#39;s doing,
and also provide more feedback to the user once it&#39;s run.
So it&#39;s a shell executable script
that requires some initial setup,
and I will walk you through that.
And you can also set up automated periodic explorer of data
with that script to aggregate with a,
well, by using, let&#39;s say a task scheduler.
So there&#39;s some work that needs to be done for that.
And this is what I started
when I worked on the TB case surveillance.
So basically, on the aggregate side,
you have the data elements
and the category option combinations
that need to be coded.
So here is an example,
as you can see, of a data element and the code
that it receives.
And here is an example of a category option combination
with a code.
So I will need these codes to map my program indicators
in the tracker instance in order to,
for this transfer to be successful.
So on the tracker, we will need,
as you see here, I will move to my indicators.
As you see here, there is an element or an attribute here
called category option combination
for aggregate data export.
So here, I map my category option combinations
from the aggregate modules,
and I will also need to create a custom attribute,
which we call data element for aggregate data export.
So we can then map it to the data element
in the aggregate package.
At this stage, I would just like to point out
that there is a bug in the DHIS2 now
that prevents the user from creating the custom attribute
for program indicators in the maintenance app.
We are working on that bug,
but when we deliver our generic packages,
let&#39;s say TB case surveillance,
these come with these custom attributes
because these custom attributes can still be
injected into the properties of an indicator via API.
So if you have any questions on that
or how this can be done,
you can get in touch with us and we will help you
in this process.
But once this bug has been resolved,
it will be easier for users to actually
just enter those mappings here,
because this is where it will appear
when you create the attribute.
So, what is done afterwards?
So you have a,
this is what the script looks like now.
So basically, we need to edit the list of program indicators
that we are going to use to push the data.
We have to specify the org unit levels
at which we do this transfer,
as well as the periods.
And then we need to specify the data attribute, your ID.
And this is the attribute that I was talking about
for the data elements.
And then we need to specify the servers that we&#39;re using.
So here is our source URL.
This is the tracker and our target URL,
which is the aggregate package.
We make sure that the date format is correct in this field.
And then, we specify the file name that will be created
for transferring the data and the comments
that will be added to the database.
And basically then we need to update the user
and the password for the servers.
And basically this is it.
So we need to, because it&#39;s a shell script,
we need to make it executable with a CHMOD command.
And then we can run it in the shell
or in the terminal on the Mac.
And then if you need automated data transfer,
you can use the scheduler
in order to make these transfers periodic.
And I think I&#39;ve forgotten to save it
in the HISP Uganda app.
The Data Import Wizard also offers you scheduling
for the jobs that you create there.
So this is basically what I wanted to show you today.
And as I said, if you have any questions,
please use the channel and the community of practice to,
we&#39;ll be happy to answer these questions.
And if you need support with the script
or with the transfer from aggregate,
please do get in touch with us,
and we&#39;ll guide you further in that process.
So, thanks.
- [Scott] Great, thanks so much, Yuri.
There are a few questions that maybe you can answer
right away for us here.
There&#39;s quite a, actually, there&#39;s quite a lot
of conversation here.
So the,
sorry, the one question that&#39;s,
one question that&#39;s been asked a couple of times,
and I think you just answered it is
using that application, the HISP Uganda application,
you can schedule jobs.
So once you set up the mapping,
you can schedule it to run periodically, correct?
- [Yuri] Yes, yes.
- [Scott] Okay.
And then what if you have aggregate and tracker data
in the same instance,
does that app also work in that situation?
- [Yuri] Yes.
I don&#39;t think there&#39;s any restriction in regard to that.
So you will just have to specify the same instance twice,
and then you will be able, the transfer will happen.
- [Scott] Great.
Then is there, are you able to provide contact details
for folks who may need assistance using the app
or using the script?
- [Yuri] Yes, with pleasure.
So how do I, do I just paste a paste it in the chat here?
- [Scott] Well, if you&#39;re fine with me
just giving out your email,
I can paste it here in the chat.
Or in our Slack.
- [Yuri] Yeah.
- [Scott] Okay.
Is there a step-by-step guide that you have
for using the application?
- [Yuri] We are, I don&#39;t have a step-by-step guide
right now, so I can copy from the notes
that I&#39;m made for the presentation,
and I can upload it to or I can either post it on Slack
or on the community of practice.
And I will also do the same for the script.
The script will be the way it looks now.
So basically what we&#39;re trying to do
is that we&#39;re trying to make it more user-friendly
so it will give you feedback and it will,
you know, on what it&#39;s doing basically.
So there&#39;ll be more kind of a validation of the process.
But again, you know, the interface requires more time
than the actual, you know, script that does the job.
- [Yuri] Right, right.
Yeah, those would be two very useful resources.
Another question is are we using that same app?
Are you able to
move data, have interoperability between two DHIS2 instances
that are just having aggregate data?
For example, you have aggregate data in one,
and you wanna move that aggregated data to another.
Are you also able to use that app for that?
- [Yuri] I have not tested it for this,
but from what I see when I create a new app,
so let me just create a new mapping.
- [Scott] Feel free to, you can share
your screen again as well. - [Yuri] Okay.
Let me see.
We are here now.
Okay.
So if I create a new mapping,
so these are the options that I have.
I have DHIS2 to DHIS2 data set,
which I think is answer to the question.
So I can move that from one data set to the other,
or from indicators.
Let&#39;s say I could even
move the data from the aggregate indicators here
to the DHIS2 data set.
- [Yuri] Right, okay.
- [Yuri] So both ways are possible.
- [Scott] Cool, that&#39;s great to see.
I think we actually have some HISP Uganda folks
that are participants.
And so, they&#39;re actually answering
some of the questions themselves, which is really cool.
And in general, I think it&#39;s important to point out
that this is a great example of how the DHIS2 community
is able to help each other, right?
So what Yuri is presenting is not an app
made by the University of Oslo.
It is a fantastic app made by HISP Uganda,
and it&#39;s just made in a generic way
so that everyone in the world can use it.
But that being said,
if you are using this app and you are dependent on this app,
I would strongly encourage you
to consider supporting HISP Uganda.
You know, everything in DHIS2 is open and free to use,
but that doesn&#39;t mean that things
are sustainable indefinitely.
And I just wanna strongly say
and encourage you that if you start to use this app,
appreciate that this app is not developed
by the University of Oslo,
and that there&#39;s a development team in Uganda
that is working to keep this app alive.
And if you are dependent on this app,
I would strongly encourage you
to get in contact with HISP Uganda.
We can provide those contact information,
and talk to them about how you can support their effort
to continue to develop and keep this app alive.
There are many apps in DHIS2 that,
you know, the University of Oslo,
we only develop about 30 apps,
but there are over a hundred apps out there.
And so if there&#39;s a good chance
that you&#39;re actually using an app that we didn&#39;t develop,
and if you wanna continue using these apps,
I strongly encourage you to figure out who developed them,
and then to figure out if you can support them.
In this case, HISP Uganda, fantastic app.
So good that we&#39;re supporting it,
or that we&#39;re presenting it here in the academy
as kind of one of our default solutions.
There is one more question for you, Yuri.
Are you aware of the metadata sync app at all?
- [Yuri] No.
Well, is that what&#39;s called, a metadata sync?
- [Scott] I think the question is coming from Lisa from WHO.
She&#39;s asking if we&#39;re aware of the metadata sync app,
and it would be nice if we joined the efforts.
I&#39;m not fully aware.
Again, there&#39;s many apps being developed all the time.
I&#39;m finding out about new apps, you know,
almost on a weekly basis myself.
I&#39;m not aware of that app,
and maybe that app may do something similar I&#39;m assuming.
- [Yuri] I have seen this app.
To be honest, I have not tried it out,
but it&#39;s the metadata sync app, right?
So, and I looked at it briefly
when I was preparing for this,
because I wanted to make sure that, you know,
I see if there are other apps that serve the same purpose,
because I&#39;m sure, you know,
that even with this script that I presented
that we might have some community members
that have developed their own ways,
and maybe they are more advanced than what I shared.
And this is just to emphasize what you said
about the power of community.
So it is great that we can reach out to each other
and get each other&#39;s support in this.
But I will definitely look into the metadata sync app
and see what it--
- [Scott] Yeah, it&#39;s coming from Lisa Grout
and Tina (indistinct).
I think that they would,
maybe we can connect the dots
and they can reach out as well.
They just posted a link to it.
- [Yuri] Scott, by the way,
can you add me to the Slack channel?
- [Scott] Yeah.
We&#39;ll have Martin do that as well.
- [Woman] Scott?
- [Scott] Yes?
- [Woman] They&#39;re two questions about using this app
to input data from Excel into tracker
on the announcements I think.
- [Scott] Have you experienced that, Yuri?
Or I believe Sam from HISP Uganda is also in the call.
Have either of you imported data
from Excel into tracker using this app?
- [Yuri] I haven&#39;t been using this app for that purpose,
but maybe Sam can answer the question.
- [Sam] Hello?
- [Scott] Hi there, Sam.
- [Scott] Hey, how are you?
So, I was working with (indistinct)
and specifically this year, we used the app
to input tracker data,
which was coming through Excel from the (indistinct).
So it is possible for import it using the tracker.
The data import reason.
- [Scott] Great, I think that&#39;s a very clear answer.
Thank you so much.
And again, example of the power of the community
that Sam just happened to be here
and be the right person to answer the question
at the right time.
So that&#39;s fantastic.