(gentle music)
- [Norah] The Data Quality App, a hidden gem.
Part of the sessions on the Data Quality Online Academy.
So, some questions about this app.
Have you seen it?
Have you used it?
Do all the analytic users
have access to this app in your country?
Are you sure?
Go and check.
So, some of the learning objectives,
we will look at what is the most common use
of the Data Quality App,
the value of validation rules,
how to translate validation rules into actual use
and some issues associated with the Data Quality App.
They will be no DHIS online training
of how to move your cursor here and what to select there,
you can use the manual.
So, the DQ App contains the following.
It allows you to do a validation rule analysis,
a standard deviation analysis,
a min-max outlier analysis, and a follow-up analysis.
So, let&#39;s talk about validation rules to start.
Who&#39;s responsible?
If I talk about validation rules,
I sort of get everybody looking away from me.
And the feeling is, &quot;Well, you know, they&#39;re not important,
&quot;so it doesn&#39;t matter.
&quot;Nobody runs them anyway.
&quot;And if they do, when you find something,
&quot;nobody does anything.
&quot;You can&#39;t change anything.
&quot;So, why bother to do this?&quot;
If we start with validations,
is we start asking the questions about who&#39;s responsible
for thinking about them and then defining them?
Is the person or the people or the group?
Is it the HMIS DHIS2 configuration expert?
Is it a program manager?
Is it a district information officer?
Who has to do the thinking
and the defining and the configuration?
Was it done by one person who takes the responsibility?
Then we ask for who&#39;s responsible for running these rules.
The data entry clerk, the program manager,
facility or district information officer or higher level?
Who&#39;s responsible for running them?
If we want to understand the logic of validation rules,
it is a method to assess the quality
of data entered in DHIS2.
And these rules are based on a set of predefined rules
set for the data.
Unfortunately, the validation rules do not allow you
to fully figure out whether or not the values reported
are completely accurate.
It is only based on what is in DHIS2.
And if a value is 25,
you don&#39;t know was it 25 clients they saw
and they transferred from the client record
onto the tele sheet onto the input form
and they captured 25?
You&#39;re just given the 25.
So, how do we define a validation rule?
We use the term an expression.
An expression is a relationship
between a number of data elements that talk to each other.
This validation rule expression
has a left side, a right side,
and in the middle we have an operator.
And so, some of the common operator used
is less than or equal to,
equal to or greater than and equal to.
So, some of the operators that we see most commonly.
Validation rules are created and based
what you know is true.
Malaria RDT tested cannot be more than malaria RDT positive
&#39;cause in order to be RDT positive, you have to be tested.
Another example is live birth
weighing less than 2.5 kilogram
cannot be more than live births.
Validation rules are created based on what you know is true.
For instructions on how to set up a validation rule,
read the manual.
They&#39;re actually very good
and we don&#39;t read them often enough.
Some simple guides to validation rules.
Validation rules are assigned into groups.
This is for analysis.
Validation rules need to be easy to use
and easy to understand.
We use these common operators,
less than, equal to or greater than.
Are we sure that everybody understands
what these signs mean and which way the arrow points?
There&#39;s also the importance field of low, medium and high.
Have we decided how to assign our validation rules
into the importance field or do we just select the default?
Validation rules also need to be consistent.
In other words, the way that they set up and written,
always have the smaller number first.
It is easier to understand, it&#39;s intuitively easier
and it makes it easier to grasp the concept.
Validation rules should be run after data entry
before the complete button is ticked.
Validation rules should also be run after most
or all of the monthly data has been captured.
So, then there are some questions
about who&#39;s responsible for this.
The facility information officer,
the district information officer,
the program officer, the program manager?
Do you have a standard operating procedure
to guide the process of running these rules
and taking action?
Validation rules, how to define them.
Validation rules is an expression
that defines a relationship
between a number of data elements.
An expression has a left side, a right side,
and then in the middle, an operator.
So, some of the common operators used
are less than or equal to, equal to
or greater than and equal to.
Validation rules are created
based on what you know to be true.
Malaria RDT positive cannot be more than malaria RDT tested.
For instructions on how to set up a validation rule,
look in the DHIS2 manual, it&#39;s actually very good.
So, how to run a validation rules.
You select an OrgUnit, you select the time period,
you select your group and you click Validate.
Depending on the size of your database
and the number of rules to be run,
became careful in what you select.
Try and avoid crashing the system.
Once you have run the validation rules, you get a report
which can be downloaded into different formats,
Excel is the easiest.
So, this is the output once you have run the report.
So, on the left, you start off
with the name of your facility,
the time period, the importance.
Remember, we discussed who decides low, medium, or high.
Then the validation rule, and in this output it&#39;s blank.
Then what is the left value?
What was the operator and the value on the right side?
And then there is a detail icon.
And if you double click on the detail icon,
you will get the rule explained to you.
So, this rule says that children five to nine years old
with acute respiratory illness
should be greater than or equal to child five to nine years
with pneumonia.
So, the left-hand side,
child with symptoms of acute respiratory illness,
five to nine years,
there were no children seen.
And the right-hand side, of the no children seen,
11 were diagnosed with pneumonia.
When you see something like this,
where there is a missing value and then a value,
you need to determine
should the 11 have been the acute respiratory
and the pneumonia?
So you actually need to go and find out
why is there a missing value
and what is the correct response
to how do you fix this validation rule?
And there are many ways of going about sorting this out.
If you get a list which you download into Excel,
this is what the report will look like,
facility, the time period, the rule,
the lift side, the value, the operator,
the value on the right side and the right side description.
And if you&#39;ve downloaded it into Excel,
you can sort it to according to organization units
and you can give to supervisors and program managers
for actions.
So this is how you sort out your validation rules.
Then the other,
so this is available in the Data Quality App.
For standard deviation analysis,
now we mainly use the WHO DQ Tool
for extreme outliers and missing data.
The min-max outlier analysis.
This you can only use if you have set min-max values,
and you need to set them first
and the next presentation will go through that process.
And the last aspect in the Data Quality App
is the follow-up analysis.
It&#39;s used to mark data that is correct,
but does not fit the pattern or triggers a validation rule,
and we will have a slide about that.
This is marked for follow-up.
When you double click a value,
you will get a data information window.
And top-left hand corner, you have a space for a comment,
and if you click on the star, you can save it.
You highlight the star and you save.
And this comment and the star is useful to explain
when the validation rule has been triggered.
It explains why the data doesn&#39;t look
as you want it to look,
and then you can run the report on the followup stars.
So, some discussions.
What are the barriers to running validation rules?
Have you looked at the data
and set the most possible validation rules?
Have you done everything that could be done?
Do validation rules pick up all the data mistakes?
We&#39;ve spoken about that earlier.
When obvious data entry errors identified,
why are they not corrected?
Who&#39;s responsible for chasing up the data entry errors?
What happens when these errors are not corrected?
What is the result?
So, here are some exercises associated.
So, confirm access to the Data Quality App
in the country DHIS2 instances.
Obtain a list of all validation rules
and the groups that they fit into.
You may have to ask the IT people to help you.
Review all your validation rules.
Review them for consistency
in terms of the smaller value first.
We&#39;ve spoken about that.
Then I want you to run at least two validation rule groups
for the last six months.
Write a short report on the rules that are violated.
As part of your short report, consider an action plan.
Do some rules need to be rewritten
to make them easier to understand?
That could be part of your action plan.
Are some rules being triggered consistently?
And is that a problem of data quality
or is that a problem with the rule?
And then I want you to think of one rule
that you can add to the current list.
Thank you.
(gentle music)