- [Scott] All right, so now we are gonna take a quick look
at how we are able to,
within
Tracker programs, perform some data quality checks.
And a quick overview, we&#39;ve just talked about the
Tracker to Aggregate approaches.
Let&#39;s talk about then some common issues with data quality
in patient records.
Then I&#39;m gonna do a really brief overview of how we can
build out some program rules.
These are some logic rules that you can put into
Tracker programs for data quality checks.
This is not a Tracker academy,
we have academies specifically on building out
Tracker programs, and goes into a lot of detail
on how to build out program rules.
I strongly encourage you to go to one of those
to get a very detailed overview or skill set
of actually how to do this.
I&#39;m gonna give you some really basic overview just now.
And then we&#39;re gonna talk a little bit about
how we can monitor completeness through program indicators.
Again, I&#39;m not gonna go into detail
on how to build program indicators,
there&#39;s another academy for that, but I&#39;m just gonna
give you a brief overview on how they can be applied
for data quality.
So let&#39;s talk about
some common issues with data in Tracker programs.
Most of us are building very complex data entry forms
in Tracker.
We&#39;re doing the same thing in Aggregate as well.
And we&#39;re not building in a lot of workflow support
to these forms.
It&#39;s a problem in Aggregate.
It&#39;s even a bigger problem in Tracker.
So if we&#39;re capturing individual patient data,
we have got to put in a lot of workflow support.
I&#39;ll give you an example of that.
Then, there&#39;s often a lot of questions,
can we calculate coverages based upon Tracker data only?
The general rule of thumb is, probably not.
You probably don&#39;t have the entire population coverage
using just your Tracker program.
So how do we then calculate coverage based upon
our Tracker data or in combination of
Tracker and Aggregate data?
And then calculating completeness
from individual patient records.
Another tricky thing is,
when is a patient actually complete?
All right, let&#39;s first go into that workflow question.
How do we address that with program rules?
Well, it&#39;s actually easier for me to show you
than to go through it.
I&#39;m gonna give you a quick example.
You&#39;re looking at a DHIS2 database
for Mass Drug Administration.
And what they are actually doing is they are using
Events to capture Mass Drug Administration,
so Mass Drug Campaigns.
So I&#39;m gonna go into the Capture App,
and this is not a demo database,
this is actually a database from a real project,
so you&#39;re not able to go into this one,
but I&#39;m just gonna show it to you as an example.
And then I&#39;m going to go into an org unit,
and I&#39;m gonna select one of my programs.
This is the Capture App.
Again, this is a different app in data entry.
I&#39;m gonna select one of my programs,
this is an Event program, I&#39;m gonna click New Event.
So now I&#39;m opened a data entry form for an Event Program.
In this case, it&#39;s a Mass Drug Administration for LF.
LF is lymphatic filariasis, which is a parasite drug.
If you&#39;re doing MDA, is Mass Drug Administration
for this particular disease.
And what I&#39;m gonna start doing is putting in
some data here, just to show you some of the warnings
that pop up as I&#39;m putting this data in.
Can just put in a contract ID,
implementation total persons, 10,
Here&#39;s the first example of workflow support.
So in Programs,
I can put in questions that if I answer,
will prompt additional questions.
Again, workflow support.
We want to build in as much workflow support.
As you&#39;re filling out questions,
you want to be able to hide certain answers,
or you want to be able to show other questions,
based upon a certain answer.
So in this box, I have a tick box that says &quot;Yes,&quot;
and if I do that, then it opens another
field that I need to fill in.
Okay.
I&#39;m just gonna start putting in more information here.
And this next question is a good one.
So we say &quot;Year Started,&quot; so here I should
be putting in a year value.
I&#39;m gonna put in
a number that&#39;s not a year, and look what happens.
So I put in what, like 200,000?
We&#39;re not even close to the year 200,000 yet, right?
And so it says,
&quot;Invalid year, this year must be between 1990 and 2020.&quot;
So if I go to 2000, see the warning goes away.
This is a great example of a simple program rule,
where if I put in a number that doesn&#39;t make sense,
it&#39;s checking the value that I&#39;m putting in,
and it&#39;s telling me in real time,
if this is an appropriate number.
I&#39;m gonna put in just a couple of more.
All right.
So I&#39;m just putting in random numbers right now,
and you can see I&#39;ve triggered another data quality check.
So in this case, what is it saying?
Well, I&#39;ve actually got an error box
in the top right corner here.
And it says &quot;Persons targeted cannot be greater than
the population eligible for PC.&quot;
PC is a treatment process.
And here they say, okay, look, I&#39;ve got 10 here.
And it says, &quot;Persons targeted
cannot be greater than pop-&quot;
And then it&#39;s telling me,
okay, check here, check here, check here.
And great, so I have 10 here, but I have 10 there,
but this is saying it&#39;s not right.
So if I just put in zero and zero,
great, now it goes away.
So the sum of these could not be greater than this.
And that&#39;s what it was, so when I put it in the zeros,
it went away.
All right, now I&#39;ve got another data quality check.
I just put in some more random numbers, it&#39;s saying,
&quot;The sum of male plus female treated
can not be greater than the sum of PreSAC, SAC
and adults targeted.&quot;
So these are aged breakdowns,
and it&#39;s saying the sum of male and female treated
can not be greater than these values here.
So what did I do, I put in 10 male plus 10 female,
that&#39;s 20, and then the sum of this is just 10, right?
So let&#39;s try to fix that.
I&#39;ll put in zero here.
Great, now that went away.
I just put in some more random numbers and guess what?
I got two more errors saying, &quot;The sum of male and females
should be equal to sum of treated,&quot; okay?
So they&#39;re saying that this sum, male/female
should also be equal to the sum of these three.
And then it&#39;s saying also, &quot;The sum of Pre-SAC, SAC,
treated cannot be greater than the sum of Pre-SAC targeted.&quot;
So they&#39;re saying this sum cannot be greater than this sum.
So let me go in and fix that.
All right, so now all my data quality checks went away.
So I just wanted to give you a quick demonstration
of program rules in action.
So this is a real project.
They&#39;re entering data across dozens of countries
actually in this particular program,
hundreds of people are entering data using
this particular reporting form.
And you can see all of the various data quality checks
are just an example of some of the data quality checks
that are coming up, as they&#39;re putting the data in.
You can also see some of the workflow support.
So for example, I ask a question, if I say &quot;Yes,&quot;
then it gives me another box to fill out.
These are done via program rules.
So let me get back to my PowerPoint presentation.
All those different data quality checks
that you&#39;ve just seen are done via program rules in DHIS2.
So essentially, what is a program rule?
A program rule allows you to
put in dynamic behaviors in response to user input.
So just as you saw, I was ticking boxes and more things
were coming up, or I was putting in values
and it was causing alerts and error warnings.
You know, that&#39;s the kind of dynamic behaviors
we&#39;re talking about.
It allows you to send a lot of direct user feedback.
So as you&#39;re putting stuff in, you&#39;re telling the user,
&quot;No, that doesn&#39;t make sense&quot; or &quot;You need to check this,&quot;
or &quot;Those numbers can&#39;t add up.&quot;
And you are building these out as expressions.
We&#39;ll talk a little bit about the expression builder
just in a second here,
but essentially these expression builders have
a lot of different options for you.
It&#39;s not just about showing warnings or errors
or tick boxes, what I showed you,
there&#39;s lots of things that this can do.
And again, there&#39;s a whole academy that goes over this,
but just to make the point that
you can really tailor these messages, these warnings,
this user feedback, this workflow support,
to using a lot of different features.
Most actions using program rules will happen immediately
when the data values are entered.
So that&#39;s exactly what you saw me doing.
So as I was putting the values in,
there was something happening immediately.
And that program rule, in terms of how it&#39;s configured,
constitutes three things, variables, expressions,
and actions.
I&#39;m gonna go through these very quickly.
Again, to get more detailed answers and explanations,
we&#39;ll have to point you to another academy,
or certainly you can ask questions and we have
lots of resources for this.
So what are programs variables?
Essentially program variables
represent attributes and data element values,
which can be evaluated as part of an expression.
So essentially these are the data elements and
attributes that you actually define.
Usually they&#39;re data elements, sometimes they&#39;re attributes.
Once you make them
as a variable, you can use them in multiple program rules.
This can include data values and attributes,
and operate these as expressions.
Let me kind of skip through that.
Here&#39;s the screen if you want to make
a program rule variable.
This is really the first step,
you have to define the variables,
then you can put them into your expressions.
And then from your expressions, you define the actions.
So in this case, we&#39;re looking at a program variable
called Sex, and the sex is a tracked entity attribute.
So this is like if you have a patient and the patient
is male or female, then this would be
sex that they&#39;re using here.
The expression is the next star,
so once you&#39;ve defined your program rule variables,
you have to define your expressions,
and your expressions are essentially
the logic that is being applied to,
or it&#39;s defining the kind of interaction that
is happening based upon the value that are being entered.
So I&#39;ll skip through that.
In the expression you have to build out operators,
again, we don&#39;t have time to go over this
in a lot of detail.
There are clear documentations linked here,
in the PowerPoint, providing you what these are.
You have to do a little bit of programming,
and it&#39;s not programming in like you have to know JavaScript
or HTML or something like that,
but there&#39;s just syntax in which you have to build out
these program rule expressions in.
And you can see here, I won&#39;t go over
each one of these examples, but you can see that they
can become actually very complex.
There&#39;s a lot of flexibility here on what you can actually
do with the program rule expressions.
So you can say like,
&quot;If&quot; statements or &quot;Greater than&quot; statements, or
&quot;Or&quot; statements, &quot;And&quot; statements,
you can really, really build some complicated things here.
You know, of course it&#39;s better to keep stuff simple.
But you can, say like,
&quot;If they enter sex as male, if they enter age
as greater than 35, if they enter BMI as this,
then recommend this action.&quot;
You can really base these program rules,
based upon multiple variables
and give specific feedback as the data&#39;s coming in.
Not useful for just data quality,
also useful for just workflow support.
Custom functions,
I&#39;m not gonna go over this, but just suffice to say
that you can build out various custom functions.
So you can count the number of days in a month,
you can count the number of days between events.
You can prompt actions if there&#39;s a specific value,
we call these our d2 Functions, you can see that
on the left side of the column there.
That&#39;s just an example.
All right so, actions.
So we defined our variables, we defined our expression,
and then we can define many different actions
that they have.
In the example that I showed you,
the action that I was triggering was &quot;Show warnings,&quot;
and &quot;Show an error.&quot;
So you saw that as I entered values,
and there was data quality checks happening,
it was popping up different errors saying,
these values don&#39;t sum up together,
you need to double-check this.
There are many different actions that could happen.
So I was just showing you basically one action.
You can check the docs here, if you
click on this actions icon, it&#39;ll take you to the docs
and all the various actions.
There&#39;s really a lot of different choices here.
So this is a brief summary.
So you enter the program rule details,
then you enter your program rule expression,
and then you define your actions.
The other thing that I want to point out is that
many of you are using Android, the mobile app,
to be able to capture Tracker data as well now.
So you&#39;re not just using your PCs,
or you actually have folks in the field,
community health workers, outreach workers,
clinicians, that are using the application.
The point to be made about folks that are using
the application is, as they&#39;re filling out data,
make it as easy as possible.
Put in pictures, make different colors,
make it so that each one of the answers
to each one of the questions is clear and distinct.
So here you see an example of a malaria program
where a community health worker
is filling out malaria cases.
And you can see that for the answers
in the top right corner,
it&#39;s saying &quot;How did you diagnose this malaria test,
did you use microscopy, an RDT,
or there was no test at all?&quot;
And you can see that there&#39;s pictures,
there&#39;s clear colors.
It&#39;s very simple, even for someone who may be illiterate
to answer this question, right?
&quot;Which one did you use?&quot;
And again, this is the best practice,
the best practice is make it as clear and simple as possible
for folks to be able to enter this data.
The next question of course is,
or a later question is, &quot;What are the treatment types?&quot;
And again, very clear, pictures different colors,
and so they would be able to distinguish
which treatment type that they provided.
So program indicators are another way in which we&#39;re able
to calculate values based upon Tracker data.
Many of you may be wondering what&#39;s the difference
between a standard indicator and a program indicator.
The main difference is that a program indicator
can have a little bit more logic put into it,
and it calculates values based within a single program.
Whereas a standard indicator cannot support much logic,
but it can calculate values across multiple programs
or multiple data sets.
Okay?
So a standard indicator,
across multiple programs or data sets,
and a program indicator, you can add more expressions,
more logic to it, but it can only calculate
within a single program.
So here&#39;s an example of program indicators
that look at completeness of data that&#39;s entered
in Tracker programs.
Two examples here, the first one is
&quot;Count of BCG doses given, divided by total number
of tracked children,&quot; right?
So what is that giving us?
That&#39;s giving us basically a coverage of BCG doses
across all of the children
that we have captured data against in our Tracker program.
A very simple program indicator,
may be applicable to like an immunization program.
The second example here is, &quot;Return the percentage
of tracked children who have recoded a BCG dose.&quot;
So tell me the percentage of children that have
received a BCG dose.
So this is very simple examples of how we&#39;re able
to actually look at something like BCG dose
completeness within a Tracker program.
So the question becomes,
a lot of times is,
if we have Tracker data and we have Aggregate data,
how do we combine those into a single coverage indicator?
What we typically recommend is that you do not use
Tracker data as your sole denominator
for coverage indicators.
Why is that?
Because typically most Tracker programs
do not have national coverage.
Meaning that most of them are still in some stage
of scaling or pilot.
So maybe you have a couple of districts using Tracker
and they are
capturing individual
service data through Tracker,
but then you have other districts
that are maybe not using Tracker,
or they&#39;re not using it as well.
And they&#39;re still capturing that Aggregated data
on a monthly basis or something.
So how do you actually then
make, say like a national coverage indicator?
Well, you need to potentially combine
the two sources of data together into a standard indicator,
but we don&#39;t recommend that you necessarily
solely use Tracker data, unless you know that you have
a hundred percent coverage of your Tracker program
across the entire country.
Let me just kind of skip to the point here.
So here we have kind of,
what&#39;s the good practice,
the best practice is to have
two different indicators, potentially.
So you have your national coverage,
that&#39;s using your Aggregate denominator,
and then you have another coverage that&#39;s using
Tracker data.
And you&#39;re able to see those side by side.
And so that&#39;s what we&#39;re actually able to look at here.
We have the coverage indicators on the left
that are coming from the Tracker program,
and then we have the individual data that&#39;s coming from
the Aggregate side.
You can see in the green is the Tracker coverage.
The blue is the national coverage coming from the Aggregate.
So you&#39;re able to see those side-by-side.
And then the same thing on the right side,
the green is the total number of immunized children,
and the blue is coming from your Aggregate data
and the blue is the total number of children
registered in the immunization program.
So you&#39;re able to see these side by side.
Again, the point being that, you know,
as it stands right now, the general recommendation
is you put your Tracker data alongside
your Aggregate data.
And view these as somewhat distinct,
unless you know that you have a hundred percent coverage
of your Tracker program, which is quite rare.
All right, just one other slide here.
Sorry.
Here we want to talk about how you monitor Aggregate data
compiled from a Tracker program to ensure that errors
have not occurred in the data transfer.
Essentially what we&#39;re looking for
is a one-to-one relationship.
So what we are saying is that, Yuri just talked through
some of the tools that can be used for this,
but you also want to put in
some program indicators to make sure
that the values are being transferred.
So for example, if I am transferring this month&#39;s
Tracker data into Aggregate,
let&#39;s make a program indicator that sums up
all of the Tracker data for that data element
for that month, right?
And then let&#39;s see that program indicator,
and then when we push the data from Tracker to Aggregate,
let&#39;s make sure that that data element that we see
in our Aggregate is the same as that program indicator.
Right?
So we can double check this.
So we make sure that we kind of have
a one-to-one relationship.
Sometimes it can become quite problematic
with the transfer process,
if you don&#39;t have these data quality checks
in place to monitor just the transfer,
did everything actually go through correctly.
Okay.
I think I&#39;m gonna skip the last slide.
Actually, Yuri covered it quite thoroughly, I think.
And so that brings us, time now is 12:06 Oslo time.
So we are gonna go ahead and take our break.
Well, let&#39;s see if there&#39;s any questions, Nora,
any questions from the community, Martin?
- [Nora] Scott, you answered the questions about Excel
into Tracker, and then there is a question from Dhruvee,
again, if we calculate coverage, if we use Event Program
to do surveys of representative samples,
using it for a annual household survey
to calculate coverage.
I&#39;m not sure.
And there&#39;s also another question from Rose.
- [Scott] So can we calculate coverage if we&#39;re using data
to do surveys of representative samples?
Yeah, of course you can,
what we were talking about, and I think that seems like
maybe a lower level, like a DHS,
like a Demographic Household Survey or something like that.
You certainly can do that,
and that&#39;s the methodology that DHS also employs.
What we were saying is that maybe for like
coverage indicators that are like total immunized
or percentage of immunized children,
or something like that, fully immunized children.
Typically we don&#39;t have Tracker programs yet
that are at national scale to be able to calculate
that one with a hundred percent certainty
from just Tracker data.
But I think that if you&#39;re looking at coverage calculations
that are just from like maybe survey data
and you&#39;re using Event Capture to get that survey data,
then I think that&#39;s probably fine.
It&#39;s not so much associated with like
clinical service delivery.
And then Rose has a question here.
&quot;Would it be possible to send program notifications and
Tracker Events as a full collective summary,
not as single notification?&quot;
Yes, I think so.
Oh, you want to schedule notifications from Tracker?
I believe so.
So you also have something called program notifications,
that when you&#39;re actually building the program,
that you can apply.
And I think maybe not using a program rule,
but a program notification might be the answer to that.
But to be honest with you, Rose,
I am not the world&#39;s expert on Tracker.
And so what we need to do is I need to pass
your question along to Yuri, who would have
a better answer than me, I hope.
All right, so now we&#39;re at 12:08.
If you were wondering if I could share with you
access to the database that I just did a quick demo,
I cannot.
That is a production instance developed by
DHIS2 Implementer, that I asked if I could just do
a quick demo of their data capture forms,
and they said that was fine.
But it&#39;s not publicly available instance.
Okay, so let us take our 15 minute break
and we will be then coming back now at, I guess it would be
12:25.
Nora, would that give us sufficient time to go through
your session after the break?
- [Nora] Yes, Scott that&#39;s fine.
We&#39;ve just had a request for the uploading of the
PowerPoint presentations piece.
- [Scott] Right, I believe mine is already uploaded,
but we need to grab Yuri&#39;s as well.
- [Nora] Yes, then 12:25, we will meet again.
- [Scott] Okay, great.
We&#39;ll see you back here in 15 minutes at 12:25 Oslo time.