- [Instructor] So another item that I wanted to discuss,
and we went over this
in our kind of overview of the session,
is about naming conventions.
So we&#39;ll share the document
that we have on naming conventions,
but there&#39;s just a couple of key principles
that we can always keep in mind when we&#39;re naming things.
And the reason that this has an effect on system design
is our ability to find items
within our system accurately
and with minimal kind of effort.
So good naming practices that they help with identifying
these different data elements and indicators.
And there&#39;s some basic principles we can follow
for basically any data element or indicator that we create.
So as a general rule, data elements do not need
the term number of in the name itself.
Now, maybe this is on the form.
Maybe this is somewhere else
when they&#39;re actually being displayed for entry purposes.
But when we&#39;re actually performing analysis,
this can make things a bit confusing.
As data elements will no longer be grouped in order,
there&#39;ll be grouped by number of,
and when you&#39;re looking for things in a list,
an order ordered list of some kind,
it makes it very difficult to find them.
We can talk about something similar for indicators.
So indicators should not be percentage of,
in the name itself.
Now maybe you can put a percentage symbol in brackets
at the end of the indicator name for example,
to clearly identify that you are having an indicator
that&#39;s the proportion of some kind,
and maybe just use the pound sign,
the number sign in brackets at the end of the name,
for example, for a numerator only indicator.
But you don&#39;t actually have to put the full
kind of text here because once again,
it makes sorting difficult.
So these are some general principles for both data elements
and indicators that we can follow
when we&#39;re naming items in the system,
or even when maybe we have to go through
and rename numbers of items,
because how they&#39;ve been named previously is quite poor.
So here are a couple examples, a couple of concrete examples
of bad practices and kind of where we can get to
in terms of better practices or good practices.
So we can see in the bad practice item,
some names of the data elements and they&#39;re quite long.
And you know, this makes it difficult to read,
to sort, to really find what we need,
but we can take this and pair this down,
slowly but surely going through this process
of kind of getting to our good example
on the right side here,
where we&#39;re just having minimal texts
that accurately conveys
what that data element is representing.
You can also see that because of the way it is worded,
that things are kind of grouped together
just by their nature,
due to the alphabetical order of that list.
And that it makes it easier to find in a sense.
So this is something to consider, this is a manual process.
Again, we&#39;ve been talking about manual processes
a little bit, you know, this is not something
that can be automated necessarily.
You&#39;re going to have to go through the data elements
and identify which ones are kind of not working,
in terms of their naming convention.
And if you&#39;re adding new data elements,
that is something that you can take
a more proactive role in perhaps,
by having some kind of guidelines
on general naming standards for items in your system.
Here&#39;s a couple of examples for indicators as well.
And this is where we see the same kind of problems
that I mentioned earlier, right?
We have this percentage of, at the beginning
of the indicator name in a lot of cases,
and we see this in live systems all the time,
but this makes the listing of the indicators
in an ordered list quite difficult
because they&#39;re not grouped by anything significant.
The names are much longer than they should be.
So if you&#39;re creating a chart, for example,
with many data items on it, it&#39;s going to be, you know,
the names will be collapsed naturally
because it just won&#39;t fit on the chart itself.
So there&#39;s a lot of implications here
in terms of analyzing our data
and outputting that data and just finding what we need.
So if we follow a couple of these very simple principles,
we can really make things easier to find in our system.
And this is once again, largely a manual process
and not something that can be easily automated.