(upbeat music)
- [Instructor] With this video, I&#39;m going to present
to you how to use
the Consistency-time page
of the dashboard of the WHO Data Quality Tool.
Let&#39;s click on the tab for Consistency-time.
And then, so that our screen will match up
with the screenshots in the guide,
we&#39;ll set Data to Core,
Period to April,
and Disaggregation to District.
Now, if we want to free up some space on our screen,
we can make the settings window disappear
by clicking on the settings icon.
Let&#39;s look at the charts on this page.
We see that there are charts for several indicators,
ANC 1st visits,
if we scroll down, ANC 4th visits,
HIV tests done,
Institutional deliveries,
Penta 3 given before the age of 12 months,
and Under 5 OPD malaria as a percentage
of total outpatient malaria.
For each of these indicators,
the page has two charts.
The chart on the left has three different lines
in different colors.
Let&#39;s explore these lines.
The dark blue line is showing the trend
in the number of ANC 1st visits
from May of 2019
through April of 2020,
which is the period that we selected.
And then, what is this light blue line?
Well, the light blue line is also showing the trend
over a 12 month period.
But in this case, it is the months
from May of 2018,
to April of 2019.
And then, the orange line shows the trend
over another 12 month period, which is May of 2017
to April of 2018.
So, each of the lines is showing the trend
over a 12 month period,
whether it&#39;s between 1 and 11 months previously,
or 12 and 23 months previously,
or 24 and 35 months previously.
This is an example of what is called
a year on year chart,
because we have placed the findings for one year
on top of the findings for other years.
And we noticed from these charts,
that the values of ANC 1st visits go up and down a bit,
but most months they don&#39;t jump up or down a great deal.
But we see two exceptions.
There&#39;s this outlier, this value that&#39;s very different
from other months, in January of 2020.
Back here, in May of 2019, we also see a jump up.
So, the year on year chart is good to show
how the value for a single month can be quite different,
not only different from the months in that year,
but different from the value for months in other years.
Let&#39;s look now, at the chart on the right side of the page.
This is a special kind of chart, also.
It&#39;s called a scatter plot.
This is because the values are scattered.
Each of these dots represents the values
for a single district.
If we place the cursor on the dot, then a window appears
showing that this is for District C-5.
And what does the value along the vertical axis represent?
Well, as we see, the value on the vertical axis
is the number of first ANC visits in April of 2020,
which was 3,917.
What does the value on the horizontal axis represent?
Horizontal axis is the average value of ANC visits
for that district during the 11 months prior to April 2020.
So, this would be from May of 2019 until March of 2020.
And the two values, they aren&#39;t the same,
but they are close to each other,
and that&#39;s why this dot is close to the line.
This line represents districts,
which have exactly, or almost exactly,
the same value in April 2020 as they had
during the average of the previous 11 months.
And all of the dots, where the two values,
the value for April 20,
and the value for the previous 11 months,
where those two values are almost the same,
they&#39;re close to this black line,
and they fall between the two gray lines.
Now there&#39;s one dot where there&#39;s an exception.
It was this dot down here.
And notice that the dot has a diamond shape,
rather than a circular shape of the dots that appear
between the two gray lines.
So, dots which are suspicious have a different shape.
This is for District B-2, which in April of 2020
reported a total of 1,425 first ANC visits.
Whereas, the average reported by this district
during the previous 11 months was 4,595.
So these are quite different.
The value on the vertical axis is quite different
from the value on the horizontal axis.
So this dot is placed outside
and identified as an outlier.
Let me show you how we might investigate
this outlier by changing the period.
The outlier appears in January of 2020.
So what if we change the period of these charts
to January of 2020?
Again, let&#39;s free up space by making the settings window
disappear.
And notice how the charts have changed.
Now, we still see trend lines in the chart on the left,
but in this case, the trend for the blue line is from
February of 2019 to January of 2020,
the period that we select.
And we see our outlier here.
Look at the chart on the right now.
Well, apart from these districts,
which had values in January of 2020,
which were reasonably close to the average
for the previous 11 months, there&#39;s a single dot up here.
And it is for District B-2.
So, in January of 2020, District B-2
reported a very large, and probably incorrect,
value of 36,835 first ANC visits.
When you compare this to the average
of the previous 11 months,
it reported only 1,363 first ANC visits
during those previous 11 months.
So this dot is showing far from the reference line,
far from the line showing equal values.
And can you explain now why it is that we saw-
let&#39;s go back to April, keep in mind the value
reported for District B-2 in January of 2020, almost 37,000-
if we change the period back to April,
can you explain why the dot was below the line in April?
Well, in fact, this dot is below the line in April
because the average of the previous 11 months,
when we are looking at the chart, based on April,
the average includes this very high and incorrect value
that was reported in January.
And so, that increases so much the average
over the previous 11 months that it pulls this dot away
from the reference line.
So that&#39;s an example of how you can do some investigation
by changing the period.
And you could also do some investigation
by changing the organization unit and drill down.
However, we will see how it is much easier
to drill down and do investigations when we talk about
the outlier page.
Before we leave the Consistency-time page,
I want to show you how we can change data,
and what happens to the Consistency-time page
when we change data.
At present, data includes, as you see,
one or two indicators from multiple programs,
antenatal care program,
HIV program,
this is labor and delivery program,
immunization, and a malaria indicator.
Notice that there&#39;s only a single immunization indicator
now included when we have data set to core.
But what happens if we change core to immunization?
Wait a while for the data to be processed.
And now, let&#39;s scroll down the page
and see which indicators are included
on the Consistency-time page.
Well, we see a new indicator, a new immunization indicator,
BCG, Measles,
OPV 1,
OPV 2, 3,
Penta 1, 2, 3,
Rotavirus 1 and 2.
So, by changing to a different group,
changing data to one of these other groups,
we can look at a larger group of programs,
specific indicators,
and we can do a data quality review
that is specific to that program.
Here, if we change to the HIV program,
we see a larger number of HIV indicators on the dashboard.
So, that&#39;s an example of how changing data
allows us to provide a more detailed look
at a more extensive set of indicators.
And later, we will practice changing this
to the district group, which has been especially designed
for data quality review of indicators
of greatest relevance at the district level.
Thank you.
(upbeat music)