(upbeat music)
- [Bob] WHO defines four dimensions
or domains of data quality
which you see presented here,
completeness, internal consistency,
which means do even the data agree with each other?
External consistency,
does the data reported by health facilities
agree with data from other sources,
such as a health facility survey,
and finally a review of the consistency of the denominators
of the population estimates
that are used to calculate coverage.
So I&#39;m going to review each of these four domains in turn.
You see here a chart that is showing the trend
over the last 12 months
in the reporting completeness for two different datasets.
It&#39;s possible with a single chart like this,
to show the trend for multiple datasets,
completeness, reporting rates,
this is the most fundamental aspect of data quality.
And before you attempt to interpret any trend
in the data themselves,
you have to look at what is the trend
and the percentage of completeness of the data.
Internal consistency, what do we mean by that?
Well, you could think of this internal consistency
as the apparent accuracy of the data
comparing one aspect of the data
with another aspect of the same dataset.
And there are several different ways
of measuring this internal consistency
at a way of measuring is here referred to as a metric.
If there&#39;s one metric which is the consistency over time
that is our data that consistent from month to month.
B, the second metric is consistency between indicators
that are related and the commonest example of this
is to assess what we refer to as the DPT dropout rates
are the reported numbers of first doses of Penta vaccine,
consistent with the numbers of third doses of Penta vaccine.
And we&#39;ll provide some other examples of related indicators.
And finally, there&#39;s a form of internal consistency,
which can only be measured by visiting the health facility
as I&#39;ve referred to.
And that is the consistency between clinic registers
and reported data and in that way,
we can measure something called the verification factor.
This is an example of the type of chart
which we can use to look at to month consistency of data.
In this case,
the number of reported third doses of Penta vaccine,
and each of these lines represents
the trend over the 12 month period.
And the Penta 3 doses for one region.
The blue line is region one.
And the blue line in particular has this hump here,
which unlike the data front of the other regions
suggests there&#39;s a certain inconsistency
from month to month
that this has jumped up in a way that we don&#39;t quite see
with the data from the other regions.
However, when we&#39;re looking at data
at the level of a region, we can&#39;t be sure,
is this due to a data quality issue
or does it represent an actual increase in services?
But look what happens
when we actually look at these trend lines
for individual districts?
So here we see the data from the same country
and from region one, but in this case,
there&#39;s one line for each of the districts of region one.
And there&#39;s a certain amount of instability
from month to month in the indicators.
But look at this line for district number 12,
where in the month of June
the reported third doses of Penta has more than doubled
and then it drops back down again.
This is highly suspicious.
And the lesson here is that
when you&#39;re looking for month to month inconsistency,
it&#39;s best to look at the data that are desegregated
to the level of the district.
And then you&#39;re more likely to pick up
these quite suspicious numbers
and have confidence that it is a data quality issue.
In fact, with DHIS 2, it&#39;s possible to drill down,
to go down to an even lower level
and identify the specific health facility,
which has reported this suspicious number.
And I think you would agree with me
that when we look at these lines for each of the doses
of a vaccine for this health center number two
of the same district of the same region,
we see that this jump in the value for the region
is actually due to a single number
reported by this health center in June.
And we can also see that this is almost certainly an error.
This is due to a data quality issue.
Not only has the typical value of less than a hundred
of the typical value of Penta 3 jumped to 3,749,
but we see that this health center in the same month
has reported normal consistent values
for the other data elements.
So here we see an example of an erroneous value
that has been reported for one health facility.
This slide shows you the table that is generated
by the WHO data quality tool
to automatically identify facilities and values like this
that are extremely suspicious,
and which are almost certainly due to errors
that have been entered into the DHIS two.
In this case, it has sorted these values
and put up at the top of our table,
the 12 months of data for Kawe Dispensary
data on Penta vaccine doses given
in females under one dose three.
And it has found that this number is the most extreme
and most suspicious value of all
in all of the immunization datasets,
and we&#39;ll practice with this WHO data quality tool
and see how it can be used to rapidly
and automatically identify such outliers.
The next type of internal consistency
that we will be reviewing is
as I said, consistency of related indicators.
And here&#39;s some other examples of related indicators.
In addition to looking at the dropout rate
between Penta 1 and Penta 3.
We could also compare the values of the first doses of Penta
to values of the first doses of OPV vaccine.
Both of these are typically administered on the same visit.
So we expect the values of these two indicators
to be roughly the same.
And then a final example.
The data on confirmed cases are frequently reported
both in the monthly outpatient department report
and reported in the malaria lab test report
that is submitted each month.
So we could compare confirmed outpatient cases
to the total number of positive RDT and microscopy tests
that were reported in a given month.
The slide here shows how the WHO data quality tool
analyzes for the dropout rate between DPT 1 and DPT 3
and it generates this type of chart
showing that there&#39;s one particular district,
which had a negative dropout rate,
which if reported for a full year
is usually a sign of a data quality problem.
External consistency,
I&#39;ll just quickly review these last two dimensions,
which aren&#39;t a major focus of this workshop.
Here&#39;s an example of how the WHO data quality tool
has compared the values
reported on a house household survey.
In this case, this was a demographic health survey,
the values for anti-natal care first visit coverage
reported on the survey versus what was estimated
based upon the data reported by health facilities.
And in this case, there&#39;s a striking difference
between what is called the routine estimated coverage
coverage that is calculated with health facility data
and the estimates based on the household survey.
And finally, consistency of population estimates
or denominator estimates.
There&#39;s a couple of things that should be assessed
about the denominators.
One is whether they are consistent from year to year,
and the second is whether related denominators,
such as the number of pregnancies,
the number of live births, the number of infants
are consistent between each other.
So here&#39;s a chart giving an example of a country,
which has not had year to year consistency
and the growth rate of the number of surviving infants
the population under one.
In fact, that estimated number under population under one
is seem to have dropped from 2015 to 2016,
and then it increased dramatically from 2017 to 2018.
So this estimated value
is not showing year to year consistency.
And similarly, if you think about it,
it is a bit unusual that we would find
that the estimated number of surviving infants
in 2018 and 2019, was estimated to be actually greater
than the estimated number of live births
that really should not happen at national level
and suggests that we had some errors in the denominators
used to calculate coverage.
(upbeat music)