- So the last thing that I wanted to talk about
are some supplemental scripts
that have been developed to support
the assessment of DHIS2 system design.
And these dig a little bit deeper
than what the data integrity check provides.
And it also provides you a bit of a summary
that you can present to others
that is more easily digestible I think in a lot of ways,
because you can enumerate the results
that are outputted by these queries.
So I&#39;ve shared the SQL file for you here.
There&#39;re series of SQL queries and one of the challenges is
that you need direct database access to run some of these.
So for example, you can run any query on users
via an SQL view within DHIS2.
So this is not something necessarily
that everyone will be able to do,
but it&#39;s good to be aware that this is a possibility
because you can always enlist a little bit of help
in making sure that you can do this.
So I&#39;m going to transfer over to the interface
where I can run some SQL queries essentially.
So you can see this in operation on a system
and kind of understand some of the outputs.
So it assesses a number of different things.
There&#39;s a data set, state elements, indicators,
users, organization units, dashboards, charts,
pivot tables, and maps.
So we can see there&#39;s a lot of stuff related
to analytical outputs, as well as things like
our data sets and our data elements.
Now you can see once again, in terms of input,
there&#39;s a big focus on aggregate data,
but I think this helps us really
to summarize some key issues that we might see in the system
when we&#39;re actually performing this type of assessment.
Okay, so we&#39;re getting a bit technical now.
This might not be something that everyone&#39;s familiar with
or that they&#39;re available to perform
without a little bit of support, but that&#39;s okay.
What we really want to impart is that
these tools are available
and someone can help you to implement them.
But because the queries are already there
for anyone who&#39;s familiar with doing this,
it&#39;s basically just something you can copy
and paste when you&#39;re running these
so you can get the output.
So the output&#39;s located at the--
so I&#39;ve run one query on datasets
just to show you an example.
I&#39;ll run another one in a moment,
just so you can kinda see how it operates.
So, I&#39;ve just pasted in the query.
And then I have the results at the bottom.
This is a query on datasets
and it gives me a bit of information
that isn&#39;t present in the data integrity checks.
So here I have the number of datasets,
the total number of data sets.
I have something called datasets abandoned
and it gives me a description of what that is.
Data sets that have not been changed in the last 100 days
and they&#39;re assigned to one or less org units.
We then have under this dataset, no updated data.
Datasets with no data values with the last updated date
within the last three periods
based on the data set period type.
And then the final one, dataset with no new data,
datasets with no data values in the last three periods.
So this is helping me to identify basically
items that are not being utilized.
We can think about how this might affect
our completeness for example.
If these datasets are not being utilized
and we check the completeness of this data,
it&#39;s probably going to be pretty low.
So the reasoning behind that,
there could be different reasonings behind
why that&#39;s not being used, but it might not be
that this dataset is even being utilized anymore.
So, if that&#39;s the case then what do we do
with these data sets where there&#39;s no new values
for such a long period of time.
And you can see this as more of a summary,
but this allows you to assess and summarize and share
some of these kind of top level issues with others.
I&#39;m just going to run another query.
So this is the file here,
I&#39;ll run it for data elements, for example.
Just copy the whole thing.
Sorry.
Copy it all.
And I&#39;m gonna run the query again.
I&#39;m just gonna paste it right in there.
It&#39;s gonna give me by output at the bottom,
and this is for data elements.
And you can see the summary of what it&#39;s produced,
total number of data elements,
data elements not in any groups.
And then it has a number of listings
for aggregate to data elements in particular.
Aggregate dated elements that are not assigned
to any organization units,
aggregate data elements with no data values.
Aggregate data elements with no data values
in the last three periods.
And the period type is based upon the data set itself.
So the last three periods could be the last three months,
if the data set is monthly, and it will be quarterly,
of course, the last three quarters perhaps,
if the data set is quarterly.
So you can see what kind of outputs that this produces.
So there&#39;s a number of queries there.
Maybe not everyone&#39;s going to be able to run them,
but if you can, I would suggest maybe on a local instance,
for example, you can run some of these queries
just to see the output and see
if this kind of helps you understand the setup
of the database you&#39;re working with a little bit more.
I think it also presents quite easy to understand
outputs for others to kind of review.
So it&#39;s not just something internally,
even though maybe they might need
a little bit of help producing these outputs.
I think that is something very nice
to present to others at a top level.
Obviously you will have to investigate.
For example, if you say, this last row in this table,
data element, no analysis.
There&#39;s 110 of these data elements that are not used
in any favorites, either directly or through indicators.
So you&#39;re gonna have to investigate
what are those data elements that aren&#39;t being used.
But at a very top level I think it&#39;s it&#39;s quite easy
to present these summaries and say,
this is why we might need to consider making some changes.
We have all this kind of abandoned,
disparate metadata in our system
that&#39;s just causing all kinds of problems,
and what do we do with it?
So, those are some of the tools you can use
in order to assess this a little bit more.
These SQL queries, you can run some as SQL views,
but there are some that you just cannot.
It will not allow you to do to the tables
that you&#39;re accessing.
So, the most foolproof way to make sure
you can run all of them is to have direct database access.
And then of course, you can run them directly
and get the output that you need.
So, the whole point of this was just to make you aware
that these tools are available.
Might not be the case where
you&#39;re actually doing this yourself.
It might be the case of course, where you are.
But now that you know they are available,
it&#39;s just another kind of way to help you assess the system.