- [Instructor] So this is the play instance,
which I think you&#39;re all familiar with.
And if we launch the data quality app,
are you all seeing that on your screen, by the way?
If we launch the data quality app
you immediately get this message that says that it&#39;s not,
hasn&#39;t been configured and this,
you&#39;ll see this as soon as it&#39;s installed,
but I&#39;m skipping ahead here because I wanted
to first comment a bit on the installation of the app.
It&#39;s like any app, if you go to app management,
you can find it in what used to be called the App Store.
Now it&#39;s in the App Hub under standard apps.
You see that the instance already has it installed,
but sometimes you want to re-install the latest version.
I find a number of national instances
where they have an outdated version
of the data quality tool.
The current one in the hub is version 1.2.3.
Let me move this out of the way.
And in some cases, it&#39;s best
to install this over the outdated version
that is on a national instance.
Fortunately, when you do that,
it&#39;s very user-friendly because it will preserve
whatever configuration has been done
with the previous national instance.
You don&#39;t have to worry about starting from scratch
when you re-install the latest version.
I think of it as rebooting the computer.
When the old version, there are issues with it.
Maybe there was some bugs, some incompatibility.
So it&#39;s often worth asking that question,
is the most recent version installed?
We also want to reassure you that installation
of this app on the production instance,
we, so far, have had absolutely no issues
with that disturbing the rest of the configuration.
So we used to tell people in data quality academies
that you should first do this on a training instance,
on a development instance.
And that&#39;s certainly good hygiene
to use a development instance first,
before you install new things.
But in this case, we feel rather confident that
this will not create problems, if it is installed
on the development instance.
Before, so installation, you click on there
and it will install,
then it will appear under the standard apps.
Now, the next thing I wanted to comment on
is access to the data quality tool.
In another number of cases,
even after the data quality academy,
some months after data quality academy,
I&#39;ve gone on to the production instance
and found that the tool is installed,
but it simply hasn&#39;t been shared.
So, I want to remind you that to work
with the national administrator and the authorities,
to come up with a good policy on who has access to the tool,
if the tool is there and it&#39;s hidden from folks,
then it&#39;s really not that useful.
And of course, this is a governance issue,
but I prefer that everybody have access
to the data quality tools.
So in this case,
I&#39;m even going into the user role of guests,
and I&#39;m going to assign this to the guests, even,
so that even they have access and saving it.
This isn&#39;t a necessary step when you use the play instance,
because you are automatically given the super user role
when you log on to the play instance.
But again, this is one bottleneck
that you&#39;ll find on national instances,
and they need to feel comfortable with transparently showing
to people the issues of data quality.
This is obviously a governance issue.
Okay.
And one which
we might discuss further,
the issue of who has access,
but in the interest of time, let&#39;s.