- [Andrew] Thank you for allowing me
to present in this academy.
It&#39;s a unique opportunity
to share our experience on the ground
and my presentation will focus much more
on the approach that Rwanda used to strengthen the HMIS
through DHIS2 and improve the data quality.
So like other countries, many other countries,
we went through the challenge of having the system
that was really responding to the needs
of the Ministry of Health.
And the system by that time in before 2000,
the system was not a web-based system
and I remember by that time their reporting rate was 60%.
So imagine taking a decision on the 60% completeness
so you can obviously see
that the data is not representative.
So that&#39;s when we started looking at a web-based system
that could be able to improve the reporting processes
but also improve the completeness.
So in 2011,
we started the process of reviewing our reporting form
because we could have not managed to move to the web-based
when we still have tools that were not harmonized.
And secondly, we wanted to have
one integrated reporting form
and bringing up also the development of SOP
to standardize the data collection
to ensure that the methods and interpretation of indicators
across the facilities is the same.
And also reducing the workload to the health facilities.
So those were the major criteria
that we used to review the reporting form.
So in 2012, we launched the web-based system,
which was built on top of DHIS2 platform, DHIS2,
and later in 2013, we developed different tools
like Indicator Reference Manual and others.
But as soon as we started in 2011,
we started with the standard operating procedures
for data management and for data quality assurance.
So in 2014, we kept on integrating other system
like a case-based system like e-TB and others
built on top of Tracker.
Then 2018, we kept on strengthening the system
by integrating the WHO data quality apps and other packages.
Then what we did was coming up with these tools
before we even engage
or bring the web-based system in place,
which is the IT solution.
So we developed the standard operating procedures
for districts and health facilities
that governs the data management
and reporting data verification and validations.
And we also reviewed the data collection tools
like patient files, registers and reporting forms.
Then later, as I said,
we also devoted the Indicator Reference Manual
to ensure that everything is harmonized
in terms of indicator definitions and interpretations
and common errors in interpreting some of the indicators.
So that was not only what we did,
it was also to bring in some accountability kind of,
but also sharing
the publication of Annual Statistical Booklet
and also promoting the information use.
So you may ask yourself
why was very important to have these tools standardized
and why SOP, developing these SOP?
One is that we had unclear roles and responsibility
at facility level.
I remember in 2011, we used to blame
some of the facility that they are not reporting.
Then they could ask you, &quot;Who was supposed to do it?&quot;
There was no clear roles and responsibility to know
who is doing what, at which level?
Then another one was we identified
that we have fragmentation of tools,
many tools that some of them were repetitive.
You can imagine that you&#39;re writing Andrew
in like thirty registers and you&#39;re repeating the same name.
So we said, no, it&#39;s better to harmonize the tools
and ensure that someone writes,
if it&#39;s a case, you just write it once or two times
but not many times.
And also systems, we had many systems that were fragmented,
vertical ones.
Then another gap that we had,
it was that there was no standard data collection processes.
So each facility used to just report the way they want
and this one was a gap.
Another one was unclear definitions and many more.
I will share these ones then you can be able to read.
So there was an urgent need to ensure that all of these
are harmonized and standardized,
and we have like a standard operating procedure
to show that everything is done in the same way
and the way we define our indicators
and collecting them is the same way.
So you can believe that when you are improving
or harmonizing your processes in terms of data quality,
this is what you do.
So you are trying to move people from this workload
that you can see that people are dragged into the data
and they spend much time just to collect data
and they spend much time to keep these papers.
So when we share that ensuring data quality,
what do we mean?
Is ensuring that we reduce all these workloads
to the health workers so that data collection is simplified
in a way that it doesn&#39;t take long time
for the health workers.
The SOP, what was the purpose of the SOP?
The purpose of the SOP like data management
is a standard operating procedure.
It was to really clarify or highlight across the facility
the procedure for data collection,
what do you do when you are collecting the data?
And the procedure for data quality assurance,
what do you do to ensure that the data you&#39;re collecting
from the registers is the same as what you are reporting
in the electronic system?
So then it was also to clarify
the health related records, storage.
Most of the time they used to ask us,
&quot;How long are we going to keep these facility registers?
All of these were supposed to be clarified
and also retention.&quot;
Another one was data reporting,
like putting in some timeline,
knowing that if you&#39;re reporting on a monthly basis,
when do we say that data is reported on time basis?
When we say that data is not reported on time basis?
So we had also the chapter on the data sharing and access
and then release,
but also we have the analysis and dissemination.
On analysis and dissemination,
we also added the key indicators that they have to analyze
and measure their performance at facility level.
So all above chapters,
they really highlight the general principles
when it comes to data management.
Then roles and responsibility,
it means that if you have someone
in charge of data management,
what is the role of the data manager?
What is the role of the chief nursing?
What is the role of the clinical director?
Everyone have to have a role.
What is the role of the head of the facility?
So when everything is really well-defined,
so from there you could be able to know
who didn&#39;t do what he was supposed to do
to ensure that data is reported on time.
So we also developed the data quality assessment, SOP,
which is standard operating procedure
that have four chapters
that really highlight the introduction.
why do we have this data quality assessment, SOP?
Then the overview of the data quality assessment process,
then the data quality assessment procedures
and data validation.
Then again, there&#39;s something that we always don&#39;t consider
when it comes to assessment, giving feedback,
which is the important part, and debriefing.
So this SOP really defines well
how you do the overall assessment,
and the way you give the feedback to the facility
to ensure that they also consider the improvement
on what you have identified as gaps.
Then the SOP, again, highlights the appendices
like a final report template.
We don&#39;t want people to invent,
like example of notification letter,
like if you&#39;re going to visit a facility,
you don&#39;t have to write a letter, the letter is there,
you only put the demo facility.
Then the correction form
in case you want to do some correction
to ensure that we track the logs,
we have the correction form.
Then the routine data quality tool assessment, audit tool.
This was there before the WHO data quality app
but now we are shifting towards the WHO data quality app.
Again, the data quality app
also focuses on the general principle, as I said,
and it also defines the roles and responsibility
of each health staff
to ensure that whoever is in the facility knows his role.
Then it details the procedures for each chapter.
Here is an example of what we have on the data quality
standard operating procedure or data management.
First of all, it defines the type of reports that we have
responsible person to ensure that that report is submitted.
Reporting level, is it central level? Is it district?
Then timeframe, is it immediate?
Like disease surveillance, is it monthly?
Is it daily? Is it weekly?
So everything is defined.
Then from there, you can see the table on my right,
that really defines the months
that defines what they have to do.
On 25th up to 30th,
they have to ensure that they gather all registers together
and ensure that no register is missing.
Then first 1st to 5th,
they have to report this into the system
and the system tracks the reported data up to fifth
as that the timely reporting.
Then 5th to 15th,
the system is opened for any data correction.
Then 15th, the system automatically blocks the dataset.
So it means after 15th,
they cannot report anything into the system.
So at least this one gives them the discipline
to ensure that on each provided timeframe,
they are really using it to maximize
the process that is done at that timeframe.
Then when they know that the dataset will not be opened
for data to be entered any time,
they also make this business to be serious.
So in SOPs and Indicator Reference Manual,
we tried to make it flexible
to ensure that it also tracks some common errors
that someone can encounter.
So we highlight them clearly on the reference manual
and SOP also.
As I said, we are also using the packages
to ensure that we simplify the way of data visualization
and the more you want people to use information
and improve the data,
you have to ensure that the tools they&#39;re using,
they are simple to use and they are able to visualize
the information that they want.
So these are different problems that we have modules
that we have in the system.
There is a program related to routine clinical reports,
case based data, which is e-TB, EPI tracker,
medical certification of causes of death.
We have on annual reports.
We have daily flash reports from the hospital
that are used by the Ministry of Health
to track the process,
to track the daily update from the facility.
We have disease surveillance.
We have PBF, performance based financing.
We have a COVID module into the DHIS2.
Then regarding the mechanism.
I think many people they are really interested to see
what are the mechanism that we use
to ensure that the data is of good quality.
We have different mechanism
but I will highlight the major ones.
The normal ones that we&#39;re all familiar with
is the normal data quality checks,
where we have what we call ISS,
integrated supportive supervision,
that we jointly work with the development partners
and we take data from HMIS
and we go down to the facilities
to check if what did they reported into HMIS
is exactly the same as what they have
in the source of data.
So this is a central level data checking, which is ISS,
integrated supportive supervision.
We have also the program specific data checking
where they bring the head of the hospitals together
because each hospital at least has 12 health centers.
So when they come together,
they give them feedback on the data,
then from there they are able to check their data.
So we have also validation rules in the system.
We also promote the information
using the analysis and feedback from the central level
which is the HMIS team.
Then we have this data set locking and approval.
Then we have the performance based financing,
which is also promotes the data quality.
So we also have the accreditations.
It means the performance based is that people,
we have like indicators on completeness and timeliness
and if three indicators when all of them they are 100%,
that&#39;s when they have the scoring of the PBF,
which is performance based financing.
Then accreditation is that most of them
they struggle to ensure that they get on a certain level
when it comes to accreditation.
Then we have decentralized also data review,
which is the monthly data validation done by the facilities.
So that one also is the additional part of that data review
and an improvement of the data quality.
So this is the example
of the monthly data validation meetings from the facilities.
You can see that they come together on a monthly basis
then they review the tools that they have
if whatever tallies they made
is exactly what is in the registers.
You can see that my people here
they&#39;re on the registers checking.
You can see the other ones are just there
they are presenting the data
that have been reported in the system
to ensure that they validate before the dataset is locked.
Then here they&#39;re also checking
if exactly what they reported
is the same as what they have in the source of data.
So on the data use part,
we also have the coordination meetings.
Coordination meetings is the monthly meetings
that the district hospitals,
because at each district hospital,
they have the catchment area.
So that catchment area comes together to review
what are the indicators
to check if they are really on track.
So at least these coordination meetings on monthly basis
also promotes the information use.
We have also the DHMT quarterly meetings that is done
bringing together the overall district
with each catchment area health facilities
and they have selected people to attend.
They also use it to present the health status
on their catchment area.
So all of this is towards to improve the information use
but also it also contributes to the data quality.
So not only that, we also have the central level,
we have senior management meeting that also uses the data.
We also have development partners
that also look at data quality.
All of that also contributes a lot
when it comes to quality data.
So we also use the global tools like many other countries,
because these tools have really brought a huge change
when it comes to data review and checking
like the WHO data quality tool,
is really a nice tool that we have institutionalized
in our standard operating procedures
and also trained our people to use it because it&#39;s a tool
that can be able to show you the outliers
and you can be able to show you the inconsistencies
along your data when you try to analyze it as a trend.
So this is the example of the WHO tool
and some of the charts that we generate.
So what we did is that we, thank you Scott and Bob.
We really worked with Scott and Bob
to ensure that our teams, I mean in Rwanda,
they are trained to know how to use it.
And it was a collaboration between University of Oslo,
WHO, and Ministry of Health.
So the tool for us to maximize its use, we reviewed in 2012,
we reviewed our standard operating procedures
to accommodate some of the features of the tool
and to ensure that it&#39;s also part of our everyday life
in the health facilities.
So not only that, we&#39;ve been working with the team,
I mean, Scott and Bob, and Ministry of Health team
to ensure that we have the dashboards
that are able to allow people to monitor their completeness
at facility level,
to monitor the trend of the data over time,
and also this one is a way of simplifying
the visualization of data on their fingertips.
Not only that, but also whenever I present this,
people always ask me about sustainability
to ensure that whoever we train is in place
and nothing is compromised and we have continuity.
I think as part of that&#39;s why I like these academies,
the academy approach is really a good framework
to ensure that countries have the sustainability
and also have the continuity of these good interventions.
Like in Rwanda we&#39;ve been really hosting different academies
before COVID, even we&#39;ve been attending different academies.
So what we did was like having our people
attending these kind of academies,
like data quality academy,
then we use to maximize it,
like ensuring that at least at each program,
we have a maximum number of people
that are able to customize the DHIS2,
that are able to configure the data quality,
that are able to support their facilities.
This one was also a motivation
because even if one person leaves the ministry
or the facility,
at least we are able to have someone
that can be able to train the rest
or can be able to replace other team.
So I could encourage countries
to attend these kind of academies to gain skills
because the more you attend the academies,
the more you gain skills of new features
and the more you get some insights from the country stories.
Not only that, as we&#39;ve been really implementing
these good initiatives,
but we were also having some constraint
when it comes to trainings.
And the problem was that we used to train
because we have money of training
but we are looking forward to see how could we train
based on the needs from the ground
not based on the funding available.
So we&#39;ve thought about the e-learning
and we said let&#39;s come up with a way,
a remote way to train people
because the more we have new features,
the more we&#39;ll need to train people.
The more we see that you have gaps,
the more we need to train them.
So we came up with e-learning that is now online.
We previously we managed to train all health centers
and district hospitals and district administration staff
on the data quality processes
and it was much more to ensure that the data quality app
is well used.
Then our slogan is that,
&quot;It&#39;s time to move learning to people
instead of moving people to learning.&quot;
So you may ask what is the contribution of the quality data,
or having the web-based system in place,
or not only having the web-based system
but also using the DHIS2
because the more you have it updated,
you gain from many features
that can really improve your data quality
but again also raise the confidence of policy makers
to use your data.
So most of the contribution
is on the policy and strategic decisions
because we are lucky that we have one integrated
case management information system that collects all data.
So it makes it to be used and trustable
and used in planning, program planning and management,
resource management, capacity building,
disease surveillance,
because even disease surveillance we&#39;re using DHIS2,
innovations, and research and M&amp;E.
So even though I presented some interventions
around data quality but we still have a long way to go
because we are not where we want to be.
We are still promoting the information used
because it&#39;s not at that level that we want
and because now we are focusing at facility
because at the central level is good
but it&#39;s much better if we keep pushing people
at facility and district level to use data
instead of us telling them
that maybe malaria have increased,
we are promoting now another approach
of having the information from them, bottom up.
So again, we are really now installing different features,
WHO features to ensure that we really maximize
the use of these packages
because most of them they are developed
based on the standards, on the global standards
and because Rwanda is also part of the global standards,
so we are taking advantage of these global standards
because most of them they have some experts
that have been really concentrating
to ensure that they bring together information
that may really help
and you countries may take advantage of.
What I like is that these packages are free
and that makes us really play with them
and use them to really improve what we are doing
in the countries.
Then definitely having these features in place,
you have to consider building the capacity
and these are the future plans that we have
to ensure that at least we maintain
what we have adapted and implemented across the facilities.
So, as I said, I wanted to show you,
I don&#39;t know other countries,
for Rwanda, this is for Rwanda.
You can see that even though we have
all those good interventions in place
but we still have much more to do
when it comes to analytical features or favorite views.
You can see that most of the users,
they are using pivot tables
and in the system we don&#39;t have only pivot tables,
we have dashboards.
The dashboard is the black one, you can see it&#39;s still down.
So we need to have people really using the dashboards,
visualizer, which is the chart, maps, and others
that really promote the information use.
But we have already started this initiative
with University of Oslo,
finding out why people like to use pivot table
than other features.
That&#39;s why we can see that there are many features
that are being released based on the field feedback.
So without taking long, these are the links.
I can share the link, but on my PowerPoint,
I have the link where you can be able to access
all these tools, the SOP, the reporting form,
the metadata dictionary
which is the indicator reference manual,
the annual statistical booklet
that can be able to show you what we are reporting
and the template.
The list of health facilities
can also be found on the website.
So thank you.
Let&#39;s keep the better information,
better decisions and better health.
This is the end of my presentations.
You&#39;re welcome Scott to take over
and guide us to the next step, thank you.
- [Scott] No, thank you so much, Andrew.
Able to measure the data quality improvement
or the data use improvement over time
or how have you been able to monitor that?
- Okay. Thank you.
We, first of all, we have different articles
that I will share
that manage to measure different indicators,
more specifically,
we&#39;ve been working with partners in health
but also we have that assessment that we do,
which is the ISS.
When you look at the measurements
because we know we have the ranging of the score,
that when it&#39;s 5%, if the error is around zero to 5%,
that one is okay.
But if the error is above 5%,
that one means that we need to put much efforts
to ensure that we reduce the margin of error.
So when you look at the results from the ground
and the study that have been done,
you can see that the data quality is pretty good
when it comes to our data that we collect from Rwanda.
But again, you know, it depends on some indicators.
There are some indicators that when you take them,
those ones that are not much more used,
they may be lagging behind
but the key indicators really have over 95% of quality.
- [Scott] Great, okay. Thank you.
A couple of additional questions.
What was the process that you all went through
to develop these data quality standard operating procedures
and how have you been able to implement them?
You talked a little bit about the remote training
but maybe you just give it a little bit more clarity
on the standard operating procedures,
how they were developed
and how you implement them in practice?
- That is a good question.
First of all, before you develop
even the standard operating procedures
you have to understand your gaps
and you have to understand what should you want to address?
Remember that in 2011,
it was the whole year of preparations
so we&#39;ve been really understanding the gaps that we had
and we already heard that the reporting rate was 60%.
So we wanted to improve the reporting rate
and the completeness.
So from there we identified different gaps.
One was that the reason why people are not reporting
is that they don&#39;t know their role and their responsibility.
So we said we need to come up with something
that really defines, what does Andrew have to do?
What does another person have to do?
What is the synergy between them?
So all of that was also part of what we wanted
to make sure that it&#39;s documented
and the process of reporting.
So again, we were also moving from a locally based system
to a web-based.
A locally based system was a little bit tricky
because by that time in 2011, before 2011,
we were forced to go to each facility
and install on individual computers
but now it was a web-based.
So we were also forced to ensure that
whatever that will be accessible online,
is it used the same way?
Is it standardized?
Reporting is the same,
because we didn&#39;t have time to go and really train them
or mentor them at their facility.
I remember one time before 2011, there is one,
I always give this example,
there is one colleague of mine from one facility
that you take eight hours drive from that facility.
He came with like a flash drive,
with a backup that I have to restore in the server.
So at the time he was in MOH,
I checked in the flash drive there was no backup
so it was like the virus really eaten the backup.
So the guy was forced to move again to the facility
and come back again and go back again.
You can understand the time wasted by that time.
So from there, at least when you have a web-based system,
you are lucky but again you have to ensure
that you have everything centralized.
Regarding training our team,
because it was the first web-based system
that we had in the country
regarding the health management information system,
we were forced to really use the training of trainers,
which is the ToT and again use the training of trainers
to ensure that we reach everyone in the country
and we transmitted the same message, so that is what we did.
But maybe currently we have many ways that it can be done
but that&#39;s what we did.
So the SOP was much more to address the gaps
that we identified,
and to ensure we standardize everything
regarding the data management verification and others.
Because even users used to ask us,
&quot;You are telling us to verify the data, how?&quot;
Then you could try to tell them do ABCD
but your colleague could also say
this different way to do it.
Then when you go down to evaluate, because we have the ISS,
what ISS does, which is integrated supportive supervision,
what did they do, they go down to access
what we documented in our SOP, is it implemented?
So by that time, we used to go down
and you are not able to see what to evaluate.
So we said, &quot;No, let&#39;s have a standard
that we can even go down and evaluate.
If we say that people have to have a meeting once a month,
is it done?
They have to have a report documented, is it documented?&quot;
Those are the kinds of things
that we wanted to have in place,
to have evidence-based, not theory-based
I don&#39;t know if I answered your question.
- [Scott] No, you did and I think that the clarification
on how you actually go down and validate
or verify what is actually the standard operating procedure
is a really good critical step.
I think from all of the case studies
that have been presented,
I think hopefully one of the very clear messages
is that standard operating procedures
are absolutely necessary.
And you&#39;ve even taken it a step further
by having a process to actually verify
if the standard operating procedure is being followed.
So I think that&#39;s really really interesting.
We have time for a couple more questions
and they are coming in actually quite quickly now.
One question is they are curious on how data quality is done
with the facility staff.
Do you call them into one place?
Is there a meeting?
Just what is the standard operating procedure
for the actual facility staff
for them to conduct data quality checks?
- Thank you, Scott.
That is a good question again.
So what we did, we have two ways.
One is that we already have the data checks
that is documented in our SOP
which requires certain group of people
like if it&#39;s a hospital, we require the chief nursing,
the clinical director, the data manager, the M&amp;E,
and some people in the services who records the data
to come together and review the data
before they report them into HMIS.
And this one is done either before fifth,
because fifth is when we say that they have
reported on timely basis but we give them at least 15 days.
It means from 1st to 15th,
they have to undergo that process.
At least within those 15 days, they have to sit down,
those key people I mentioned and I&#39;ve even shown the picture
and they review.
Reviewing means they bring the register
and check if what they really counted
is the same as what they reported.
So, but again, after that meeting,
they have what you call coordination meeting.
The coordination meeting
is the same as the previous meeting,
only that the previous meeting
focuses on the quality of data,
checking if there&#39;s anything that you reported wrongly.
But the coordination meeting is the catchment area meeting
where it brings together with the health center
in that catchment area,
then what they do is that the M&amp;E and the hospital
presents the key indicators
saying that, for example,
we had three maternal deaths, maybe last month
and the first month it was one maternal death.
Then they may ask some people in the maternity
why it happened, then they have to explain.
Then when they&#39;re explaining, they take some actions.
Those actions, at least they may say,
&quot;We have to improve the case management in maternity,
we have to improve the way we treat the mothers.
We have ensure that the ambulance,
when they are going to transfer mother to their facility,
it doesn&#39;t take long.&quot;
Those are the kinds of discussion that they have.
Then at the end of the day, they take also actions.
At least those actions are on top of the real data
that they took from the system.
Again, in case, they reported the wrong number,
you can understand that someone in maternity will say,
&quot;No, we didn&#39;t have four maternal deaths, we only had one.
So I need to understand where three are coming from.&quot;
So those are kinds of discussion they discuss.
But again, it is one, is just improving the quality of data.
The second one is improving both the information use,
which is the actions.
Then again, also checking if what data says
is people think that they have in their services.
So I think that is what I could say that we have,
but again, as you said, Scott,
whatever that is written in SOP
is evaluated after six months.
So each six months we go down,
which is the ISS, integrated supportive supervision,
with development partners,
then we check if they are really implementing
what is written in SOP.
At least that one makes them to really make sure that
whatever we have in the SOP is implemented and is used
and also we ensure that the SOP
also defines well those kinds of meetings of data checks
and what did they have to check and who chairs the meeting.
If the person who chairs the meeting is not around,
who replaced that person.
After the meeting,
you have seen that we have appendixes of the report,
the type of the report that they have to document,
actions that they have to take,
how they have to conduct the next meeting
by reviewing the previous actions.
Those are things that we manage to document well
to ensure that it also guides the facilities.
Thank you.
- [Scott] Great, that&#39;s very, very clear. Thank you, Andrew.
We have time for one more question.
And I think the question is,
what is your experience in sharing data with stakeholders?
Maybe implementing partners, NGOs,
how do you regulate the number of data managers
in the system?
And do you have any challenges with this?
- Yeah, that&#39;s a good question
that is a discussion everywhere that I&#39;ve really visited.
So for the facilities and district it&#39;s by default.
All of them they have to have access
and we give them access, it doesn&#39;t require anything
because the data that they report
is from their institutions.
But when it comes to development partners,
we also have this mandate
of ensuring the development partners
are also part of the process that we undergo.
So what we do is that in HMIS,
we have a focal person
that is assigned to each development partner
that ensures that whatever requests they need
is shared with them.
So if today we have a new NGO
that&#39;s coming through to support the health sector,
what they do, they just do a request.
They just do a request where you say that,
&quot;I&#39;ll be needing this data to monitor our interventions.&quot;
So what we do we also respond back and say,
I mean, the minister of health responsible can say,
&quot;We will be giving you this data.
Please contact this focal person
that will be ensuring that whatever that I need
is on your disposal.
It doesn&#39;t take when you&#39;re going through the processes.&quot;
So that&#39;s how we are doing it
but currently we are not giving access to everyone
to have access in the system.
We are ensuring that accessing this system is limited,
but in a way that we are able to serve our stakeholders
by assigning the focal person.
But again, we are now developing the data warehouse,
which is the the portal
that will be making some of the data
to be available to the partners
but again we also have a mandate
or obligations of ensuring that on annual basis,
we publish the statistical booklet that really highlights
all key indicators that anyone, a researcher or DP,
which is the partners, can be able to use
when they are reviewing their interventions.
Thank you.
- [Scott] Okay, and sorry, one last question here.
I think it&#39;s a good question,
one that I was wondering about myself.
Is there any penalty or are there any rewards
for actually following the SOPs
or if they&#39;re not actually following the SOPs,
are there any penalties
when you do the actual like go into the field, the ISS?
- That&#39;s another one.
So what we did was in linking together
some of these mechanisms or framework
that we have accountability framework.
I think for us, what we have in Rwanda
is that each staff have what we call KPI,
key performance indicator.
Like if I&#39;m Andrew working in the facility,
I have a key performance indicator,
and my key performance indicator is linked to my TOR
and what I have to deliver on daily basis, so that&#39;s one.
And we have some portion of what we call PBF,
performance based financing, that is linked to my KPI,
which is performance based financing.
But it&#39;s not only that we have managed
to link all those mechanism
that really promotes the good quality data or reporting,
two different mechanisms.
One is performance based financing,
where people are evaluated on quarterly basis
based on different indicators.
Like in data management,
for us we have like three indicators,
I mean for data quality,
completeness, timelines, and accuracy.
All those three indicators
are in performance-based financing.
In case one indicator is not well done, you get zero
so there&#39;s no tolerance.
So it means they have to make sure
that all those key indicators are reported
and really reported well.
So if it&#39;s timeliness, you reported on time, 100%.
If it&#39;s accuracy, at least you&#39;re in a range of 5%.
If it&#39;s completeness, you&#39;re on range of 100%,
then that&#39;s when you get 100%.
But if one of those is maybe 80 or 60,
you&#39;ll get zero for everything.
So it means you have to make sure that everything is 100%.
Another thing is that accreditation,
we have managed to link also with accreditation.
In accreditation when they&#39;re trying to move facilities
from level one to level two, level three, level four,
they also review these tools.
They have to check if you have SOP in place.
They have to check if you understand the chapters of SOP.
They have to see if you undergo
the process of what SOP says.
They check different components
but also when it comes to data management,
they check those areas.
At least that one, when like me, I&#39;m in a facility A
and I see that my components
really made my facility to go in level two,
it is also a motivation.
Another one is this is where we are bringing the e-learning.
They&#39;ve been telling us that we train them
but we don&#39;t give them a certificate.
Now we are trying to keep the database
that also highlights who were trained
in the specific period of time
but also they get certificates.
So those are things that really motivate the facilities&#39;
interlinked frameworks that are in place
that motivates the facilities.
And as you go on,
people start having the attitude of doing it themselves.
Maybe one time when you visit us,
you will see that when it comes to first and fifth,
when you go to facility,
everyone will be telling you, &quot;Oh, we are late to report.&quot;
They will be really rushing
to ensure that they report on time
and ensure that everything is really accurate
because you know, on quarterly basis and six months,
there are a team of people
that will go down to check if what they reported
is the same as what they have.
And another thing is that after the ISS,
which is integrated supportive supervision,
the feedback is submitted officially,
it&#39;s the minister who signs the feedback.
It means, imagine if I&#39;m Andrew
and I see the letter of the minister
saying that my department is not performing well.
So they really make sure that the feedback
comes when it&#39;s positive
instead of coming when it&#39;s negative.
Another thing is that we don&#39;t only report
what they have done specifically,
we also get the general feedback
that can improve the system.
So we say, &quot;Generally we find that people don&#39;t conduct
maybe data validation meetings.&quot;
So it becomes like a general feedback.
That one also improves
because you get your specific feedback
but again, so you get the general feedback too,
that we have found everywhere
but at least you make sure that the next time
it&#39;s not also you
who is going to be highlighted in the report.
So I think those are the key things,
we have other steps like development partners
in their support area,
they also conduct the self checks
to ensure that people understand how to check this data.
We have districts that supervises lower levels.
We have lower levels, the district hospitals
that supervises the health centers
and all of this is also documented in SOP.
And we also go down and check
if the hospitals really supervise their health centers.
All those mechanism that brings in the supervision,
accountability, roles and responsibility,
contributes a lot when it comes to data quality.
- [Scott] That is the best way to end the entire academy.
Andrew, you actually have the honor
of being the very last presentation in the entire academy
and I think this is a really great one to end it on.