- [Scott] All right, so in this video
we are going to cover the second part
of detecting outliers in dashboard
using validation rule notifications.
The way that we&#39;re going to do this
is by building predictors
and then tying those predictors
to our validation rule notifications,
but in this video,
we&#39;re just going to go over how to configure the predictors.
Before we get into the nitty-gritty of building predictors,
let&#39;s just quickly take a look at some examples
of the kinds of outliers
that we&#39;re going to be able to detect with these predictors
and automatic validation notifications.
Here is a very common picture
that we see in a lot of countries.
We see we have various data elements,
sometimes indicators,
progressing over a series of months as a line chart,
and then we see one month for one of these data values
that is significantly higher than all the others.
You see most of them have a fairly linear trend,
and you see this one peak jutting out right in April 2018.
This is clearly an outlier.
This data does not follow the normal trend.
This data is so high above the normal accepted value range
that you can clearly see illustrated here
that it&#39;s almost certainly a data quality mistake.
Now, these kinds of data quality mistakes
can throw off national statistics,
so if every month we&#39;re expecting about 54,000,
in this case BCG doses,
and then, in one month,
you report 170,000 BCG doses.
Now, of course, that could be
from a massive, massive outreach campaign,
maybe some door-to-door vaccination efforts,
but by and large,
almost always these are going to be data entry errors
where maybe a person at a health facility or a hospital,
maybe they meant to put in 7,000 doses given,
and they put in 70,000 doses given, on accident.
It&#39;s a very easy thing to do.
You just add a couple of extra zeros
as you&#39;re putting data in, and you go to the next cell,
and you don&#39;t look back at...
It&#39;s very, very common,
and so we see a clear example of this here,
where you see a very common trend
across all these various data elements.
They&#39;re not changing or fluctuating
that much month-to-month,
but one month is really jutting out,
and if we were to leave this data entry error in place,
then, for April 2018,
you would probably see that the BCG dose coverage
was well over 100%, maybe 200%,
and that would make folks question
the quality and the validity of all of the other data.
If you have one month that&#39;s 200% BCG coverage,
can we trust the rest of the data?
So the point is that it&#39;s very, very important
to identify and correct
these kinds of data entry errors,
and the way that we&#39;re going to start showing you
how to do today
is have DHIS2 do this for you,
have DHIS2 automatically detect
these kinds of data entry errors,
these kind of data quality problems,
and send you a notification when it has detected them
so that you can correct it immediately.
You do not want these kinds of data entry errors
to linger in the system for very long,
so on this slide,
we&#39;re gonna look at just a couple of other examples
of some clear outliers.
The chart at the top is looking at BCG doses
to measle one doses dropout rate,
so that is the proportion of children
who are receiving the BCG dose
and then not receiving the first measles dose,
and we expect this to be zero.
We expect them, every single BCG dose,
to be the same value as the measles dose.
We expect every person to get both vaccinations,
and we can see that in some org units,
and these bars here are representing org units,
that we have some locations
where the children are receiving
significantly higher BCG vaccines
versus measles vaccines.
Now, of course, this should not be the case.
We should always see that the number of BCG vaccines
are the same as the number of measles vaccines.
This top chart is showing us
the BCG-to-measles-one-dose dropout rate,
and what we expect to see
is that the number of BCG doses given
is equal to the number of measles doses given.
Here, on the top chart, we have a target line of zero.
Again, that&#39;s indicative of the BCG vaccines
doses given should equal the measles.
We should be a one-to-one relationship there.
Then we&#39;re giving ourselves
an acceptable maximum range of 20%,
and that means that we are allowing,
in this particular country scenario,
a dropout rate of 20%
from BCG vaccine to measles one,
meaning that 20% of the children
who got the BCG vaccine
will not get the measles one dose,
and they&#39;re saying that that&#39;s an acceptable range,
of course, not ideal, but an acceptable range,
but you see we have two bars here.
These bars are representing health facilities
where we have a 72.1% dropout rate
and a 73.4% dropout rate.
Now, what does this mean?
This means that
we have 72.1
and 73.4%
of the children who received the BCG vaccine
not receiving the measles vaccine.
Now, obviously, this is a big problem.
This is either a data quality mistake,
or this is some kind of breakdown
in clinical service delivery.
We should never see a dropout rate this high,
so this is telling this program manager that,
&quot;Hey, we&#39;ve got problems in these two health facilities
&quot;in that the majority of children
&quot;who are receiving the BCG vaccine
&quot;are then not receiving the measles,
&quot;and so I need to follow up.&quot;
Hopefully, in this scenario,
you find that it&#39;s a data quality problem.
If it&#39;s not a data quality problem,
then you have some serious problems
with your measles one doses
in these two health facilities,
so those are the bars
that are going above the acceptable maximum range.
Let&#39;s look, now, though, at these few bars
that are going below the zero target line,
so they&#39;re going down.
These are negative values,
and we see that there are two here
that are really quite big.
We have one that&#39;s negative 74.5
and one that&#39;s negative 271.4.
What does this mean?
This essentially means
that we have more children receiving the measles vaccine
than we have receiving the BCG vaccine.
Now, that is extremely unusual,
basically, impossible from a clinical perspective.
This is almost certainly a data-quality issue
in these two health facilities
where the bar is going lower
than the target line,
and you see that we actually have three others,
health facilities that are reporting
that the measles one is higher than the BCG.
Now, there should be an acceptable range for this, too.
We appreciate that in many countries
you&#39;re reporting on two different cohorts of children
between the BCG vaccine and the measles one vaccine.
Maybe you have some kind of seasonal birth
patterns or trends in your country,
but a value of negative 74.5
and negative 271.4
should be considered extremely unacceptable
no matter how much
seasonality you have to your birth rates in your country.
It&#39;s basically guaranteed
that these are data quality problems,
that someone accidentally put in
far too few BCG vaccines
or far too many measles one doses,
so these are definitely something
that needs to be followed up on,
and the point of this chart at the top here
is showing you that you can see these
very, very, very clearly,
these bars that are way too high,
and these bars that are way too low,
and you&#39;re going to be able, if you&#39;re looking at this,
if you&#39;re a program manager,
to immediately follow up on these.
They should be as obvious as they possibly can be.
Again, examples of outliers,
especially that negative 271.4, an extreme outlier.
All right, let&#39;s take a look at the next chart below this.
This next chart below this
is looking at new malaria cases, under five,
versus new malaria cases, five and above.
The under five are showing up here
as the green portion of these stacked column,
or excuse me, this is a stacked bar chart,
and the blue portion is showing
the five-and-above proportion of the population
in this stacked bar chart,
and you see that we have set our range
for this chart to be up to 100%,
so here we have, essentially, a clear representation
of the proportion of total new malaria cases
being disaggregated by under five and over five.
Now, we expect, in most countries
that have malaria,
to have about 30%
of our new malaria cases
to be under five, okay?
That&#39;s a very, very common trend
that we see around the world where we have endemic malaria,
so you see that at the 30% line, that&#39;s what we have.
We have a black line going through 30%
that says expected range under five, minimum.
Now, we&#39;re giving ourselves a little bit of a buffer
because it can vary based upon your population distribution
in terms of age,
but we then give ourselves
an acceptable upper range of 35%,
and you see, again, at the 35% line,
we have a strong black line cutting through that,
and it&#39;s telling us that between 30 and 35%,
we should see
that under-five population end
and the over-five population begin.
Now, what you see here, if you look through the months,
kind of going from top to bottom as you scan through,
you see that in November 2018,
our new malaria cases under five
are around 65%.
You see that green at November 2018.
You see that green line
going way, way, way, way past the acceptable ranges
and going far into what, in the other months,
is just the blue, just the over five,
and this is another clear indication of an outlier,
so November 2018,
there is clearly an outlier
in your new malaria cases under five.
Someone accidentally put in a value that was way too big,
and you can see
that it&#39;s throwing off our national statistics.
It&#39;s throwing off our national distribution
and disaggregation of our age breakdown
of the new malaria cases,
so if you were to look at this,
you would say that somehow, in November 2018,
65% of our malaria cases
were under-five population.
Now, that&#39;s just not clinically possible.
I can&#39;t even imagine a scenario
in which that&#39;s clinically possible,
so that means that you have an outlier.
You have a data quality problem in November 2018,
and if you look at the values that we have reported
for our new under-five cases,
most months, they&#39;re ranging between,
they&#39;re ranging between
about 100,000,
maybe 150,000, something like that,
but here, in November 2018,
we&#39;re up above nearly, we&#39;re nearly 300,000 cases.
Whereas our over five is still
in the acceptable average that we&#39;re seeing,
and, of course,
you have to appreciate that malaria&#39;s seasonal,
so it&#39;s going to,
what we&#39;re not seeing here is the seasonal curve,
but we&#39;re still seeing
that the proportion is way out of whack.
It&#39;s just not possible,
so again, another clear indication of a outlier.
The point of these two charts, really,
is to show that we can see outliers
in a lot of different ways, right?
In the first chart,
we saw that we can see an outlier stick up
in a kind of month-to-month trend.
Here, on the first chart here,
we&#39;re able to see that outliers being illustrated
by a relationship between two different data elements,
so, for example, here,
a BCG-to-measles-one-dose dropout rate,
so we&#39;re comparing these two data elements together
to see outliers in one or the other,
and then, on this malaria example in this bottom chart,
we&#39;re seeing outliers represented
by disaggregations
of our clinical data by age.
You maybe also can do this by gender,
and so these are just to show you
that we can find outliers in a lot of ways,
but this requires you to look at the dashboards,
to look at your charts, to have these,
that you&#39;re routinely looking at them.
Of course, people are not always
routinely looking at their DHIS2 dashboards,
and so the most effective way
to make sure that people address these kinds of outliers
that are throwing off national statistics
is to configure DHIS2 to be able to automatically detect it
and to send a notification to the user who can correct it.
Okay, so let&#39;s take,
just before we get into the crazy predictor stuff,
let&#39;s just do a quick overview of
how do we identify these outliers on a standard dashboard
and isolate the actual outlier itself?
Well, we have some steps for this,
and I&#39;m gonna show these to you just in a second.
The first step is that we want to isolate the period.
Usually, we just wanna drill into one month.
Then we want to change the chart type to a bar chart.
Then we need to isolate the data element.
Then we need to isolate the facility level
to see where the data is coming from,
and then we change the layout
so that org units is in category, period&#39;s in filter,
and data is in series.
Now, I just did that really fast.
Let me just show it to you in real life here,
so I&#39;m going to go to the demo site
for the academies.
Here we are.
I&#39;m going to log in as demo
and then District1#.
- [Scott] Yeah, okay, so here we have a similar chart
to what I just showed you,
and I think even Bob mentioned this in the videos.
Where is the outlier here?
Well, there&#39;s probably two outliers:
This point here, back May 2019, ANC first visits,
and this one here, ANC first visits
from January 2020.
Now, how do we figure out where this data is coming from?
Where&#39;s the facility that&#39;s causing this outlier, right?
Now we need to do a quick recap
of how to use the Data Visualizer app,
so what I&#39;m gonna do
is just show you the whole process here.
I am going to, I can&#39;t explore this on the dashboard,
so I&#39;m going to click the Open In Visualizer App button,
and that&#39;s gonna take me
into the Data Visualizer application,
so now we&#39;re in the application,
and we could start to drill into this data.
What was my first step?
My first step was to isolate the periods,
so we know that the outlier&#39;s in January 2020.
I am going to go to my period selection.
I&#39;m going to deselect all these periods.
You see we have 13 months here selected.
I&#39;m gonna deselect these.
I&#39;m gonna go to fixed periods,
and I&#39;m gonna say January 2020.
Turn that one on, and here we go.
Just some dots because we have a trend line,
but we don&#39;t have a trend if it&#39;s just one period.
Here&#39;s still my outlier, way up here.
Then we need to change the chart type to a bar chart,
so I&#39;m gonna go over here to the chart types.
Change it to a column.
You could also change it to bar.
I&#39;m gonna choose column, and there we go,
so now we actually see all the data next to each other,
and still, here&#39;s our outlier, all right?
Now we want to isolate that data element,
that data element that has the outliers ANC first visits,
so I&#39;m gonna come to data,
and I&#39;m gonna turn off everything
that&#39;s not ANC first visits.
Click Update. Boom.
Now we just got one big bar. That&#39;s fine.
Now let&#39;s figure out
where this data is actually coming from.
Now, the easiest way to do that
is to go into our organizational units,
and you see right now I have
the relative User Organization Units tick box selected.
I&#39;m going to untick that.
I&#39;m going to select National level, or the National,
and then I&#39;m gonna select my level,
and I&#39;m gonna go ahead
and go all the way down to Facility level, okay?
So that&#39;s gonna show me all of the facilities.
Click update. Nothing changed.
Why did nothing change?
Because my layout is not correct,
so the last step is to change the layout.
We are going to move organizational units to category.
We are going to move period to filter,
which automatically went for us
when we switched out with the org units,
and we&#39;re going to leave
data in series.
Click Update. Boom.
Where is that outlier? Well, it is clear.
This is right here.
Outlier is at facility 147,
and in one month, they reported 35,888
ANC first visits, okay?
This is how you isolate for the outliers
going from a dashboard and through the Data Visualizer.
A few steps here, right?
You also have to know how to use the Data Visualizer.
Now, wouldn&#39;t it be nice
if this notification was just sent directly to my e-mail?
How do we do that?
Well, that&#39;s what we&#39;re gonna talk about now.
How do we see this outlier sent directly to my e-mail?
I know I just went through that quite quickly.
If you want to revisit how I just gone through
and use the applications and the dashboards
to identify this outlier,
please go back and rewatch this presentation,
and you&#39;re certainly welcome to slow it down if necessary.
All right, and again,
I showed this example just before the break,
but Rwanda has at least configured some to do this,
at least partially, to automatically detect the outliers,
and send them, and push them to people&#39;s, to e-mails.
All right, so the way
that we actually calculate the outlier threshold,
and, again, we have to compare the data that is entered
against an outlier threshold.
The way that we actually calculate that outlier threshold
is using predictors,
and we put that predicted value into a validation rule.
Predictors...
Right, so predictors have typically only been used
for data elements in DHIS 2.28 to 2.34.
Starting in 2.35,
we can actually start to do some of this analysis,
not using predictors, but using indicators,
so the release that we actually just put out yesterday,
you can start to use this and standard indicators,
but most of you, basically, all of you
because we released it yesterday,
are not using 2.35 yet.
I&#39;m gonna show you how to do it
in 2.28 to 2.34.
So let&#39;s take a look at some of these predictors.
What are these calculations for?
So predictors really use
previously reported values.
They use previously reported values
to calculate a new value, all right?
That&#39;s really what predictors are for,
and we can, a couple of examples of this,
so the first example:
I want to get the average malaria incidence
over the last six months, right?
You can&#39;t use a standard indicator for that.
You cannot use,
the only thing that you can use
to calculate that value in DHIS2 is a predictor.
Another example: I wanna calculate
the average ART consumption over the last three months.
Maybe you&#39;re using DHIS2
for some kind of supply chain monitoring,
and using predictors,
you would be able to calculate, say, average consumption.
Next point: I want to see the average ANC visits
with three standard deviations,
&#39;member, we talked about
what standard deviations were yesterday,
for the last 12 months.
This would produce an ANC 1 outlier threshold.
This is really the,
actually, what we&#39;re gonna be building now.
We want to see what is the outlier threshold,
and the way we calculate that is
we want three standard deviations from the average
over the last 12 months.
Predictors can also be used,
the next bullet point, the fourth bullet point here,
predictors can also be used
to count the number of facilities that report some value.
This is a very, very highly requested
indicator in DHIS2,
and even though we&#39;re not,
it&#39;s not related to data quality, necessarily,
I just wanna make the point clear
that using predictors, you can count the number
of org units that did something,
so I wanna know every org unit
that recorded more than five malaria cases
or how many org units recorded more than five malaria cases.
Well, you can actually get that number
using predictors from aggregate data.
A couple of words of warning here.
Predictors have to be scheduled jobs.
Just like we talked about scheduling jobs
and validation rules,
predictors have to be scheduled jobs.
Predictors do also require quite a lot of processing
on your CPU, on your servers,
so if you have a lot of that predictors running,
quite often, you can really tax your server,
just like we talked about with validation rules,
so you have to be very careful
about how many predictors you have run, when they run,
and how much data they actually generate
because these could all have server (stammers).
They could all affect your server. Excuse me.
If you are a server expert
or a server administrator out there,
please feel free to talk to us
about exactly how you should be considering
how many predictors to run, when to run them,
how much data to store
because if you just set these up
without considering how your server is performing,
you could really set yourself up for disaster,
so how do we make a predictor?
Well, predictors are actually,
the value that&#39;s generated through a predictor
is actually stored as a data element in DHIS2,
and the reason that this is good or is useful
is that that data element can then be used in indicators.
It can be used in validation rules.
It can be used in anywhere that you use a data element,
so again, predictors are very different
than standard indicators.
Standard indicators calculate values on the fly.
They do not store those values.
They just, every time you turn on an indicator,
that value&#39;s calculated, right?
Predictors actually calculate the value
and then store that value as a data element
so that you can go back and use it in other places,
so how do we do this?
We first make a data element.
Then we make the predictor,
and we assign that predictor
to store that value that it generates in the data element.
Then, just like with indicators and data elements,
we have to put the predictor in a predictor group.
Then we schedule the predictor group to run,
just like we did with the validation rules,
and then, finally, we can put that predictor
into a validation rule
to allow us to get those outlier detection going,
so how do we make the outlier threshold?
Well, the first step
is that you have to make your data element,
and so I&#39;m going to quickly cover how to make data elements.
This is not a DHIS2 configuration course, specifically,
but you have to make the data element first,
and this is the screen to make a data element.
Again, you go to your Maintenance app.
You click Data Elements.
You click the plus button,
and then you&#39;re into making a data element.
You have to give your data element a name, of course.
You also have to give it a short name.
Typically, the short name is the same as the long name.
In this case,
we&#39;re saying ANC1 Outlier Threshold, hyphen, your name,
and again, you&#39;re putting your, hyphen, your name
in case you&#39;re doing this right now.
You&#39;re following along.
You&#39;re able to recognize your outlier threshold
from anyone else who&#39;s making theirs right now.
Your domain type will be set to aggregate,
your value type set to number,
and your aggregation type set to sum.
Then we need to go in and make the predictor,
so again, we go to Maintenance app.
We scroll all the way down
to the bottom of the Maintenance app.
You&#39;ll see the predictors there.
You&#39;ll click on the predictor,
and you can click that blue plus button again,
and you&#39;ll go into making the predictor.
The screen you see here is actually how,
is the screen you would build the predictor in.
Again, first step, as always, give it a name.
Second step is, of course,
you can also give it a short name, and a code,
and a description as well,
but the second compulsory step is to define the output,
so we just made a data element.
We need to go in and find that data element we just made
and assign that data element to this predictor,
and just to repeat myself,
the predictor will store the value that is generated
in that data element, okay?
We also have to define a period type,
so at what frequency will,
so the frequency was (indistinct) run,
but how will that aggregated value
in that data element be stored?
And we&#39;re gonna say monthly here,
and then, the next step, which is absolutely required,
but it does not have an asterisk next to it,
and so please hear me.
You have to select an organizational unit group level,
or sorry, organizational unit level.
You have to select
an organizational unit level for predictors,
so here, the typical rule of thumb is
select the level at which the data is captured
against the values that will be used
to calculate your predictor.
Select that same level,
so in this case, ANC data is coming in at facility level,
so I want my predictor,
I want the value that is generated
to also be stored at facility level,
so I&#39;m selecting facility here, okay?
So please, you have to select an organizational unit level.
If you don&#39;t, the predictor will not work.
The next step
is to define your generator, okay?
In the generator,
this is where you actually put in the calculation
for the predictor,
and in the generator,
you first have to define a missing value strategy.
This is the same as the validation rules,
and it will just say if the values that are missing,
how do I handle the values that are missing
in the calculation that you&#39;re providing?
The default is skip any values if it&#39;s missing,
and the question is, is this usually good?
And typically, with predictors, it&#39;s not useful.
We actually want the calculation,
even if there are some values missing,
and the reason is for that
because we still wanna calculate this value.
This value&#39;s actually referencing previously reported data,
so even if, and in this case,
we&#39;re actually gonna be looking
at 12 previous months of data,
so if we leave it to skip if all values are missing
or skip if any values are missing,
then, if it skip if any values are missing,
then if there&#39;s one month of where there is no data,
then we won&#39;t actually generate our predictor,
and that&#39;s not what we want.
We actually want them to generate the predicted value
for the average over the last 12 months
even if there is one of those months
that doesn&#39;t have a value.
Okay, again, I think this is something
that&#39;s easier to show you than to
to talk about on a slide,
so I am gonna go into my Maintenance app.
I&#39;m gonna scroll all the way down to predictors.
I&#39;m gonna go into my generator.
All right, and remember,
we&#39;re making a predictor that is going to produce
an outlier threshold for ANC 1,
so again, how do we calculate an outlier threshold?
Well, the outlier threshold is the average
plus three standard deviations
of the value,
so how do we do that?
Well, in predictors,
we are allowed to type in various mathematical operators.
If you&#39;re curious on what all of these operators are,
I think I have a slide on it,
but you can also just Google DHIS2 predictors,
and there is a clear documentation on all the various ones,
but for the ones
that we&#39;re gonna use right now is AVG,
and then, that&#39;s the average,
and then we&#39;re gonna find ANC 1,
and I&#39;m just gonna say ANC 1 visits.
Close my,
sorry, close my brackets,
and you see my translator&#39;s already working,
so I&#39;m taking the average of ANC 1,
plus
I&#39;m gonna do another open bracket,
three times
the standard deviation,
and standard deviation is typed S-T-D-D-E-V,
another open brackets.
I&#39;m gonna then add ANC 1 visits again
and two closes.
Right, so now it&#39;s actually translating properly,
so we are taking the average
plus three standard deviations from the average.
Remember, yesterday we talked about standard deviations
and the bell curve.
Three standard deviations off the average
means that it&#39;s going to pick up any value
that is 98% different
than the average, okay?
98% different than the average
over all of the sampled values.
All right. Again, I have to give it a name.
For the sake of time,
I&#39;m just gonna copy and paste that in there.
Submit.
Okay, here it is again.
I&#39;m back into my PowerPoint,
so the formula for standard deviations
is average plus the data element
plus three standard deviations, three times S-T-D-D-E-V,
and then ANC 1 again.
You might be wondering if this is case sensitive.
In older versions of DHIS2, it is case sensitive.
In newer versions, it is not,
so if you&#39;re using DHIS2 point,
I believe, 31 or older
and you&#39;re using predictors,
you need to put these in all capital letters.
If you&#39;re using 31 or newer, so 31, 32, 33, or 34,
you can put these in lowercase letters, like you see here.
Yeah, so here are the other functions for predictors.
You can see that there&#39;s quite a lot,
like average, count, max, median,
min, standard deviation, sum.
These can be used in different situations.
The next step is that we have to define our counts.
Sorry for the spelling mistake here on count,
but we have to define our counts.
Now, again, in this particular situation,
looking at producing an outlier threshold,
we want to reference the last 12 months of data,
so we are gonna say
12 sequential sample counts here.
A sequential sample count is just
what was the last period?
And how many of those periods do you wanna count?
So we&#39;re gonna say our last period was months.
We&#39;ve already defined that elsewhere in the predictor.
We&#39;re gonna say 12.
We wanna look at the last 12 months of data.
Our annual sample count, which is saying
how many previous years do you wanna reference?
We&#39;re gonna leave that one to zero,
and then, we have a sequential skip count.
Sequential skip count will allow you to say
I wanna skip some number of previous samples.
In this case, we&#39;re not adding a,
we don&#39;t need a sequential skip count,
so we&#39;re not gonna even add it in,
so what does this actually look like?
Let&#39;s pretend that we are in
March right now, okay?
Let&#39;s pretend that we are in March,
and the numbers that you see listed here,
these are months of the year,
so January through December,
and then 1, 2, 3, 4, January, February, March, April.
Okay, so let&#39;s say that we are in April,
and we say we have a sequential sample count of 12.
What will that do?
Well, that will take the previous 12 months,
so that would take from March to April of last year,
annual sample count is zero,
so we&#39;re just looking at just those last 12 months,
and our skip count is zero,
so we&#39;re not skipping any values in the last 12 months.
This can become more complex, of course, right?
So for seasonal data,
you typically have to have some combination
of annual sample count and sequential sample count
to be able to factor in the epi curve of malaria,
that bell curve that you have of seasonal malaria
or any kind of seasonal disease.
I won&#39;t go into it now for the sake of time,
but there is clear documentation
on our website in our user manual
on how to build out predictors
using combinations of sequential sample counts
and annual sample counts
to factor in more seasonal data.
So that is how you make
the outlier, or sorry, the predictor
that generates the outlier threshold.
How do we then put that into our validation rules?
Again, we wanna have a validation rule
that checks the ANC 1 value
against the ANC outlier threshold,
and say if that ANC 1 value
is higher than that outlier threshold,
send me an alert.
Send me a notification.
Let me know that this value
is 99% different than the average.
Well, it&#39;s the exact same process that we just went through
in building validation rules.
Here, you can see building out the validation rule.
We give it a name.
We then give it a description.
Again, an instruction.
You can define the importance.
Our monthly type, again,
or sorry, excuse me, our period type, again, is monthly.
Our left-side expression is ANC 1 visits.
Our operator is less than,
and our right-side operator or expression
will be ANC 1 threshold,
so again, validation rules need to be defined
based on what we know to be true,
and in this case, we can interpret that to be ANC 1 visits
should be less than ANC 1 outlier threshold,
and again, that threshold value is a data element
that is coming from a predictor,
so what happens when we run this validation rule?
We can see that we received
a lot of validation notifications,
and just looking at this one example here,
we can see
that we have a value
for facility 583 in October 2019
that was reported
a ANC 1 value of 126,
but our outlier threshold is 117.9,
so it&#39;s saying, &quot;Hey, look.
&quot;126 is bigger than 117.9.
&quot;It should be less than.
&quot;Here&#39;s an alert,&quot; okay?
Before I cut over to
revisiting some of the scheduling,
I do wanna quickly show you
how you use predictors to count org units,
and in this case,
I&#39;m saying I&#39;m counting the number of org units
that have a stock-out of some commodity.
This is not related to data quality.
It&#39;s just highly requested thing to know,
and so, in predictors,
we can also put in if statements in our generators,
and that if statement here,
if you look at the translator,
where it says valid at the bottom of the screenshot,
just directly above that, you have the translation,
and this saying if the stock-out of RDTs,
number of days is greater than zero,
count a one.
If not, record a zero,
so what is that actually gonna do?
That&#39;s gonna say that if you have more than one,
or if you have one or more days of stock-out of RDTs
that&#39;s recorded in your monthly reporting form,
then it&#39;s going to count a one value,
and that one will be saved as a data element
against that facility,
and you can use that value
to then aggregate up the hierarchy
and say how many facilities
did I have a stock-out of RDTs last month?
Or you can even, say, put that value onto a map,
and you can make a map showing specifically
these are the facilities that had a stock-out last month.
That&#39;s how predictors can be used
to count health facilities.
Again, it&#39;s a little bit more of an advanced concept.
If you have questions, please send those on Slack,
and we&#39;ll be happy to come back to them.
For the sake of time here,
we don&#39;t have time to go into
more advanced functionalities with predictors,
but there is a lot that you can do with them.
Hopefully, you appreciate that.
All right, so one additional point
that I need to make
is that predictors
also have to be scheduled in the Scheduler app, okay?
So it&#39;s a different job
than the maintenance job
that we use to schedule validation rules,
so we have our ANC outlier threshold,
and we are going to make the job type predictor.
Again, you select the frequency that you want.
Just like we did the validation rules, exact same,
you can select a predefined frequency.
You can put in your own frequency through a cron expression,
or you could say continuous execution.
Again, I highly recommend
that you do not use continuous execution
unless you are in a disease-surveillance scenario,
and you&#39;re only using one or maybe two validation rules.
The job type will be predictor.
This is, again, different.
The job type for the validation rule
was a monitoring job type.
This is a predictor job type,
but the parameters are the same,
so we have to define our relative start
and our relative end.
Again, rule of thumb, relative start, negative 60,
maybe negative 30.
You just wanna cover a few previous months, right?
Relative in to being just one, which is tomorrow,
and then, when we have to give our predictors
into our Scheduler,
so you just type out the predictors here.
You&#39;ll be able to select them, and then you add the job.
Now, let&#39;s say that you have some predictor jobs.
Then, you have your analytics tables
and your validation rule alerts.
If you&#39;re a system administrator,
I&#39;m talking to you right now.
If you&#39;re not a DHIS2 techie,
you&#39;re probably not gonna appreciate a lot of this,
but the point to be made
is that you have to schedule these jobs to run concurrently.
You cannot schedule these jobs to run at the same time,
and they need to run in a specific order, okay?
For you to actually be able to generate
your validation rule alerts,
so the first thing is that
you schedule the predictors jobs to run first, okay?
And you, again, you want to have all of these jobs run
when the server usage is low,
when there&#39;s not a lot of people on the database.
The predictor jobs, for example,
you see the example here on the right side of the screen,
could run at, say, 11 o&#39;clock, 23 on a Sunday.
Very few people are gonna be looking at DHIS2
at 11 o&#39;clock on a Sunday.
Then you have your analytics tables run after that.
Again, the analytics tables
are just a function that has to be performed
in order to see the data on the dashboards
or in the Data Visualizer on maps, et cetera,
so you want those to probably run
right after their predictors.
You can have that run maybe an hour later.
Run that at midnight on Sunday.
Analytics tables, depending on the size of your database,
may take a while,
so if you give yourself a few extra hours of buffer,
and say then you want your validation rule alerts jobs
to run at maybe 03,
so a few hours after your tables, your analytics tables,
and if you run them in this order,
that means that your predictors come first.
Those predictors are then able to be seen on your dashboards
if you want, if you have them there,
and then, they&#39;ll be able to be pushed out
in your e-mails.
If everything goes properly,
then this will all happen when you&#39;re asleep.
When you wake up in the morning,
you&#39;ll see an e-mail from DHIS2
saying, &quot;Hey, look.
&quot;These are the alerts that were generated last night.&quot;
Okay.
There is some question
already posted in the community practice
or on the Slack channel around how do I get e-mail?
Or how do I configure DHIS2 to send an e-mail?
Well, the reality is that
you have to generate an e-mail service
from your service provider.
DHIS2 does not have a built-in e-mail host.
This has to be provided from your service provider,
so if you are a ministry of health,
and you are using a telecommunications company
in your country hosting your DHIS2 instance,
or hosting, say, your e-mail service for your ministry,
that host, that company, whoever it is,
needs to provide an e-mail host
or an e-mail endpoint for your DHIS2 instance
to be able to send e-mails.
Again, not something
that University of Oslo can provide you,
so it has to come
from whoever&#39;s hosting your e-mail service.
Many of you are probably using Google
as your default e-mail service,
so if you have a Gmail, for example,
and if you are using Google,
then we&#39;ve given you some of the guidance
on how to configure this,
but you have to provide a host name,
a port number, a username, a password.
A username and password, this is for your e-mail service.
This is not for your DHIS2.
You need to provide a TLS, an e-mail sender address,
and an address to send test e-mails.
Again, all of this has to be provided
by your e-mail service provider.
We cannot provide this to you.
This has to come from whoever&#39;s hosting your e-mail service.
Any telecommunications company that hosts e-mail services
should be able to provide this to you.
These are fairly basic things, to be honest with you.
The example that you see here is
if you have your e-mail hosted by, say, Amazon Web Services,
on the left side of the screen,
and like we do here at DHIS2,
we have our e-mail&#39;s hosted by Amazon Web Services,
so that would be our host criteria.
Of course, you don&#39;t have our password,
so you can&#39;t use the same thing.
Okay, so we have maybe just 10 more minutes
for any burning questions.
Nora, is there any terrible issues out there,
or what&#39;s the most terrible issue out there?
- [Nora] Yes, Scott, there were a few questions.
I&#39;m just going through them.
Under introduce yourself from (indistinct).
Does predictors work in event and tracker too?
How does that different from program indicators?
- [Scott] That&#39;s a really good question.
Yes, you can use event and tracker data in predictors.
The difference between a program indicator
is that that predictor value is actually saved
as a data element, right?
So you&#39;re able to, then, use that predicted value
in other calculations, in validation rule notifications,
anywhere that you can use a data element,
and that&#39;s very unique
in that you cannot do that with a program indicator.
There&#39;s also different types of calculations
that can be done in predictors
that cannot be done in program indicators.
Predictors can also incorporate values
across multiple programs,
so that could be very useful to you,
that if you have a program for ANC,
a program for immunization, a program for birth,
or follow-up, or something like that,
and you want to have a value
across all of those different programs,
you can use that to make a single calculation.
You can do that in a predictor.
You cannot do that in a program indicator.
Any other questions?
- [Nora] Yes, there was something about
can you use data elements across different data sets?
- [Scott] Yes, yeah, of course,
you can use any combination of data elements that you want
to make a predictor.
- [Nora] And then, for the general QA,
that the number of, from Fernando,
the number of standard deviation to add to the average
to set the thresholds that vary
depending on the value we&#39;re tracking,
but a good rule of thumb is three,
and I think that is what you are (indistinct) using.
- [Scott] Yeah, I think he said it perfectly.
I would totally agree.
I think three is a good rule of thumb.
We don&#39;t have the intelligence in DHIS2 yet
to be a little bit more flexible there.
We would like it to help the user define
what would be an appropriate number of standard deviations.
We are kind of starting to explore how to do that,
but right now, I think you&#39;re absolutely right.
Just set it to three.
Three is probably not going to steer you wrong
in most cases.
- [Nora] Then there&#39;s a question just above that
from Paul from Cameroon.
Can you explain the significance of each term:
0, 1 0 0, 1, 0?
I think that&#39;s a cron expression?
- [Scott] That could be a cron expression.
It could also be that he was referring to the if statement,
so I could go a little bit more into detail
on the cron expression,
so let me just get back.
Let me go to the Scheduler app.
Okay, so it looks like some folks have already done this.
That&#39;s great, so the cron expression...
If I just make a new job, I&#39;ve gotta define my job type.
Again, the monitoring job is for validation rules.
The predictor is for predictors,
so I&#39;m just gonna make a validation rules.
My cron expression,
I have the ones that I can already choose,
so like every day at midnight,
and, say, every week,
and this would be every week
at 3, I think it&#39;s 3:00 a.m.,
so I&#39;m just gonna say test, Add Job.
Yeah, okay, so that would be the first day at every day,
first day of the week at 3:00 a.m.,
so let me kind of explain this to you
a little bit more clearly,
so each one of these values,
so we have
0 0 3 ? *
and then MON.
Well, hopefully, you understand the MON.
That&#39;s Monday,
so each one of these actually represents a unit of time,
so we have second, minute,
so zero, zero seconds,
at zero minutes on the third hour,
and then we have day and month,
so it&#39;s the day is defined as Monday, and the month is,
or sorry, we have a day and week,
and then the day of the week, month,
so we have this running every Monday.
Now, I know that is kind of confusing to folks.
Please just Google it, so
if I just Google cron expressions,
there are free formatters online
for building cron expressions,
so, for example,
if I want to say I want something to run
every month, then...
I&#39;m sorry.
I want something to run every day
starting on Sunday.
Then automatically generates a cron expression for me.
If I could say I want every day
on the first day of the month,
then you see it generates a cron expression,
so if I copy this,
go back to DHIS2.
- [Man] All right, Scott,
there was an update about that question from the user.
Apparently, it&#39;s about predictor configuration.
(Nora speaks indistinctly)
- [Scott] Okay, well, let me just finish this then,
so I&#39;ve just copy-and-pasted the cron expression
for every day, the first day of every month here,
so you see that.
If I click Save Changes,
then you see you can say when&#39;s my next execution?
You can see my next execution
is November 1st at midnight, okay?
So you see that there,
so that&#39;s how you can do cron expressions.
The actual question was
on setting the org unit level for the predictors.
Is that correct?
- [Nora] It was to do, to count facilities
with dropout drugs.
- [Scott] Yeah, so this is not...
Actually, in two weeks, we have an entire academy
on supply chain
and building predictors for the supply chain,
so I recommend that you attend that academy
if you really wanna specifically know how to do that,
but very quickly here, let me just show you,
if I wanna count the number of facilities
that have any specific value that&#39;s recorded,
I go into my generator, and I type if, open brackets,
and I&#39;m just gonna say
acute flaccid paralysis death under five,
just for the exam,
and I&#39;m gonna say if acute flaccid paralysis deaths
are greater than, let&#39;s say five,
then record one,
if else, record a zero.
Now, what does this predictor do?
You can see that it is considered valid.
This will say if that health facility that month
recorded more than five acute flaccid paralysis deaths,
then it will count one,
so the way you translate these if statements is like
if this, then this;
if else, then this,
so if this is greater than five, count one;
if else, count zero, all right?
So this is basic, basic, basic,
basic computer programming, basic if statements,
but here, that&#39;s what is going on,
so if this is greater than five,
then count one;
if else, count zero,
and so what will this do?
This will say, &quot;Oh, this facility had more than five.
&quot;Record a one value,&quot;
and that one value, again, is saved as a data element,
and that data element can be aggregated up,
so you can say how many, across the entire country,
how many health facilities did I have more than five
acute flaccid paralysis deaths this month?
And you&#39;ll have a number there
because for every single one that does,
it&#39;s counting a one, okay?
Now, this is a very basic example.
You can make these much, much more complex,
and you&#39;ll actually,
if you do come to the Supply Chain Academy in two weeks,
you&#39;ll see that we&#39;ve made some
that are much more complex than this,
but this is a very basic one
to be able to count the number of facilities
that record any particular value.