- [Narrator] So another area that I wanted to discuss
was data element value types,
in particular, numerical value types.
And this is true for whether you&#39;re using tracker
or aggregate data.
So there&#39;s a lot of different numeric value types
that are available in DHIS2.
So there&#39;s six to be exact,
and we can see a description of them here.
I&#39;m not going to say the description.
You can please download the slides and you can have a look
at the description of each
or you can of course, refer to the documentation.
Now what happens here?
The data element value types actually place
a hard check on what data, sorry,
can be stored within the data element itself.
So if I pick number as my numeric value type
for a particular data element,
this means I can enter basically any value.
I can enter a negative value.
I can enter a value with the decimal point.
I can enter a value that is maybe not valid, right?
So we have to be much more careful
when we actually have a look at this,
and one thing you can do,
I&#39;ll make sure to put the link to the instance
in this presentation, but you can go to this instance,
it&#39;s the Sierra Leone demo instance,
and just have a look at the value types.
If you go to maintenance and data elements,
and then filter the list by value types,
check number for example, and see if it&#39;s appropriate
for a lot of the data elements that are there.
And if it&#39;s not, you know,
maybe something should be considered.
I&#39;d say about 80% of the time or more,
depending on the system,
positive integer is typically the numerical type
that you would want to apply to your data elements.
You&#39;re often not going to have lots of negative values.
Of course, there are specific scenarios
where you will need that,
but you won&#39;t need it most of the time.
You also will need having, you know,
other than having whole values,
you probably will need some hard check on this.
So this means when I enter anything below zero,
if I enter negative value
or if I enter a value with the decimal place,
DHIS just won&#39;t store that value.
So you do have to be careful in some sense,
because you wanna make sure
they can enter the value that they need to, you know.
There is scenarios of course, where you might need decimals,
maybe you&#39;re importing data for example,
for an adventure tracker program of some kind,
maybe a survey for example,
where there&#39;s some percentages calculated
and you&#39;re storing that.
So you should be aware of the value type of course,
that you&#39;re utilizing in that scenario.
I&#39;m not saying always use this value
and value type, but you know,
it&#39;s probably the one that you often wanna use the most.
And if you just have a quick look in systems,
if you go to their maintenance,
their data element maintenance
and just kind of check, filter out that list and see, okay,
is there a lot of numbers and is that appropriate
for the data elements
that are actually stored in my system?
Because if it&#39;s not, then there might be some consideration
in order to change that.
The issue is of course,
if you&#39;re going to update this and modify this,
there could be values that are stored already previously.
So you would wanna go through kind of do
a bit of an audit of it and just make sure
that you&#39;re not kind of messing
things up even more than they already are,
but you can see the kind of impact
that the value type would have on your data quality.
If you&#39;re having all kinds of incorrect values
being stored in your data elements, then of course,
when you go to do your aggregation,
it&#39;s going to be wrong as well.
So when you review your data
or when you see any of your data outputs,
there&#39;s going to be some problems
with your data quality in all likelihood.
And this is more a result of user error
and things of that nature, right?
Maybe these values aren&#39;t being entered like this
incorrectly on the paper even,
but when they go to enter it on their keyboard,
lots of things can happen of course, right?
So we just have to be a bit careful
and institute this check,
just for the sake of kind of covering, you know,
this particular portion of our configuration.