- [Instructor] So another item is user management.
And where user management has the most impact
on data quality is actually related to data access.
So user roles, user groups and the authorities
that we then assign these roles.
So one thing is to keep on top of this,
because these authority sometimes change,
they get deprecated,
they don&#39;t really work in the way we intended over time
and keeping up-to-date on that
is not really the easiest thing to do.
But what are then the best practices for this?
So once again, I don&#39;t have the solutions
to a lot of these problems,
I think it&#39;s done differently in different places.
Certainly like everything else,
I always try to implement SOPs for this.
I will pull up an example of one
after I just kind of explain this a bit more.
But in a lot of places we could say the same thing
for users as we have for organization units,
decentralizing them becomes very challenging.
Decentralizing this function becomes very challenging,
particularly if you&#39;re having kind of top level expertise
in the system that you&#39;re implementing
and the ability then to manage users
is left to maybe a small group of people.
And there could be thousands of users in that system
that need to be managed.
We already talked about disabling, removing users.
This is very challenging just to leading any object.
But then, we wanna make sure we are organizing users
in some way, and then we have some methodology to do this.
So what can they view, what can they edit?
Maybe they can only see a subset of information.
And users also have an effect on user groups.
And user groups are very important actually
for this data access concept,
particularly when we&#39;re trying to do something
about sharing, because it&#39;s basically impossible to manage
sharing on a user level if you have thousands of users.
Even if it is possible,
theoretically, it&#39;s certainly not very practical.
So having these user groups there is quite important,
but they&#39;re often not there.
And if that&#39;s the case then, then what do you do?
So, user management is really important for data access.
I suggest proactive approaches are taken
when kind of implementing this initially,
many of us are past that point
and there&#39;s already lots of issues.
So, there has to be then procedures in place
in order to kind of handle this a bit more
because there are certain things that are not easily done
through the maintenance interface.
Some things you have to approach in a different way.
So just thinking about how we transfer these skills
over to the teams we&#39;re working with,
in order to allow them to control data access
in a more meaningful way that makes sense to them
based on their program&#39;s needs.
So here&#39;s another example,
standard operating procedure for creating users.
Now you might&#39;ve noticed at this point in time,
that I don&#39;t use any screenshots actually to create my SOPs,
and that is mainly because the user interface
keeps changing, the authorities keep changing.
So if you&#39;re trying to maintain this over time,
becomes quite challenging.
But the idea is also to make this as short
and understandable as possible.
So kinda make it straight to the point,
and just specify what people need to do
when they want to create a user with certain rights
in their system.
But this is another, there&#39;s not a,
there might be some problems with this approach of course,
but it&#39;s another way to kind of help things move along.
So I posted this and you can have a look at this as well,
basically just goes over what roles they should be assigned,
and which user groups they should be assigned
to you essentially
because this becomes a larger problem obviously
with access to the data as we have been discussing.
So we also have the issue of sharing.
And sharing is directly related to our user management.
So when user groups are well-defined,
then we can apply sharing to our sets of metadata.
But like I said, that&#39;s often not the case.
You might not have a lot of well-defined user groups
in the system.
And this is still kind of,
this concept has been around for some time,
but this whole idea of sharing both for tracker
and for aggregate is still quite challenging
in a lot of places making sure that the right people
have access to this data.
And more so then,
maybe this is something we set up initially,
we help people to set up initially.
But then what happens after that?
Long-term management of sharing
becomes very challenging, because there are no tools
to manage sharing well in DHIS2.
So we can kind of click on one item,
click on one data element and then share it, right?
Through the user interface.
But that&#39;s not practical, right?
There&#39;s no way you can manage sharing in a large system
like this, like a lot of the implementations
that we&#39;re working with.
So, what do we do then, we script a lot of this, right?
We come up with with different solutions,
there&#39;s different solutions out there that can be used
for scripting this process.
We come up with some way to do this ourselves,
and then maybe we document it at that snapshot,
at that point in time.
But then what happens as new programs are added,
new data elements are added, new data sets are added?
How do we share then all of these items?
How do we transfer this over then to countries as well?
Because there&#39;s no real good mechanism right now to do this
through the user interface that would make it easy
for countries to learn how to do sharing correctly.
So that&#39;s what we sometimes see it being done so poorly,
because there&#39;s not really a good mechanism for it there
at the moment, this is something we can fix, right?
Often we can go in there
and we can fix the sharing actually.
We can have a great influence there in helping countries
to fix this problem.
But the main challenge is then,
how do we have countries kind of take this up
to do a lot of these functions and operations on their own?
So here&#39;s an example of an actual system
where sharing has gone completely wrong.
It had over 6,000 dashboards,
nearly 3,000 of them had nothing on them,
the majority of them were completely private,
just private to that particular user,
so they were serving no function.
You had a couple shared with individual users,
you had a couple of maybe shared
with a couple of user groups,
there were a couple that were public.
And then we go through all the analytical objects as well,
all their favorites, all their data element groups,
all the indicator groups and categories, et cetera.
So when we have this amount of metadata in our system,
you can see there&#39;s obviously other problems here
unrelated to sharing all kinds of general problems
that we&#39;ve been discussing.
Maybe a complete lack of coordination,
lack of procedures in terms of adding metadata
to the system.
But then when we go to actually,
dive down into this a bit further,
because of the way that this is configured and shared,
it&#39;s going to make it extremely difficult
to find what is required to analyze your data.
This has a direct impact on the ability
to kind of output quality, sorry,
create quality outputs.
Because if I can&#39;t even find what I need,
then it&#39;s going to be extremely challenging
to create anything that is useful for my needs,
that I can even start to begin to review
the potential data quality issues.
And then, how do I handle that if I can&#39;t even see
what I want,
or if there&#39;s just so much overwhelming information,
if I have 83 public data element groups
with over 13,000 public data elements,
finding what I need is going to be extremely challenging.
So in some cases,
we want to share everything with everyone, right?
We want to kind of, as a data repository in particular,
we want to promote this type of sharing
of information across programs.
But at the same time, there might be instances
where we need to narrow what we&#39;re sharing
and make this work a bit more,
so people can see what they need to quickly,
find what they need to quickly and not just have access
to everything all at once.
So, there are two items here.
We can influence this more because we can go in there
and clean it up.
But at the same time, how do we then transfer the skills?
That&#39;s kind of the question I&#39;m posing.
How do we then transfer a lot of this over to countries
where, because we&#39;re going to script.
Cleaning up something like my example here,
we wouldn&#39;t do anything manually, right?
We would script all of this,
we would find other ways, other solutions,
to make this process a bit more automated.
So what I&#39;d like to do is kind of initiate
a bit of discussion around this topic,
because some of you might have solutions
that I&#39;ve not been able to think of obviously.
As I mentioned,
I didn&#39;t have the solution to all these problems,
I&#39;m able to identify a lot of them
and make long-term adjustments
to actually fix some of these things,
but nothing immediate in some cases.
So, if you have kinda more immediate solutions
or different ways to handle these,
certainly interested in hearing from you.
So when you assign programs and datasets
to organization units,
what considerations have you made in the past,
particularly as it relates to things like,
completeness of information and appropriate access
to those programs and datasets?
What are some approaches that have worked
when dealing with user management?
In particular, decentralized user management
and making sure people have the right access
to the right pieces of information?
How have you dealt with countries managing mass sharing?
Has this something that you&#39;ve been successful in imparting
to countries so they can manage this on their own,
or is this something
where you were still kind of heavily involved
with supporting due to the nature of your relationship
with that country and the kind of inability
that we have right now with DHIS2 tools
to do this easily?
So, have you been able to successfully decentralize
any of these roles?
That would also be very interesting to hear from you all.
And how have you approached capacity building
around these functions?
Because I think one of the main challenges is,
we&#39;re going to keep seeing this poor design
if we&#39;re not able to have others basically learn
how to do these various functionalities within their system.
If it&#39;s always his group supporting this,
then that&#39;s not sustainable.
That&#39;s not a sustainable approach,
that&#39;s not what we want to do.
It might be the case where the tools
need some significant modification in order to support these
and make these things easier to do.
But in the interim, we need some placeholder.
So, I&#39;m just curious how you&#39;ve kind of dealt
with a lot of these in the countries you&#39;re working with.
So we&#39;ve created a discussion board
for this particular topic
just to directly underneath within this module here.
And I&#39;d be really interested
if you could kind of just post some of these,
some answers to these questions.
Just to have a think about it
and post some responses to these.
If this is not something you have a lot of experience with,
don&#39;t worry, maybe you just read
some of the replies from others,
but this is something maybe we can come back to
when we have our live discussion later on.