- [Jenny] I&#39;m going to kick off the session
by giving you a bit of a historical perspective
on where South Africa was during the 1990s
and then in the early 2000s.
What we had is I think a very familiar scenario
to most of you that are attending this training.
Your countries probably experienced the same thing.
We had multiple health authorities.
These authorities use multiple forms for collecting data
and the data collection tools were not at all standardized.
In fact, when we did research on this,
we did find that there were
up to 50 plus data collection tools in a single facility.
It was largely a paper-based system.
And obviously this made analysis very difficult,
and we found the data wasn&#39;t being used.
And really if you submitted data or didn&#39;t submit data,
it wasn&#39;t picked up very quickly.
I&#39;ll give you an example of this.
There was a health authority in the Eastern Cape
at that time that decided they would really like to have
a lot more coherent information system,
developed a very primitive,
some simple minimum data set
with standardized data collection tools,
and had a method for analyzing this.
It was still paper based,
but it gave the facility managers the opportunity to see
what performance was, to graph that performance,
and then take action accordingly.
And in the process,
this health authority decided that they wouldn&#39;t submit data
to the province at that stage.
And so it took about a year and a half
before this was even picked up and queried.
It was also the beginning, shall I say,
this simplistic, primitive data information system
that was started there.
There was a parallel process happening
through the University of the Western Cape in Khayelitsha
where they were testing DHIS1 at that stage,
which is a non-web based system,
or was a non-web-based system.
And there was cooperation between the two parties,
which really led to the introduction of DHIS1 one,
first of all in the region
that this health authority was situated in,
and then escalated to the province
when they saw that really we&#39;re getting
much more useful data to work with
based on this development.
And so DHIS1 essentially used the minimum data sets
and what was being collected in that authority to populate
DHIS1 with some additions.
And it was rolled out, as I said,
to the Eastern Cape province.
And then because Eastern Cape
implemented it so successfully,
the national government became interested
and DHIS was eventually rolled out to the entire country.
As I said before, it was a computerized database,
not web-based.
It was based on MS Access and pivot tables.
But it did have some very good data quality features
amongst which we had data regression and interpolation.
We included validation rules, both absolute and statistical.
And for us, very importantly,
it had a very user-friendly method of customizing data sets
per facility type,
which allowed us to monitor completeness
of the data element capturing for those data sets.
This data was then extracted into standardized pivot tables,
using a DataMart functionality,
and then the data analysis and reporting
was done from there.
And people, in general, were very comfortable
with that system.
Together, with what was in the database,
we had a number of other initiatives
to facilitate the implementation.
The country developed a minimum data set
with standardized data collection tools.
We had a district health management
information system policy with a set of SOPs
ranging from the facility level
right up to provincial national level, which...
What would be the right word?
Which set out what was required from the users of data.
And also, very importantly,
the country began to employ information staff
in both the districts and provinces
to operationalize this whole DHIS1 roll out.
What we used to do in those days
was when a new form was introduced,
data quality checks were done within three to four months
to make sure that everyone
was interpreting the definitions correctly,
and so what was being captured in the system,
that was consistent and coherent,
and everyone was collecting the same,
and we could compare apples with apples.
We also undertook an extensive training on data quality
and on use of information
to ensure that people understood
the importance of the data quality
and that really the point of collecting data
is to make sure that it is used,
and it&#39;s not just collecting data for data sake.
Another initiative at that stage was that we introduced
pre-submission data validation,
and we developed a standardized template
for people to collect this, to do the pre-submission on.
I&#39;m going to talk more to this point
on pre-submission later.
So I won&#39;t give too much detail here. Sorry.
And the final thing was
that South Africa has a process
where data is locked at the end of the financial year
so that no further editing can be done.
So in addition to doing pre-submission data validation,
the country had data cleanup workshops in each province
to make sure that we picked up on anything
that would seriously skew the data before locking.
And the data&#39;s locked
and people prepared their annual reports based on that.
So why did we stick with DHIS1 for so long,
and why did we then decide to update to DHIS2?
Mainly the delay was because of the data quality
and analytics features that DHIS1.4
that we were using at that stage had,
and the DHIS2 at that stage
that did not have all of the data quality features
that were available in DHIS1.4.
However, the compelling shortcomings in DHIS1.4
meant that we decided
that we really did need to move to DHIS2,
not least of which was the updating of standalone computers
at every capturing point when a new board was released,
and also the length of time
for data to reach the National Department of Health.
What we had at that stage was that
data that for a specific reporting period
would only be available in the national database
60 plus days after the reporting period,
which really didn&#39;t leave room for using the data.
It was more just getting a historical perspective
on what it looked like.
So now that we are on DHIS2,
we have certain data quality strategies
that we follow in the country.
Obviously we&#39;ve gone for a minimum data sets
because this impacts so heavily on data quality.
The more data you collect,
the more likely you are to have data quality issues.
The minimum data set, the process is that
it is revised every two years.
And it goes through a great amount of consultation
across all levels from national to province
to districts to sub-districts,
and the programs are given an opportunity to input into it.
And they also rigorously debate
what was in the previous data, minimum data set,
and anything that really wasn&#39;t used is kept out.
And once they&#39;ve settled on the minimum data set
for the next two-year period,
it is signed off by the Minister of Health.
Another strategy we have is daily data capturing.
We refer to it as DDC,
and it takes place at service point level.
The reason why we introduce daily data capturing
is because what we found
when the auditors audited the information system
in South Africa,
which is part of the legal requirements in the country,
they don&#39;t only look at finances,
they look at your information as well,
and what they found was that the majority of the areas
that they found between the source documents and DHIS
were related to the correlation of data
much more so than with the capturing of that data.
So daily data capturing involves setting up,
I&#39;ll give you an example, a clinic.
Each of the consulting rooms in the clinic
where data is collected is then set up at level six
in the org unit hierarchy in DHIS.
And the data capture will then capture on a daily basis,
for that service point,
the data in their data collection tool.
It is not put into a summary form in a way.
It is captured directly from the data collection tools
into the database.
And in this way, we cut out the codation errors.
We also use standardized public dashboards
of which three are devoted to data quality.
And I&#39;ll talk to this a little bit later on.
Another strategy is to apply legends to our indicators.
We use robotized colors to show performance,
and then we also color code blue for any unlikely values
so that they stick out from a data quality point of view.
For data quality, we&#39;ve also developed two HTML reports.
One monitors the timeliness and completeness
prior to deadlines.
I will give you an example.
I will show you an example of this report a little later.
And also we have the element reporting rate
for our community outreach services.
It is the only service
where we were able to really look in detail
at element reporting rate
rather than finding other means
of trying to monitor completeness.
Then we have the pre-submission reports,
as I mentioned earlier,
that are in that standardized template.
And these pre-submission reports also meet the requirement
from the DHMIS,
District Health Management Information Systems, policy,
which requires the higher level to give feedback
to the lower level
within five days of them receiving the data.
We do a monthly data quality report
that is sent to the National Department of Health.
And this gives an overview of the data quality
within the DHIS for the reporting period.
And another strategy is that we do
rapid internal performance data audit,
where we compare source data with the values in the DHIS.
This mimics what the Auditor General of South Africa
would be doing when they visit facilities to audit.
So what do we measure?
We measure timeliness and completeness
by using the flagging,
clicking on the Complete button after data entry
of a particular data set.
So basically what we do is we have the number of data sets
that are assigned to the facility
and then when that data set has been completed
in the data entry screen by the 10th of the month,
it is considered to be timely.
That&#39;s the 10th of the month following the reporting month.
And completeness is the same measurement, but in this case,
it is by the 30th of the month.
Obviously these are the proxies
for timeliness and completeness
because it is dependent on
people clicking on the Complete button.
And I could do that
without necessarily completing all the data
within the data set, or alternatively, they could forget
to click on the Complete button.
So it looks as though they haven&#39;t captured the data
when they have.
So in addition to these two,
we have program completeness,
and for program completeness,
what we do is we have selected proxy data elements
from each of the programs that are in the data sets,
and these are flagged.
And we also look at the number of facilities
that are expected to report on those proxy data elements.
And from this, we calculate the program completeness.
Also not an ideal method of measuring completeness,
but at least it gives an indication
that at least one of the data elements
has been captured for each program.
And the assumption is if they&#39;ve captured that one,
the likelihood is that they have been providing that service
and are reporting on it.
The ideal, of course, is to have an element reporting rate
with customized data sets.
At this stage, we only do that
for the community outreach services
because it is a defined data set
which every single outreach service is expected to report on
every single data element.
As opposed to the program reporting rate
where you don&#39;t have the customized data sets
and you may have a facility that does not necessarily need
to report on all the data elements that are in the data sets
that have been assigned to them.
We do missing and outlier analysis using the WH app.
And we do run validation rule reports
to pick up the violations as well.
So I said earlier
I would talk to the data quality dashboards,
the three that we have.
The one is called the Data Quality dashboard,
and it is like an overview
of the various data quality measures
that we have in the system.
And then we have two other dashboards
that are specific for use
at the lowest level of the hierarchy,
and that is the Daily Data Capturing monitoring one
and the Data Quality monitoring.
The Daily Data Capturing monitoring one
is so that the managers can assess
whether the data at the daily data capturing site
is being captured on a daily basis
and not left for a week, two weeks, a month,
and then back captured,
because that would defeat the whole purpose
of trying to improve data quality using daily capturing.
And the Data Quality monitoring one
is really just used to be able to check on
those types of data elements
that are not suitable to check on
from a data quality perspective using validation rules.
They don&#39;t fit the setup of the validation rules.
So the data quality dashboard has, as I said,
like an overview of the data quality,
and this is an example.
So we have a favorite that monitors the overall timeliness.
This example is timeliness for the whole country.
A province would obviously see the same thing
for their specific province.
And we have the one for completeness.
Then we look at the country as a whole
over a 12-month period to monitor it over time.
And then we also look for the country
at each specific province in the country
for the last three months.
If you look at these two dashboards, we read them together.
So this is the raw data that makes up the timeliness rate
and the raw data that makes up the completeness rate.
And you can see we use category option combos
for which data sets were actually completed
over which data sets were assigned to the country
in that particular month.
So we look at it over a six-month period,
and you can see the examples here
of how we use legend sets
even for our data quality indicators,
where green is we&#39;re happy
that they are completed on time.
The orange would represent that they need to improve,
and the red would mean that they&#39;re critical
and they need to pay attention to this.
I also said earlier I would show you an example
of our HTML report that we use
for timeliness and completeness.
Once you&#39;ve selected your period and your org unit,
it will give you a summary here
of the reports that are expected,
the number that are compliant,
and the number that are non-compliant.
You can then go and look at it in depth
by clicking on this button to hide the compliant
and just focus on those that are not compliant.
You can also go and filter on any of these columns
to refine your search.
And you will see the expected reports for a given facility
or a given data set,
or even a given service point,
and who actually completed and completed on time.
And then you can go and follow up on these facilities
before the due date to make sure.
So before the 10th of the month we focus on timeliness
and highlight to the district, sub-districts, facilities,
which facilities have still not completed before the 10th.
And we cut our losses after the 10th.
And then we focus on the ones that haven&#39;t completed
to try and at least get them to complete
before the 30th of the month.
This is an example of the program reporting rate,
which is on the Data Quality dashboard.
You can see that the levels of program reporting completed
are pretty high.
Our standard is that we expect 99.5% completeness
of that particular proxy data element.
And if they have any less than that,
they are highlighted for action.
And then this is the element reporting rate HTML report
that is used for the outreach teams.
Once you&#39;ve generated the report,
it will give you a summary of the compliance
for the particular level that you drew the report for.
In this case, it was for the provincial level.
And 94% of the facilities...
94% of the data elements that should have been reported on
were reported on.
You can then further go and look at it by facility
to see which of your facilities were the ones
that stopped you from getting your 100%.
This was done over a three-month period.
And you can see this facility
did not submit everything in April,
and this one in May,
and these two just didn&#39;t submit their reports
at all for May.
You can then also go and look at it
per data element to see which of the data elements
were the ones that were not completed on time.
And obviously in this case,
all of the data elements were not completely captured
by every facility.
And it was a result of these two zeros in May.
Then we did the missing and outlier analysis
for our pre-submission data validation.
We do a comprehensive missing and outlier analysis,
and that is put into the pre-submission template
as an annexure.
And it is submitted to the lower level
for action on the missing data
and to deal with the outliers.
But in the data quality report that we do
for the National Department of Health,
we have selected the priority indicators for the country,
and we really just focus on the worst 15 facilities
over the 12-month period under review,
just to give an indication
of how that particular priority program is performing
and how bad the missing and outliers are.
Then for the validation rule violations,
this we really only do
as part of our pre-submission data validation.
This is an example extracted from
the pre-submission data validation template.
And for each of the areas that we assess,
it follows the same principle, but in this case,
it&#39;s for validation rules
where you explain what the validation rule analysis is about
and why we do it.
Then you look at where it can be found.
And then we explain how you run the report.
And finally, we give an instruction
on how this report should be downloaded
and saved as an annexure in the pre-submission template
that goes back to the lower level for feedback.
For training and guidelines,
we do have an online training for daily data capturing
that is fairly popular.
And for this there is a learning manual
explaining what it&#39;s about,
why we do it, how we do it, et cetera.
We also have a data quality module
in our DHIS2 foundation course with its learner manual.
And we have a specific guideline for dashboard maintenance
because it is so important that the dashboards
are kept up to date in order for them to be relevant
for the use of that information
and to monitor the data quality that we have.
So we like them to be current,
and so they are maintained on a monthly basis.
And with every (indistinct) review,
these guidelines are also reviewed
to add in any new data elements,
indicators that have been selected
and to remove anything that is no longer relevant.
I&#39;m now going to just show you a few slides
on the progress we&#39;ve made over the years
since we introduced DHIS2.
This is with daily data capturing.
Obviously South Africa does have the same limitations
as many of the other countries in Africa,
and perhaps some of the Eastern countries,
where we have challenges with connectivity
at our facility level.
So when we started daily capturing 16/17 financial year,
we have made steady progress through the years,
and we&#39;re currently at 44% at now year that has just ended,
the 19/20 year.
But there&#39;s ongoing pressure
to get more and more facilities capturing daily.
And so there is work being done
on trying to improve the connectivity at facilities,
but it is a limiting factor.
Our progress with our timeliness and completeness.
We started at around 39% for timeliness
and we&#39;re currently around 76%.
And for completeness, we started around 52%,
and we&#39;re now at just on 90% for that.
For program reporting, you can see that in 17/18
we really had no one on target
and it was a lot better in 18/19.
And then in 19/20 we had a lot more of the green.
So just to conclude then,
we have obviously made considerable progress
with improving data quality since we introduced DHIS,
both DHIS1 and DHIS2.
But maybe the take home message is that
really it is very important to do monthly monitoring
and reporting on data quality.
Otherwise it tends to stagnate and sit at a certain level
or even regress.
So we are constantly looking at our data quality,
monitoring it on a monthly basis,
and thinking of new ways to measure our data quality,
or improve the measures that we do have in the system.
And so that&#39;s it from South Africa. Thank you very much.
- [Moderator] Thank you so much, Jenny.
That was a really wonderful presentation. Really clear.
I would like to invite anyone from the.