- [Narrator] So let&#39;s, let&#39;s go to the numerator group page
and take a look at that.
What we have here are the default numerator groups,
general service statistics.
You see how number of physicians has been added to it
and then various programs.
And notice these buttons.
So, just as we can add a numerator,
we can add a numerator group,
and that&#39;s what I&#39;m going to do.
Um, I hope by the end of the session,
we&#39;ll get uh, get around to talking about
how the tool can be used at district level routinely.
And for that, of course, at district level,
they, they might use Core,
that we&#39;ve discussed before,
or you might actually create a group
just for the district.
In fact, there might be multiple groups
for the district so that it, uh
the district could have a tailored group
that it was looking at the indicators
that it felt were most important.
Of course, to do that
they would have to work with
the national data administrator.
But you could imagine, uh,
that being worked out.
The district is not going to have
the access to configure the tool,
but you could imagine them working
with the national data administrator to add
a group just for their district.
But what I&#39;m going to add now
is the group called Human Resources.
(typing)
- [Narrator] Should have done better
in high school typing class,
but anyway, uh, okay.
So, we have now the group here, but it&#39;s empty.
So we&#39;re going to add to that.
Scroll down and find what we&#39;ve just configured.
Number of Physicians.
Now you might think that it&#39;s been added,
but you&#39;ve got to take one more step.
This is actually not in the group yet.
It&#39;s just been selected from the dropdown menu.
So we have to click on that.
And finally, it&#39;s in the, uh
it&#39;s in the Human Resources group.
But let&#39;s go back to numerators.
So now, if you look at, uh,
this new reference numerator,
you see it&#39;s in two groups.
It&#39;s in the General Service Statistics,
and it&#39;s also in the Human Resources group.
And on the dashboard,
since we&#39;ve added a new group,
we now have that in the dropdown menu,
that in the settings window of the dropdown menu,
we can select Human Resources.
And for some reason,
the completeness of the staffing data set
isn&#39;t appearing.
Let me see if there&#39;s something more
that has to be done.
Yeah, somehow I didn&#39;t, notice here,
the dataset hasn&#39;t appeared
and every once in a while the, this happens.
And if you don&#39;t see
the completeness on the dashboard,
go back to configuration,
to administration and see if the data set is there.
I think I have, what I have to do is redo this.
Can&#39;t explain to you why it doesn&#39;t,
hasn&#39;t appeared.
Cause I thought I selected data staffing,
data set, but,
maybe not.
Um, Okay. Dataset for completeness.
Let&#39;s see if we can get this app.
Okay.
So now we&#39;ve got the data set in there
and if we go back to the dashboard,
we can select our Human Resources group,
there, there we are.
It&#39;s, and as is typical,
we&#39;ve got a pretty low reporting rate.
Um, oh these are, by the way,
this is kind of a strange thing
to put on the dashboard because
the HR data is probably reported only annually.
And uh, so you can&#39;t, for example,
with, with only annual data,
uh, look at, um, you see no data return.
And the reason is,
there&#39;s no monthly data on, on staffing.
I think, I think you could,
in the analysis function,
you could set that, I&#39;m getting sidetracked,
but it&#39;s sometimes useful to think about
how you would look at data that is
quarterly or annual.
You&#39;ve got the option in analysis
to set the periods to, uh,
you could in theory get custom
that&#39;s how you&#39;d do it, I think.
Uh, multiple,
you could look at multiple years for outliers,
but seldom do you have multiple years of the,
of the human resource data, but okay.
Back to, uh, the numerator configuration,
I&#39;m gonna pause there.
So, so far we&#39;ve, we&#39;ve talked about
how to fill in the main table
and the role of numerator groups
and how to add a numerator group.
You could also remove it from a numerator group.
I&#39;m going to remove Physicians from
General Service Statistics.
And now it&#39;s only in the Human Resources.
Uh, yeah okay, now, and
General Service Statistics, where are we?
There we are. Okay.
You could also,
if you decide that you don&#39;t want
the menu to be so full,
if you look here after a while,
after you&#39;ve added a whole bunch of uh,
of groups, you, you have a pretty full menu
and you might want to simply
remove a group that,
that is not on the dashboard.
So you can also do that.
You can delete a group
that has no, uh, has no numerators,
which you want to put on the, on the dashboard.