- Move on to numerator relations,
this numerator relations, what is numerator relations?
This is configuring what appears on consistency data.
And we already have a couple of things. Actually,
I&#39;m going to remove one of these so that I can show you
how it&#39;s done.
Um, so for now on numerator relations,
we only have the DPT one to three dropout rates.
That&#39;s all that&#39;s configured so far.
And if we look at the numerator relations page,
it comes with some defaults,
some default comparisons that the WHO recommends looking at,
for example,
comparing the first visit for anti-natal care to the first
dose of tetanus toxoid, or here is the first dose of,
of SP for preventive therapy for malaria in pregnancy.
And one of the comparators that they recommend is the DPT
one to three dropout rate.
Notice how this is already filled in for you.
So the tool will automatically complete parts of the
numerator relations page.
If you have already configured numerator A and numerator B,
which, which we have.
So I haven&#39;t done anything to fill this in.
The tool has automatically filled this in.
You should check that it has done it correctly because
sometimes it, it misinterprets.
And then you, as we,
as we have seen on the dashboard that the dropout rate will
appear automatically.
So I&#39;m going to try to add this one
antenatal care compared to first visit for anti-natal care,
compared to the first dose of SP for IPT.
And when we, when we try to fill in the form, you see here,
here&#39;s the comparison, the type A is about equal B.
Well,
we can also select A is greater than B because often they,
not,
every woman is going to get SP for various reasons during
their first antenatal care visits or,
or even some subsequent visits that the first numerator has
been filled in automatically.
But then when we try to find the, the comparison numerator,
we look down the list and it&#39;s not there.
So you, what you have to do is,
is actually configure IPT one.
And fortunately there is in the ANC group,
there&#39;s a IPT first dose,
given at the primary health care units.
So once we configure this,
then the tool, when we go back to numerator relations,
it&#39;s automatically filled in and you can add things.
One that I like to add.
It&#39;s an interesting one.
If you think about it
ANC one compared to DPT one.
So how many of the pregnancies that present for their first
antenatal care visit go on to get their first dose of
DPT.
And let&#39;s say, choose A equals B.
We&#39;ve got short lists because we&#39;ve only configured a small
number of numerators,
and we&#39;re going to compare that and save it.
In fact,
I&#39;ll go back now and see what the dashboard looks like,
but having done that, you,
you see the table that that row of the table is filled in.
And now when we go to consistency data,
we&#39;ve got three different comparisons.
Remember our advice from the last session,
that&#39;s as interesting as it is to compare two different data
elements. This is the function of the data quality tool,
which is most demanding of the backend. And it slows down.
Sometimes this page will not load
It won&#39;t render and you&#39;ll find yourself waiting for a long
time. So it may be best if you find the page,
not loading to limit the data consistency to just a couple
of data comparisons,
but here&#39;s comparing,
here&#39;s the one we added.
Well, we added this one
and you see there&#39;s fairly good comparison.
And we added this one.
So indeed ANC1 does have a almost linear
relationship to first dose of Pinta vaccine.
Again, this, the only reason this works is because we,
we discussed yesterday, the idea of a steady state,
and this works because the number of pregnancies tends to be
roughly constant over time.
And if you have high levels of antenatal care coverage,
then most,
every pregnancy leads to a first antenatal care visits.
Most pregnancies result in a live birth.
And if you&#39;ve got high coverage with Pinta 1,
most live births received their first dose of Pinta
vaccine.
So this is always reassuring to see this kind of comparison.
And it works only if you&#39;ve got pretty high data quality,
pretty complete data, a few outliers,
high levels of coverage with antenatal care and
immunization.
And it&#39;s a fairly robust assessment of the quality of the
data system when you&#39;ve got this, this linear relationship.
But obviously there are some exceptions.
Let me again, I encourage anyone to raise their hand.
If you want me to pause, I, if not,
I&#39;m going to cover these thresholds.
Notice how tight the, the thresholds are here.
This is plus 10%. This is minus 10%.
And when the thresholds are so tight,
you&#39;ve got a large number of districts which have diamond
shaped dots because they fall outside of plus or minus 10%.
So,
and even this one where antenatal care is one is pretty
close to Pinta one.
And maybe we don&#39;t want to identify this as being a
suspicious value.
We want to accept districts that have at least this,
dot that is at least this close to the reference line.