(upbeat music)
- [Bob] I&#39;m going to share with you
something called the WHO&#39;s framework
for data quality review.
This is an approach to assessing
the quality of the data,
which are routinely reported
by health facilities each month.
There are a variety of tools
that you may be familiar with for assessing data quality.
Here are several of them.
WHO has a data quality review tool kit
that you can access using this web link.
We will provide you with these PowerPoint slides
and later, perhaps, you can browse this website
and even download the three documents
that describe in greater detail
the WHO data quality review framework.
To begin with, we should say something
about the frequency of data quality review.
This assessment of the quality of data
could take place at various frequencies.
It could be monthly, and this is going to be a large
part of the focus of this workshop,
how staff at health facility
and district level could routinely,
that is monthly, assess data quality.
On the other hand, at a national level,
there should be a process that is at least once each year,
perhaps just before the annual health summit,
the annual review of progress
against the core indicators
to assure the quality of data
before they are interpreted for the annual review.
And then in the longer run
certain specific health programs,
such as the immunization program or the HIV/AIDS program,
might have every three to five years
of more in-depth program specific review.
There are two principle methods
for assessing the quality of routine data.
The first involves surveys,
or at least, a supervisory visit
it requires a visit to the health facility
to examine the facility registers,
recount the data and compare
that recounts of data with the data
that have been recorded
and reported on the monthly report.
This type of visit to the health facility
allows the surveyor or the supervisor
to as well collect information
about such things as the availability of staff
or the presence of standard operating procedures,
or whether there are sufficient numbers
of reporting formats available,
and the supervisor or surveyor can examine
the health facility or the district health office
to see evidence of use of data,
visualization of data.
Now, with all of these advantages
of a data verification survey,
or a visit to the health facility,
it has to be acknowledged that it is expensive
it requires travel.
And for this reason such an approach is often infrequent.
And sometimes it is applied
only to a sample of health facilities
or a sample of districts.
On the other hand, there&#39;s the other approach
which we referred to as the data desk review.
And that&#39;s going to be the main focus of this workshop.
No travel is required.
It&#39;s called a desk review
&#39;cause it can be done from the office
where the data base is maintained.
If someone has access to the DHIS2 instance,
then they can undertake a review,
not just occasionally,
but it can be done monthly.
It&#39;s practical to do this
and not just for a sample of health facilities,
but the review can look at the data
for all health facilities nationwide.
And if the right tools are installed in the DHIS2,
then this desk review is able to actually drill down
and that is investigate at a lower level
and find out were there any suspicious data
have been reporting from.
(upbeat music)