- [Instructor] So another issue that you might find
is dealing with data dimensions.
So there are really three areas that you can define
what&#39;s a data dimension
to be used in analytics ops in DHIS2.
This includes our categories,
category option group sets,
and our organization unit group sets.
This all affects what is essentially the left side menu
that users see when they&#39;re performing analysis
on various items in these apps.
And if this becomes so large that people cannot
make heads or tails of what they&#39;re seeing,
then it&#39;s not really kind of being used
in the way it should be.
The whole idea is that we want these dimensions
to be present so people can drill down,
can desegregate their data in the way that&#39;s necessary
to support their analysis requirements.
If they&#39;re not able to find what they need,
this is going to have some impact on
how they actually utilize the system itself.
So it can affect data quality,
but this is also a bit of a user issue as well
in terms of what they&#39;re seeing.
And if this list, in this example here,
that you can see there&#39;s kind of top and bottoms
to this list, but I can keep scrolling down
and more and more would be there.
So one way to do this obviously is if you&#39;re sharing
and we&#39;ll talk a bit about sharing more,
but you can choose to share
which data dimensions people see.
So they&#39;re not seeing everything.
They&#39;re only seeing the ones that are relevant to them.
But one of the main problems with DHIS2
is that for all three of these items, categories,
category option group sets,
and organization unit group sets,
they have this data dimension checkbox ticked by default.
So anytime I go to create a new one,
it&#39;s just going to appear on that menu,
and it&#39;s going to get larger and larger and larger
until it&#39;s basically I cannot navigate or find anything
that I need, or at least not easily,
unless I really know the system well.
So, one thing that I often like to do
is make sure to incorporate whether or not to select this
in a data dimension.
So that&#39;s standard operating procedure
that I shared with you.
We&#39;ll just go back to that real quick.
I made sure that I highlight that you have to decide
whether or not you should use a data dimension
for that particular item that you&#39;re creating.
Because if not, if you just go to create a new category
or an organization unit group set,
or a category option group set,
it&#39;s going to add it to that left menu.
And this is going to cause some challenges
with the ability to find what you need
in order to analyze your data correctly.
Another challenge that we might see related to system design
and data quality is when we find a lot of
duplicate data elements.
So just in this example here,
I have a number of duplicate data elements
that are storing or representing,
I should say, the same item.
They&#39;re all about maternal deaths.
Every single one of these items that I see here
is related to maternal deaths.
And in fact, it&#39;s just representing the same,
basically the same concept.
So what do I do in this scenario?
Now, this is a bit more complicated
because these different data elements
can belong to different programs.
They might belong to the same program.
It might be reported a couple of different times
in the same system, but they might belong to different
programs as well.
And the challenge here is that different programs
will then be reporting different values potentially.
And you&#39;re not actually sure then in this scenario,
what is the source?
What is the source of truth for this particular data item?
You don&#39;t really know when there&#39;s so many different values
that represent the same concept.
You can kind of pick and choose,
and programs kind of do this because they&#39;re stuck with
the item that they&#39;re really the ones responsible for
or feel they&#39;re responsible for.
But in an integrated system,
this is not really the best approach.
So this is more a measure to identify this problem.
I can&#39;t say I have an immediate solution
for rectifying this issue,
because this is not something that can be done quickly.
You cannot just take all these data elements
and collapse them.
You&#39;re gonna have all kinds of different values.
Potentially you&#39;re gonna have different programs
that are responsible for kind of maintaining these as well.
So there&#39;s not an easy workaround that I personally
can recommend to you on this,
but this is just something that you really should look for
and try to help over time countries and other partners
fix this type of issue.
Because this becomes very challenging to deal with
from a data quality point of view
when you&#39;re no longer sure what the actual value is
for the item that you&#39;re looking to analyze.