- [Instructor] So, I&#39;ve brought up
a lot of different issues
that are potential challenges
dealing with system design
and resulting in poor data quality,
and also just frustration in terms of creating
our data outputs.
There are a number of different ways
we can actually review a lot of these issues.
And I think I&#39;ve touched upon
kind of identification of a number of these problems.
A lot of them are just manual processes
where we&#39;re looking at things
like trying to find problems with our forms,
trying to see if there are duplicate categories,
if there are duplicate data elements,
things of that nature.
So it&#39;s just kind of keeping a sense of our system,
mapping it out.
What might help in terms of eating these manual processes
is having a kind of mapping a layout of our system.
Things like data dictionaries,
for example, are kind of immensely helpful
in performing this type of manual review
and identifying if there is all kinds of issues
with desegregations and data elements
across our different programs,
whether it be for tracker or for aggregate data.
Now, if these are in place,
then it makes manual review of these systems a lot easier,
but there are some other things
that we can look at from kind of measuring
a quality perspective and just kind of highlighting
some of these sources of potentially
problematic errors within the system itself.
So we can look at things like the raw number
of data elements, indicators, and data sets,
and just kind of make counts
of this to see if this is in line
with what we would expect based upon
the different pieces of information that are collected.
We can also look at poorly defined metadata.
So I&#39;m going to share with you a document
on naming conventions that was written
for the WHO digital data packages.
And this is just to give you a flavor
for where you might want to institute
some naming conventions in the location
that you&#39;re working with.
This is something we can also have some effect
on as we can help people to do bulk updates of the names,
which is really difficult
through the DHIS2 user interface.
Once again, something like a data dictionary
would also be very helpful here
if it&#39;s available because things like definitions
and descriptions can be taken directly
from those data dictionaries
and added to our descriptions in DHIS2.
So if we want to see if two objects
are actually the same, we can refer back
to the description and seeing,
in order to see if this is actually representing
the same item and if they need to be collapsed
later on eventually.
We can also look at things like metadata duplicates.
And I&#39;ve talked about this already
in quite some detail just by going through
the user interface and trying to identify
if what we&#39;re seeing is duplicated in several places.
Things like indicators, data elements,
and all this stuff around categories
are some examples where we can just kind of go through
the user interface and do some type of assessment.
So we&#39;ll talk about this a little bit more
in terms of the results of this process.
And what we might need to do
when we find a lot of these errors.
We also want to describe some other tools
that could be used to assess DHIS2 design.
And this includes a data integrity checks
and a number of supplemental SQL scripts
that are also available to perform
some initial assessment of the database design.
Now I put here in the loop learning objectives
that we want you to be able to describe
the following only because if you&#39;re not comfortable
running an SQL script, for example,
all you need to know is that there are scripts available
and you can get the output of this
and maybe have one of your team members
kind of help you do these types of things.
So as long as you&#39;re aware
that some of these tools are available,
you can always kind of lean on them
and get someone else to kind of help you
implement them in practice.
So here&#39;s an example of the result
of a manual assessment in a live system.
And one thing that we have to be kind of cognizant of,
that we have to be thinking of,
basically whenever we&#39;re doing these types of reviews
is that there&#39;s often going to be significant pushback.
This type of activity is often difficult to explain,
but there is a huge impact on data quality
as we&#39;ve been discussing over the course
of these various sessions.
So what we see here is a number of metadata items.
And then in the first kind of significant column,
current system, is the actual system as it stands currently,
then what I have in the next box
is expected in new system.
So sometimes we have to actually rebuild
the database, you know?
And this is a big step and it&#39;s a very time consuming step
and it takes a lot of effort and resources to do,
but I wouldn&#39;t shy away necessarily
for making that recommendation.
If it is going to result
in significant usability changes
that would just make the system much easier to use,
make the data quality,
improve the data quality significantly
by collapsing various data elements
and getting the right value for them.
So now you&#39;re aware of what your source data elements are,
you&#39;re aware of what your desegregations are.
You&#39;re able to collapse these to be correct.
And users are only seeing one version
of these data elements,
of these desegregations in their system.
So they know they&#39;re can be confident
that they&#39;re selecting the right value
when they&#39;re making their outputs.
So this can be a bit challenging to go through
and actually come up with the results
and implement the solution,
but actually just going through it
and doing a manual review,
even without kind of saying,
&quot;Okay, now I&#39;m going to actually implement
all of these changes in practice.&quot;
But just being able to identify
some of these things and show people
how this can have an effect
on what they&#39;re doing and maybe ease
some of their frustration by implementing
even some of these bandaid solutions
like category option groups and group sets
that kind of mask things from the user itself
can be hugely beneficial just by going through the system
and kind of having a look at how it&#39;s been built and set up.